<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A miscellany of divers problems containing ingenuous solutions of sundry questions, partly moral, partly of other subjects / translated out of French by Henry Some ...</title>
            <title>Meslange de divers problèmes. English</title>
            <author>Pellisson-Fontanier, Paul, 1624-1693.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1662</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 249 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 148 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53987</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1108</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R20442</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12355101</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12355101</idno>
            <idno type="VID">60121</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A53987)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 60121)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 220:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A miscellany of divers problems containing ingenuous solutions of sundry questions, partly moral, partly of other subjects / translated out of French by Henry Some ...</title>
                  <title>Meslange de divers problèmes. English</title>
                  <author>Pellisson-Fontanier, Paul, 1624-1693.</author>
                  <author>Some, Henry.</author>
                  <author>Thoms, Samuel.</author>
                  <author>Pellisson, Georges, d. 1677.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[58], 227 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Charles Adams and are to be sold at his shop ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1662.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation of: Meslange de divers problèmes.</note>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Samuel Thoms.</note>
                  <note>The dedication states this work to be by P. Pellisson, who wrote the history of the French academy, also translated by Some.</note>
                  <note>Also attributed to George Pellisson. Cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>First ed. of this translation. Cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Life.</term>
               <term>Questions and answers.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:60121:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:60121:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A <hi>MISCELLANY</hi> OF DIVERS Problems.</p>
            <p>Containing ingenuous Solutions of ſundry Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, partly Moral, part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of other ſubjects.</p>
            <p>Tranſlated out of French by <hi>HENRY SOME,</hi> M. A. late Fellow of the <hi>Kings Colledge</hi> in <hi>Cambridge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Charles Adams,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the ſign of the Talbot, near St. <hi>Dunſtans</hi> Church in Fleet-ſtreet, <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1662.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:60121:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:60121:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:60121:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:60121:3"/>
            <head>To the vertuous La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, M<hi rend="sup">ris</hi> 
               <hi>Elizabeth Chaſe,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">ris</hi> 
               <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces Heywood,</hi> and M<hi rend="sup">ris</hi> 
               <hi>Laetitia Briggs,</hi> the three ſiſters of his dear friend Mr. <hi>H. Some.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Vertuous Ladies,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WHereas <hi>common and low ſpirits,</hi> might ſuſpect this action, as a
<pb facs="tcp:60121:4"/>
deſign to renew a paſt ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, ſeeing me, after a year of mourning, recall the memory of ſo ſad a loſs: I know, <hi>your more generous ſouls,</hi> will rather interpret my intent, an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to allay your too long grief, when I revive the memory of a <hi>dear dead Brother:</hi> Since your rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, being ſo near of kind to his, cannot but judge it a weakneſs, to preferr the <hi>paſsion</hi> of an <hi>uſeleſs ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row,</hi> above the <hi>merit</hi> of a <hi>pious gratitude.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:60121:4"/>And yet conſidering, that others will be ſo par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial, as to blame, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever their fancies do not approve: I muſt forbear to heighten the cauſe of ſadneſs, by recounting the particulars of your loſs; only I would fain begg your leaves, to acquaint the world, that in <hi>this</hi> they and you are partners. But how ſhall I effect that? ſince experience hath now taught the vulgar, what was formerly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved to the knowledge
<pb facs="tcp:60121:5"/>
of the more prudent; That the commendation of our friend is frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly but the cloak of a ſelf-conceited folly: And the world having been of late ſo much abuſed by hypocriſie, is now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſuſpicious even of vertue, if once recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended; eſpecially by a perſon, whoſe obſcurity leaves him lyable to their cenſure. However the love of goodneſs, the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation of friendſhip, and conſciouſneſs of truth,
<pb facs="tcp:60121:5"/>
ſhall prevail with me to the hazard of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute</p>
            <p>I ſhould indeed, both betray an high folly in my ſelf, and injure the worth of my Friend, ſhould I, conſidering my own diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ability, undertake to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe at large of all his merits; and yet thus much I cannot but ſay, his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuous diſcourſe, his modeſt deportment, his humility and candour, gained a more then or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary
<pb facs="tcp:60121:6"/>
reſpect from all that ever he converſed with, and this they ſhall witneſs for me: They that had the happy op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity of knowing him more throughly, found his Learning ſo great, and communicat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with that freeneſs; his piety ſo true, and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed with that inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, that they could not but love him with admiration, which alſo increaſed in thoſe that had a more ſpecial and
<pb facs="tcp:60121:6"/>
conſtant intimacy with him; for ſuch knew him ſo paſsionate a Lover of all ingenuous Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that he ever count<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that hour loſt, which was not imployed in ſome kind or other of it. He hated naught ſo much as idleneſs, or doing no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and that made his very recreations, as ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous as others ſtudies. And this gave him the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of being skilled in modern languages: which although he attained unto,
<pb facs="tcp:60121:7"/>
by a ſagacity proper to his diſpoſition, and his own induſtry, yet his courteſie would afterwards enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain diſcourſe with the common Tutors and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed Teachers of them upon all emergent occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. This his true love to Learning, gave our Nation the opportunity of knowing the Nature and Conſtitution of the new Famous French Academy, by his tranſlation of their Hiſtory, written by <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur P. Pelliſon,</hi> which
<pb facs="tcp:60121:7"/>
was a thing ſo acceptable to the Author, that he was pleaſed to write him a particular acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and communicate to him alſo this preſent <hi>Treatiſe,</hi> which likewiſe at times of divertiſement he taught to ſpeak Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh: In the peruſal of which, I doubt not but the more ingenuous will reap ſatisfaction, and find ſufficient cauſe to love the <hi>Tranſlators</hi> memory, if they conſider that it is not offered as a part of his
<pb facs="tcp:60121:8"/>
more ſolid labours, but as a valuable Eſſay of wit, and to be uſed as it was made, only in a Diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
            <p>That which I offer to you, <hi>worthy Ladies,</hi> I give not as <hi>a Preſent,</hi> but repay <hi>as a due,</hi> which without injuſtice I cannot detain; a greater reaſon, then that which engageth me to a publication, entituling you to the right of Patronage: For the memory of a dear friendſhip cannot herein
<pb facs="tcp:60121:8"/>
challenge any thing from me, but what the intereſt of a nearer relation makes entirely yours, and toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with it, the Devoirs of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt humble ſervant, <hi>Samuel Thoms.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Cambridge,</hi>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Jan.</hi> 10. 1661.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:60121:9"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:60121:9"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Conceive it would be rather preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in me than humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, if before you come to read what I here preſent you, I ſhould not give an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of ſome things that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect
<pb facs="tcp:60121:10"/>
my deſign, and the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of theſe <hi>Problems,</hi> which may occaſion you either to bear with their faults, or to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn them with the more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and juſtice. In the firſt place, ſeeing me alledge com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly many ſeveral reaſons of the Queſtions I handle, you may poſſibly deſire to know, Whether I propound part of them to exerciſe my wit, and to beautifie my work, like an Oratour, that ſaies not only all he believes to be true, or like truth, but alſo all that he thinks advantagious to his cauſe. To this, Reader, let me tell you, that in ſome places indeed, the obſcurity of my matter hath given me licence to make bold conjectures, and ſuch as ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb facs="tcp:60121:10"/>
to me more likely to add Beauty than Light to my work: But that theſe places are very rare, and that everywhere elſe I have laboured to give only ſolid reaſons, and have alledged many of them, becauſe having conſidered my matter many wayes, and at ſeveral diſtances, I thought they might be all true. Some indeed may here ſay, that it is not very likely that one and the ſame effect ſhould have ſuch different cauſes, for commonly when we think we have found one ſolid cauſe of an effect, this makes us deſpiſe all others, and we are apt for this reaſon to eſteem them vain and frivilous. But, Reader, I am not of this judgement, nay on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb facs="tcp:60121:11"/>
do think, that when we diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe upon an effect, we ſhould ſcarce ever content our ſelves with <hi>one</hi> good and true cauſe of it alone, becauſe every conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable effect hath <hi>many</hi> cauſes which contribute to its gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deur, as all Rivers are formed by the uniting of ſeveral brooks, and many petty rivu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>letts. This is very evident of its ſelf in ſome kind of things; as for example, That which caſts a man into a diſeaſe, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be alwayes one ſole cauſe, but many cauſes united; ſo when the Queſtion is to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of the ruine of a State, it is clear, that it will never be ſufficient to think of finding one ſolid reaſon only, becauſe it alwayes hath many. But
<pb facs="tcp:60121:11"/>
though I ſee my ſelf confined within the bounds of a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face, which I am afraid to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed too much: yet I will in ſome ſort ſhew you, as much as the brevity which I ſtudy will ſuffer me, that this is no leſs true in regard of our <hi>Paſsions, Actions and Humours,</hi> which are the matters the greateſt part of this book is compoſed of. Firſt, for our Actions, and the particular and ordinary mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of our mind, I may ſay that all our Paſſions do there appear together alwayes, and act their parts there, though it be not alwayes after the ſame faſhion: juſt as in each Come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy that is acted, they are the ſame Actors that appear upon the Stage, though they do not
<pb facs="tcp:60121:12"/>
there repreſent the ſame per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. And as they ſay that no Element ever appears to us in its purity, that is entirely ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated from others, and void of all mixtures; I conceive alſo that after the very ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, not one of our ordinary Paſſions, which are as it were the Principles and Elements of our manners, doth ever ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in its purity, and without ſome mixture of the others: ſo that by this means it ſcarce ever happens, that it is only one ſpring which moves and actuates our ſpirits. It would be as long as it is eaſie to prove this by abundance of examples; but I ſhall content my ſelf to alledge ſome of them. If it be demanded,
<pb facs="tcp:60121:12"/>
               <hi>Why we deſire glory?</hi> It is, without queſtion, (to give one ſolid reaſon of it) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we look upon it as a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Life, and that we think our Being is amplified and extended according as our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nown ſpreads very far, and as we are known to many men; but for all this, if there be not another cauſe given, we ſhall not very well ſatisfie this demand: For it is very evident, that we deſire it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, becauſe the good opinion that others have of our excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency, fortifies and upholds the opinion which we have of it our ſelves. Beſides, we do without doubt deſire to gain Eſteem, becauſe it is a way to make us be beloved, and that
<pb facs="tcp:60121:13"/>
we deſire to be beloved; nay farther we wiſh it, both for its own ſake (becauſe there is a natural ſweetneſs in being be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved, and that none of the leaſt) and for the convenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that come by it. Even ſo too, if a man enquires, <hi>Why we revenge our ſelves?</hi> he will preſently find that we do it for divers ſeveral cauſes, which come from different re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects. For it is partly becauſe pretending that the injury re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived hath caſt us down, we labour to raiſe our ſelves up again, by making him repent that did it. And partly, we do not deſire only to make him repent, but we think alſo that we diſcharge our ſelves in ſome ſort of the hurt we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived
<pb facs="tcp:60121:13"/>
from him, in making him ſuffer as much. As we ſee that children think to free themſelves of a kiſs which one hath given them by force, in re-kiſſing him from whom they have received it, and ſay they will give it back to be rid of it themſelves. Partly alſo, (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out having any regard to the thing in its ſelf) we revenge our ſelves for the opinion of others, and for fear one ſhould come to think that we had not power or credit enough to do it: Beſides this, we do it out of Fear for the future, and to the end that he which hath offended us, may not preſume to do ſo any more; (For though this be not formally the deſire of Revenge, certain it is that
<pb facs="tcp:60121:14"/>
it alwayes contributes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto:) And laſtly, we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge our ſelves, becauſe that, as the ſhaking of Fear ceaſes not ſo ſoon as the danger is over; ſo the hurt we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, hath left in us a blind impreſſion of hatred which laſts ſtill after that is paſt, and hath only its ſelf for the reaſon of its ſelf. If we ſhould now examine the motion of the ſoul in <hi>Love,</hi> we ſhould find in it a ſtranger mixture of all ſorts of Cauſes, Natural and Moral, Corporal and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual. In a word, we ſhould as eaſily find that it is the ſame with all the other ordinary and extraordinary humours of our minds; I mean, that there is not any of them that hath one
<pb facs="tcp:60121:14"/>
only ſource, and that they have alwayes many roots, ſome whereof look backward, and ſome forward, ſome to the right hand, others to the left; nay we ſhould find they have almoſt alwayes quite contrary cauſes, ſince that moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly they come to us partly from ſtrength and partly from weakneſs, partly from reaſon and partly from blindneſs; and that they almoſt alwayes ſhew both ſome perfection and ſome imperfection both at once.</p>
            <p>Behold, Reader, the firſt thing I was to ſpeak to you of, upon which I have, it may be, inſiſted too long. Paſs we now to that which remains with all poſſible brevity. Some of my friends, whoſe leaſt advice
<pb facs="tcp:60121:15"/>
weighs much with me, coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelled me not to forget in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral places of this Book, ſome reaſons that are common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly given upon the Queſtions I here handle, for fear leaſt I ſeem to be ignorant of them. But I told them that this might breed in you a great diſlike; and that beſides, though thoſe cauſes which are vulgarly given of divers Queſtions, are many times very good, yet are they more often ſuperficial, or at leaſt not the principal; and this in my opinion proceeds from hence, that the vulgar hath the common ſenſe much better than its underſtanding; and that by this means it ſees in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed well enough with a ſingle eye the things that touch the
<pb facs="tcp:60121:15"/>
common ſenſe, but is much leſs able to give the reaſons of them, or diſcovers ordinarily only the ſhalloweſt. This I told them for mine own juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation; and after they had heard me, they believed it was ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient that I alledge theſe vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar reaſons, when it is altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther neceſſary to do ſo, and that I ſhould here acquaint you, that I have ſlighted many others, or for fear of rendring my ſelf te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious, I would not alledge them all.</p>
            <p>Moreover, I have formed the moſt part of theſe <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blems</hi> in a very conciſe and ſuccinct manner, and by way of Queſtion, in imitation of ſeveral antient Philoſophers, and that I might comprehend
<pb facs="tcp:60121:16"/>
the more things in fewer words. But becauſe a conciſe and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinct reaſon, which ſtr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>kes the mind ſuddainly, ſeems at firſt to be more acute and gentle, than ſolid and profound; and becauſe I know that people judge often enough of things, as of men, by their countenance and habit: I was not willing to tie my ſelf alwayes to this me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, and have many times vented my reaſons after a more Dogmatical and poſitive man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and made my diſcourſe a little more diffuſe. Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, I hope that in judging the whole work in groſs, you will acknowledge to me that I could not have allowed leſs room to theſe meditations which I here offer you, and that I had not a
<pb facs="tcp:60121:16"/>
deſign to make you loſe in the reading of my book any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable part of your time, which you ought to imploy bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the three things, Reader, which I deſired to ſpeak to you of; However I do not pretend, by telling you what I have endeavoured to do, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice you in favour of me; I ſay only that I have endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured, and not that I have performed any thing: and on the contrary, to take from you all preoccupation, and to leave your judgement the more free, let me tell you, in putting a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod to this diſcourſe, that I my ſelf am not ſatisfied, whether I have conceived my reaſons with ſufficient ſtrength, whether I
<pb facs="tcp:60121:17"/>
have explained them with grace and clearneſs enough; whether my ſtile be hard or pleaſant; and that I demand your judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: Nay I declare unto you, that I doubt not but there are many faults in this my book; and that thoſe that ſhall think ſo, will be of my opinion. And if ſtill others ſay, that there are more faults than perfections in it, and that I have done nothing which deſerves that you ſhould read and approve it: I ſhall not reply any thing more harſh and ſharp, then that this may very eaſily be, ſince that my ſpirit is ſo imperfect, and that I am not certain they are in the wrong.</p>
            <p>And if you demand, what it is that hath given me the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence to expoſe to your view
<pb facs="tcp:60121:17"/>
this work which I preſent, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the diffidence I have of my own abilities; I ſhall anſwer, that it is on the one ſide a certain Goodneſs and Complacency which ſome per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons Illuſtrious for their worth, and ſuch as I am ſure you know and reverence, have had for it; and on the other ſide, the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream deſire which I had to do ſomewhat that might be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to you; for it is certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Reader, this deſire, more than love of glory, or any hope that I could have conceived to ſee any ſucceſs proceed from my labours that might be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantagious to me, that hath ſweetened whatſoever it could have of pains or trouble in it; and I hope, that if you make
<pb facs="tcp:60121:18"/>
any reckoning of theſe Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophical reflections, wherein I have mingled light matters with important, I may perhaps one day offer you ſome others upon higher ſubjects, from whence you may receive much more profit.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:60121:18"/>
            <head>On the judicious Tranſlator Maſter <hi>Henry Some</hi> late of Ks. Colledge Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, my dear and deceaſed Friend.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>WHat Problems <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> never told,</l>
               <l>Nor <hi>Plutarch,</hi> nor this <hi>Oedipus</hi> unfold,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:60121:19"/>
               <l>Reſolve who can: wherefore im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial Fate</l>
               <l>Of uſefull mens ſhort life contracts the date?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Whence your ſmall Pox more unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenting are</l>
               <l>Towards the High, the Learned and the Fair?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Why fell ſuch loyal expectations ſhort</l>
               <l>Of your ſo near, and ſo long wiſh'd for Port?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Why ſhould a candid, ſtudious, peacefull mind</l>
               <l>Scarce through this angry Age ſafe paſſage finde?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But ſtay, bold Muſe; None may without offence</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:60121:19"/>Fathom the Depths of State and Providence.</l>
               <l>Reſt we content what Nature hath reveald</l>
               <l>To read, and leave thoſe other volumes ſeald.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Our Joy, our Sorrow with<note n="(a)" place="margin">Prob. 4, 5.</note> diſtinguiſh'd tears;</l>
               <l>Our<note n="(b)" place="margin">47.</note> Laughter at this Authors Bar appears;</l>
               <l>Who doth to ſolid Reaſon recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile</l>
               <l>Ev'ry<note n="(c)" place="margin">28.</note> almoſt in volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary ſmile.</l>
               <l>The ſpring of Paſſions, and the quick Debate</l>
               <l>Of Actions ſeeming indelibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate,</l>
               <l>Are here diſclos'd: his Clue does guide your mind</l>
               <l>Her ſelf through her own Laby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinths to wind.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:60121:20"/>Now we diſcern,<note n="(d)" place="margin">51.</note> Why the parch'd ears grow white,</l>
               <l>When your hot Conſtellations unite:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>We more then feel what<note n="(e)" place="margin">7.</note> ſtreightned Eaſt-winds blow:</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="(f)" place="margin">39.</note> The Serick Inſect we admire and know:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I know too<note n="(g)" place="margin">12.</note> Whence my friend who did but aim</l>
               <l>At doing well, hath hit the mark of Fame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet unreſolv'd of what one Page pretends,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="(h)" place="margin">6.</note>That men not beſt may make your ſureſt friends,</l>
               <l>His life retracts that; and againſt pretence</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:60121:20"/>Of Demonſtration brings full evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</l>
               <l>Like diſpoſitions ſtrong affections move:</l>
               <l>None worſe then He, can challenge equal love.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Jan. 2. 1661.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Chriſtopher Ware <hi>Maſter of the Free-School of</hi> Tun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:60121:21"/>
            <head>To my Worthy Friend Mr. <hi>Samuel Thoms</hi> Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſher of this work of our Deceaſed Friend the Tranſlator Mr. <hi>Henry Some.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>SOme do aſperſe <hi>Tranſlations,</hi> ſay they be</l>
               <l>Like <hi>reverſt Arras</hi> rugged Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>g'rie.</l>
               <l>If ſo, wee'r well by this example taught</l>
               <l>'Tis the <hi>Tranſlators,</hi> not <hi>Tranſlations</hi> fault.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:60121:21"/>
                  <hi>SOME</hi> could out-do his author, lend his ſtory</l>
               <l>A <hi>borrow'd,</hi> greater then its <hi>native</hi> glory;</l>
               <l>Not like thoſe Scriblers, as ill taught as fed,</l>
               <l>Who turn books not int' other tongues, but bread.</l>
               <l>He knew as well to <hi>write,</hi> as to <hi>Tranſlate;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To <hi>lend,</hi> as <hi>borrow</hi> learning; nor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grate</l>
               <l>To forraign witts, could, as well ſtockt as they,</l>
               <l>His <hi>Paris</hi> bills in <hi>Cambridge</hi> coyn repay.</l>
               <l>Nay he was an <hi>Original</hi> of <hi>wit</hi>
               </l>
               <l>So fair, ſo worthy, <hi>Heaven Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> it.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But can I name our loſs, nor pay his Herſe</l>
               <l>The tributary duty of a Verſe?</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:60121:22"/>A duty, though ſuperfluous, ſince he</l>
               <l>Was to himſelf ſufficient Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie.</l>
               <l>Should we his <hi>Learning, Vertue, Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor</hi> ſcan,</l>
               <l>Thoſe joynt <hi>Perfections</hi> ſpeak him more then <hi>Man.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Dear Sir! when I recall thoſe Attick nights</l>
               <l>We once enjoy'd with him, thoſe loſt delights;</l>
               <l>When his diſcourſe charmd our at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentive ears,</l>
               <l>And ſwell'd us then with joy, as now with <hi>tears,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>When we could call his learn'd di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſions ours,</l>
               <l>With which he us'd to wing the ſlow-pac'd hours;</l>
               <l>Methinks ſtern grief doth all my ſence engroſs,</l>
               <l>And the remembrance duplicates our loſs.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:60121:22"/>
               <l>But Sir 'tis you alone muſt now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trive</l>
               <l>This loſs, and in his writings make him live.</l>
               <l>Then as (while he lyes low in ſilent earth)</l>
               <l>You've given this <hi>Poſthume off-ſpring</hi> happy birth;</l>
               <l>So ſtill, <hi>Lucina</hi> like, propitious be,</l>
               <l>And's <hi>other labours</hi> from abortion free.</l>
               <l>Raiſe him a <hi>monument</hi> laſting as <hi>Fame,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And let as <hi>Trophies</hi> of his living Name,</l>
               <l>His <hi>learned reliques,</hi> while his aſhes burn,</l>
               <l>Riſe like the <hi>Phaenix</hi> from their <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents</hi> Urne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then when his happy labours ſhall be grown</l>
               <l>Old in eſteem, enrich us with your own.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:60121:23"/>So ſhall your name with his enrolled ſtand,</l>
               <l>And both in Honours train walk hand in hand.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>R. S. <hi>Late Fellow of Kings Colledge.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:60121:23"/>
            <head>Upon the untimely death of his moſt Ingenious and Learned Friend Mr. <hi>Henry Some,</hi> the Tranſlator of this Book.</head>
            <l>S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rely in Nature, there's ſome rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, Why</l>
            <l>The beſt of Spirits do the ſooneſt Dy.</l>
            <l>Brisk wits, it ſeems, are like the pureſt fire,</l>
            <l>Which brighteſt burns, but ſooneſt does expire.</l>
            <l>The overleaven'd ſort of men, we ſee</l>
            <l>Aged and loathed like the Raven bee:</l>
            <l>Whilſt the more ſprightly part, like fragrant Roſe</l>
            <l>Lov'd and long-liv'd in death their eyelids cloſe:</l>
            <l>The Learned Planet courtier to the Sun,</l>
            <l>As ſwift as Poſt his ſtated race doth run:</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:60121:24"/>Whilſt his dull brother, with his leaden face,</l>
            <l>Ends not his courſe, in twice ten times the ſpace:</l>
            <l>Ah me! it grieves me, that the ripeſt wit,</l>
            <l>Should fatal prove, to him that own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it:</l>
            <l>This kild my Friend: from henceforth be't a ſhame</l>
            <l>To be long-liv'd, for years your wit will blame.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. Jones <hi>fellow of the Kings Colledge in</hi> Cambridge.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:60121:24"/>
            <head>A Table of the Chapters contained in this Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume.</head>
            <list>
               <label>PROB. 1.</label>
               <item>WHat is the reaſon that the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs and ſubtilty of wit which appears in the execution of an evil action, makes us think it ſometimes more ugly, and ſometimes leſs? <hi>pag. 1</hi>
               </item>
               <label>PROB. 2.</label>
               <item>Whence comes the cuſtom of making fire-works and ſhooting off Guns, either when a Peace is made, or after a Victory, or at the entrance of Princes into ſome City, or upon
<pb facs="tcp:60121:25"/>
other the like occaſions? <hi>4</hi>
               </item>
               <label>PROB. 3.</label>
               <item>Whence is it that the Choler of him that hath no cauſe to be afraid of us, and hath our necks under his foot, is ſometimes ſooner appeaſed by bravadoes and boldneſs, then by humility and entreaties? <hi>9</hi>
               </item>
               <label>PROB. 4.</label>
               <item>Whence comes it that Fears are a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to ſadneſs, and how they are formed? <hi>13</hi>
               </item>
               <label>PROB. 5.</label>
               <item>What is the reaſon there are Tears of Joy? <hi>16</hi>
               </item>
               <label>PROB. 6.</label>
               <item>Whence comes it that many very wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men are often times the beſt friends? <hi>20</hi>
               </item>
               <label>
                  <pb facs="tcp:60121:25"/>
                  <hi>PROB. 7.</hi>
               </label>
               <item>What is the reaſon that the Wind which comes in at a window, or a little hole, is more dangerous than that which we feel abroad in the open field? <hi>25</hi>
               </item>
               <label>PROB. 8.</label>
               <item>Whence comes it that Evil is more active then good? <hi>28</hi>
               </item>
               <label>PROB. 9.</label>
               <item>What is the reaſon that Water-drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers are greater lovers of fruit than others? <hi>31</hi>
               </item>
               <label>PROB. 10.</label>
               <item>What is the reaſon that there is no ſuch enmity as that which ſucceeds amity? <hi>33</hi>
               </item>
               <label>
                  <pb facs="tcp:60121:26"/>
                  <hi>PROB. 11.</hi>
               </label>
               <item>Why hath extream affliction no Tears? <hi>36</hi>
               </item>
               <label>PROB. 12.</label>
               <item>What is the reaſon that ſome things are gotten beſt by neglecting them? <hi>41</hi>
               </item>
               <label>PROB. 13.</label>
               <item>What is the reaſon that thoſe things which we are accuſtomed to, are not prejudicial to our health? <hi>44</hi>
               </item>
               <label>PROB. 14.</label>
               <item>Whence comes it, that (as it is the ſaying of ſome body) a great ſervice is not ſo proper to gain our affections, as many petty ſervices done in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued ſeries, and on all occaſions? <hi>49</hi>
               </item>
               <label>
                  <pb facs="tcp:60121:26"/>
                  <hi>PROB. 15.</hi>
               </label>
               <item>What is the reaſon that a great Joy makes us facile to pardon injuries? <hi>53</hi>
               </item>
               <label>PROB. 16.</label>
               <item>What is the reaſon there is ſo much falſe news ſpread abroad, and that many delight to make others believe ſtrange things? <hi>60</hi>
               </item>
               <label>PROB. 17.</label>
               <item>What is the reaſon that having been long on horſe-back, a man doth better refreſh himſelf by walking a little on foot, then by ſitting ſtill? <hi>63</hi>
               </item>
               <label>PROB. 18.</label>
               <item>What is the reaſon that when we come to reſt our ſelves after much walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, we find our ſelves more weary a while after? <hi>64</hi>
               </item>
               <label>
                  <pb facs="tcp:60121:27"/>
                  <hi>PROB. 19.</hi>
               </label>
               <item>Why is it good not to let a wicked man, that hath power to do what miſchief he pleaſe, perceive that we are jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of him? <hi>66</hi>
               </item>
               <label>PROB. 20.</label>
               <item>Whence comes it that Beaſts do know naturally how to ſwim, and that Man hath need to learn? <hi>74</hi>
               </item>
               <label>PROB. 21.</label>
               <item>What is the reaſon that the fruits that grow at the tops of the boughs, are the beſt? <hi>79</hi>
               </item>
               <label>PROB. 22.</label>
               <item>Why do good men think they ought to ſpeak in proper terms of other Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and Vices, but not of things
<pb facs="tcp:60121:27"/>
that regard Wantonneſs and Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral love? <hi>81</hi>
               </item>
               <label>PROB. 23.</label>
               <item>Whence comes it that they ſay what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever cures us and is good for us, diſlikes us, and that on the contrary, we love that which hurts us? <hi>90</hi>
               </item>
               <label>PROB. 24.</label>
               <item>What is the reaſon that children in winter, though their face and hands ſeem to ſhew that they are more af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted with cold then men grown, yet are not eaſily perſwaded to warm themſelves? <hi>95</hi>
               </item>
               <label>PROB. 25.</label>
               <item>Whence comes it that when we are in affliction we are better diverted by the repreſentation of ſome Tragick Hiſtory, or by the recital of ſome great misfortune, then by more mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb facs="tcp:60121:28"/>
ſhews or facetious tales. <hi>97</hi>
               </item>
               <label>PROB. 26.</label>
               <item>Why do ſome noiſes make a man ſleep? <hi>100</hi>
               </item>
               <label>PROB. 27.</label>
               <item>What is the reaſon we aggravate our miſeries, and love to perſwade others that we are very unfortunate? <hi>105</hi>
               </item>
               <label>PROB. 28.</label>
               <item>Why do many men laugh to ſee another man fall? <hi>113</hi>
               </item>
               <label>PROB. 29.</label>
               <item>What is the reaſon that they which embrace civil and worldly affairs with too violent an ardor, are ſubject to loſe all ſenſe of Religion and the knowledge of a Deitie? <hi>115</hi>
               </item>
               <label>
                  <pb facs="tcp:60121:28"/>
                  <hi>PROB. 30.</hi>
               </label>
               <item>What is the reaſon that the loweſt Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits are commonly moſt perſwaded of the truth of their opinions? <hi>120</hi>
               </item>
               <label>PROB. 31.</label>
               <item>Whence is it that in the greateſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of affliction, we do many times take up more readily a conſtant re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, then in others that are much lighter? <hi>122</hi>
               </item>
               <label>PROB. 32.</label>
               <item>Wherefore are old men great talkers? <hi>123</hi>
               </item>
               <label>PROB. 33.</label>
               <item>Whence comes it that in all kind of things thoſe that do but meanly in them, are moſt commonly more ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere and rigid Judges of others, then thoſe that excell therein, and hold the firſt rank? <hi>127</hi>
               </item>
               <label>
                  <pb facs="tcp:60121:29"/>
                  <hi>PROB. 34.</hi>
               </label>
               <item>Whence comes it that it is ſo eaſie to blame and finde fault, that the leaſt able do it beſt, and that it is much more hard to commend? <hi>132</hi>
               </item>
               <label>PROB. 35.</label>
               <item>What is the reaſon that when the Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hath been very cold, they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly ſay, the Summer that follows will be very hot? <hi>136</hi>
               </item>
               <label>PROB. 36.</label>
               <item>What is the reaſon that Fear makes ones hair ſtand on end? <hi>138</hi>
               </item>
               <label>PROB. 37.</label>
               <item>Whence comes it that many being in a Frenzy have ſpoken Latin, or Greek, wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>t having ever learned either of theſe Languages? <hi>141</hi>
               </item>
               <label>
                  <pb facs="tcp:60121:29"/>
                  <hi>PROB. 38.</hi>
               </label>
               <item>What is the reaſon that a too earneſt entreaty makes us unwilling, inſtead of inciting us, to grant that which is deſired of us. <hi>146</hi>
               </item>
               <label>PROB. 39.</label>
               <item>What are the cauſes of the marvellous things which we obſerve in the Silk-worm? <hi>151</hi>
               </item>
               <label>PROB. 40.</label>
               <item>Why are good men oftentimes ſubject to a light promptitude of Choler? <hi>161</hi>
               </item>
               <label>PROB. 41.</label>
               <item>Whence comes it that they ſay, the love of Grandfathers to their Grand-children is greater then that of their Fathers? <hi>165</hi>
               </item>
               <label>
                  <pb facs="tcp:60121:30"/>
                  <hi>PROB. 42.</hi>
               </label>
               <item>Why is it that a rare and eminent ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue which ſhines in a Prince, raiſes greater motions of love in the lower ſort of people then in other men? <hi>168</hi>
               </item>
               <label>PROB. 43.</label>
               <item>What is the reaſon that Shame makes a redneſs ariſe in the face? <hi>177</hi>
               </item>
               <label>PROB. 44.</label>
               <item>What is the reaſon that when we bluſh, it appears eſpecially in the forehead? <hi>185</hi>
               </item>
               <label>PROB. 45.</label>
               <item>What is the reaſon that Praiſes make a man bluſh? <hi>187</hi>
               </item>
               <label>PROB. 46.</label>
               <item>What is the reaſon a man laughs more
<pb facs="tcp:60121:30"/>
at a pleaſant jeſt, or a merry tale, when he himſelf that tells it doth not laugh? <hi>190</hi>
               </item>
               <label>PROB. 47.</label>
               <item>Why do we laugh in ſeeing a thing very ill-favoured, ſince that which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights the mind, one would think, ought to have in it ſome perfection? <hi>193</hi>
               </item>
               <label>PROB. 48.</label>
               <item>What is the reaſon that Man being inclined to flatter himſelf, doth nevertheleſs aggravate his own imperfection above the truth; as for example, in ſaying there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but folly, and injuſtice, and ingratitude in the world? <hi>198</hi>
               </item>
               <label>PROB. 49.</label>
               <item>What is the reaſon that according to the common ſaying of the Poets and of Ariſtotle himſelf in the ſecond
<pb facs="tcp:60121:31"/>
book of his Politicks, Valiant and couragious perſons are moſt ſubject to love? <hi>208</hi>
               </item>
               <label>PROB. 50.</label>
               <item>Whence comes that averſion to marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age of perſons too near? <hi>212</hi>
               </item>
               <label>PROB. 51.</label>
               <item>Whence proceed the exceſſive Heats of the moneth of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> and the other effects which are attributed to the Dog-ſtar? <hi>221</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <trailer>The End.</trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="problem">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:60121:31"/>
            <head>
               <hi>PROB. 1.</hi> What's the reaſon that the addreſs and ſubtilty of wit, which appears in the execution of an evil action, makes us think it ſometimes more ugly, and ſometimes leſs?</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Queſtion having two parts, doth not the reaſon of the firſt conſiſt in this, that he which is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious and imployes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>his wit to do ill, ſeems to be more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ngratefull towards God, in abuſing the gifts which he hath received of him? Or elſe is it, that he which
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:60121:32"/>
hath cunningly carried on a very malitious action, ſeems not to have been touched with any remorſe of conſcience that troubled his judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for which reaſon he is account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed more wicked and more unnatural? Or elſe, is it that an evil action full of wit and addreſs, cannot have been committed by a ſudden and pardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able motion; and that this addreſs which appears in it, ſhews that a man hath digeſted it at his leaſure, that he had a long time had it in his mind, and that he executed it with a full and conſtant will? Or elſe, is it becauſe he that ſins ſo craftily, ſeems to have been very violently deſirous to ſin, ſince it is certain that a violent deſire whets the wit, and renders it fruitful in inventions? Or elſe, is it becauſe the more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious a treaſon is, the more cloſe and ſecret alſo it is; ſo that there is requiſite the more impudence and diſſimulation to execute it? Or laſtly, is it becauſe the rendring
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:60121:32"/>
deceitful by a very refined treaſon, the common aſſurances which we take of things, is an undermining the foundations of publick repoſe, and after a particular manner, the ſhaking of nature, which hath not given us any better means to guide our ſelves in civil ſociety, and an inſtructing of knaves new wayes to hurt honeſt men, ſo that this is a being doubly guilty; as a thief is doubly guilty, if not content to ſteal the fruits of a garden, he enters into it by ſome place formerly inac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſible, and makes a new way for thoſe that ſhall have a mind to imitate him? But if this be ſo, whence comes it then, that at other times the ingenuity that ſhines in the execution of an ill action, makes us blame it leſs ſharply, and ſweetens the hatred it ought to beget in us? Is it in this caſe not ſo odious, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the luſtre of wit may in ſome ſort repair the defect of it? Or elſe, becauſe when experience teacheth
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:60121:33"/>
us, that the <hi>beauty</hi> of the mind, and a <hi>black</hi> malice ſeldome lodge toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and do not willingly aſſociate; we do then frame ſome excuſeable motives to an evil action, when we ſee ſome gentleneſs ſhine in it, and conceive that he that did it, was forced to it, either out of <hi>Gallantry,</hi> or by the ſtrength of ſome ſudden <hi>Paſſion,</hi> rather than out of an extream <hi>Malice</hi> and <hi>ill-nature?</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="problem">
            <head>
               <hi>PROB. 2.</hi> Whence comes the cuſtome of making fire-works, and ſhooting off guns, either when a peace is made, or after a victory, or at the entrance of Princes into ſome City, or upon other the like occaſions?</head>
            <p>FIrſt, as to publick rejoycings; Is it becauſe joy which is a violent dilatation of our ſpirits, cannot be better expreſſed then by ſhews
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:60121:33"/>
which conſiſt only in violent dilata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of powder by fire? Or elſe, if there be no likelyhood that men did ſo nicely regard ſuch a relation, and that mans imagination out of a ſecret impulſe, took up a thing that reſembles the motion of joy to expreſs it by? Is it rather becauſe <hi>Light,</hi> which all theſe Artificial fires redouble, is naturally the Emblem of <hi>Joy,</hi> and does naturally delight the imagination more than any thing? And therefore we call <hi>ſadneſs</hi> a <hi>dark</hi> cloudy humor, and when we ſpeak of it, we ſay that it overſpreads the mind as 'twere with a <hi>cloud.</hi> Or elſe, is it not becauſe we finding that our <hi>own</hi> voice is too weak to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent our joy, and that it is wholly unequal to the greatneſs of our contentment, we borrow the mouth of Cannons, and the noyſes of pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to expreſs it, and to carry the news of it ſpeedily on every ſide, and make it as it were even mount up to heaven? It is manifeſt that <hi>Joy</hi> of all
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:60121:34"/>
the Paſſions is that which deſires moſt to be known and publiſhed, and a joyfull man is equally raviſhed that his friends and enemies know that he is ſo. Or elſe, as it is a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to ſee the picture of ſome great Dragon, which had frighted us, after that we have no more cauſe to fear it; is it not alſo delightful for the ſame reaſon to ſee the vain images of troubles, violences, and paſſed wars in the fires of joy after that a peace is begun? Or elſe may we take it thus, that as it is a ſign a man hath faſt bound a ſavage beaſt, when he can play with it without harm, and without dread, and make a paſs-time of its rage and fury; ſo it is a ſign that one hath faſt chained up that cruel monſter, War, when one can freely ſport with the moſt terrible inſtruments of its fury, when one can make them vomit up, whatever they have moſt hurtful and affrighting, without any mans receiving either fear or hurt thereby; and that one
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:60121:34"/>
makes them ſerve for a divertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to Women and Children? Or elſe is not this <hi>ſecondary</hi> and inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent uſe which we make of them as it were a teſtimony that we aboliſh the <hi>firſt;</hi> and therefore alſo when we would ſpeak of a profound peace, we uſe to ſay that all the inſtruments of War ſhall become inſtruments of Husbandry, or ſhall be employed to other uſes?</p>
            <p>Now ſeeing that fireworks and the reports of the Canon are uſed to repreſent a publick joy, is it not for the ſame reaſon that they are uſed at the entrance of Princes into ſome City, as it were to teſtifie to them that their arrival is eſteemed a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick happineſs? Or elſe was it not firſt inſtituted on this manner, out of an extream <hi>flattery,</hi> as if they meant to ſay, that they judged the ſoul of the Prince that is thus received, ſo <hi>Martial,</hi> that they thought they could not better pleaſe him, than by ſhows that repreſent <hi>War?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:60121:35"/>If any one, notwithſtanding all this, ſhall wonder, that to <hi>receive</hi> a Prince, we do to him in like manner as we would do if we deſired to <hi>drive</hi> him <hi>away,</hi> and that we expreſs our <hi>kindneſs</hi> by the moſt proper marks of <hi>hatred</hi> and <hi>hoſtility:</hi> is it not on the contrary, partly for that the imagination of men is carried to it, becauſe naturally a violent <hi>love</hi> bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows the characters of <hi>hate?</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we ſee that beaſts when they make much of their little ones, they ſtrike them little blows, and toſs them up gently into the air; and that mothers careſſing their children with all tenderneſs, give them little <hi>pats</hi> and call them <hi>rogues:</hi> and that the beſt friends delight to quarrel with one another ſeemingly and in jeſt: and we might queſtionleſs prove the ſame by <hi>wanton love,</hi> choſe we not rather to paſs by this proof, then to write any thing that ſhould defile this paper. And if yet you demand of me, why a violent <hi>love</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:60121:35"/>
borrows the characters of <hi>hatred;</hi> Is it not out of a too great deſire of flying the appearances of flattery, and falſe amity, that it runs into this contrary extream, which is more irrational; as if flying from an enemy, a man ſhould caſt himſelf down a precipice? Or rather that in this there is nothing done otherwiſe than ought to be, but that extream <hi>love</hi> hath ſome characters like to the violence of <hi>hatred,</hi> becauſe generally all extreams reſemble one another?</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="problem">
            <head>
               <hi>PROB. 3.</hi> Whence is it that the Choler of him that hath no cauſe to be afraid of us, and hath our necks under his feet, is ſometimes ſooner appeaſed by bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vado's, and boldneſs, than by humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and entreaties?</head>
            <p>IS it not for the reaſon that <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagne</hi> gives of it; namely that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:60121:36"/>
generous perſons ſuffer themſelves rather to be overcome by the generoſity and greatneſs of the courage of him whom fortune hath laid low, than at his cryes and groans, becauſe they are more ready to reverence the image of vertue, then ſimply to be bent by compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, which many times may be unreaſonable? Or elſe, is it from ſome other cauſes, as for inſtance this, that it is a thing that aſtoniſhes and ſurprizes him who can do what he pleaſe with us, to ſee that inſtead of ſubmitting to him, we brave him, and that every aſtoniſhment is as it were an arreſt and ſurprizal of the ſpirit, which conſequently interrupts the motion of Choler, and gives the ſoul that is ſurprized with it, time to be better adviſed? To this might be added, perhaps, that in Choler the ſoul many times moves not, but by the violence of the firſt ſwing that is given it; and that in this caſe if one can ſtop it, it is infallibly extinct; as
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:60121:36"/>
one deads the motion of a body which is moved only by the violence of an impreſſion it receives, if one ſtop it but one ſole moment. Or elſe, is it becauſe the bravado's and boldneſs of thoſe whom an extream misfortune hath caſt down, doth not ſhew ſo much <hi>Conſtancy</hi> and <hi>Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> although at the firſt ſight it ſeems to do ſo; as on the quite contrary <hi>Despair,</hi> becauſe he that <hi>hopes</hi> nothing, doth likewiſe <hi>fear</hi> nothing; ſo that inſtead of raiſing <hi>Choler</hi> it excites <hi>Pitty?</hi> Or elſe may we venture to ſay, that naturally every thing is extinguiſhed by the ſame cauſes which made it live, when they are too abundant; and that as <hi>Love</hi> is extinguiſhed by too free and too wanton careſſes, and <hi>Fire</hi> by too great an abundance of wood caſt on it, it may fall out ſome times after the very ſame manner, that the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity and utmoſt exceſs of injuries <hi>appeaſes</hi> Choler inſtead of <hi>provoking</hi> it? Or elſe, is it not becauſe the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:60121:37"/>
and bravado's of thoſe that ſee themſelves to be in our power, are a teſtimony of their <hi>free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> and that we believe they have no worſe thoughts than thoſe that they dare thus expreſs with ſo much liberty, whereas, if they beg of us with ſubmiſſion and humility, we ſuſpect them of <hi>hypocriſie,</hi> and fear leaſt this diſſimulation covers ſome black revenge, and an implacable and furious hatred againſt us? Or elſe, is it that for a man to humble himſelf before us, is to furniſh us with a ſubject of only <hi>Vulgar</hi> clemency, which as it is leſs fair, ſo it doth with leſs violence attract us; and that, on the contrary, to brave us, after having offended us, is to furniſh us with matter for an <hi>heroick</hi> clemency, which is more beauteous in its ſelf, and followed with more of glory? Or laſtly, is it that he which doth freely reproach us, and boldly declares our injuſtice, cutting our ſoul to the very quick by this vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:60121:37"/>
of his diſcourſe, doth awaken it, makes it come to its ſelf, forces it to be attentive to the reaſons he alledges, and makes it comprehend them better, after which, though its intereſt oblige it to a greater re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge then before, it cannot ſtill continue its rage, becauſe, as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſaith very well, <hi>a man is never angry injuſtly,</hi> that is to ſay, againſt that which he doth very clearly know to be reaſonable?</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="problem">
            <head>
               <hi>PROB. 4.</hi> Whence comes it that Tears are a comfort to ſadneſs, and how are they formed?</head>
            <p>IS it not that Tears do not proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly unload the <hi>heart,</hi> as it is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly ſaid, but the <hi>brain,</hi> which being more dry after it is delivered of thoſe humidities, ſerves the ſoul better, and is the cauſe that he which
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:60121:38"/>
is afflicted having his reaſon more clear and ſtrong, ſees better the juſt grounds he hath to comfort himſelf? Certainly it is probable enough that the <hi>brain</hi> becomes more free, and the ſpirit more <hi>ſerene</hi> after this <hi>ſtorme</hi> of <hi>tears,</hi> as we ſee the <hi>air</hi> is never more ſerene than after <hi>rain;</hi> and the example of children teaches us that the moiſtneſs of the brain ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companies the weakneſs of reaſon. Or is it moreover that by weeping we diſcharge part of the pituitous humour, or of the melancholy hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, both which caſt the ſpirits into penſiveneſs, and a dull heavineſs or ſtupidity? Truely this ſecond reaſon ſeems not to be void of like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyhood no more than the firſt. But (will ſome one ſay) whence proceed Tears, and what is their fountain? Certainly it is no eaſie queſtion to anſwer; and perhaps, to reſolve it exactly, would require a longer ſearch then can be allowed a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blem. But yet methinks one might
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:60121:38"/>
venture to ſay according to the appearances we ſee, that our inward parts compreſſing themſelves in ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, as it is the property of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, there iſſues from them ſome moiſture by this compreſſion, as from a ſpunge ſqueezed: Or elſe that the brain continuing cold in ſadneſs by reaſon of the ſpirits flying to the heart, it yeilds through its coldneſs ſome thin ſubſtance which becoming heavy, ſeeks its way out; Or elſe, as ſadneſs generally weakens whatever is in us, that retentive faculty of him that is ſad, is not ſtrong enough to keep back, as it did before, thoſe humidities, which we call Tears, but ſuffers them to run out when it relaxeth its ſelf.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="problem">
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:60121:39"/>
            <head>
               <hi>PROB. 5.</hi> What is the reaſon there are Tears of joy?</head>
            <p>IS it that a too violent <hi>good</hi> wounds us many times as well as too ſtrong a <hi>light?</hi> Or elſe that every change of condition in which one hath long continued, how happy and advantageous ſoever it be, hath alwayes ſomething of incommodious in it? Or elſe, that there is ſome bitterneſs, and as it were an infuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of wormwood in the greateſt part of the ſweets of this life? Or elſe, is there not ſome natural reaſon in it? and may we not ſay that <hi>joy</hi> exceſſively dilating our inward parts, doth by this means drive out ſome humidity; becauſe that which is dilated cannot contain it ſelf in the ſame bounds where it was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore? Or elſe, is it not that in an
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:60121:39"/>
affliction, we are hindred from weeping, out of a fear for the future, which makes us imploy all our thoughts in conſideration of means that may deliver us from that which we fear; ſo that after we are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come more happy, we do yet many times nevertheleſs cry, to ſatisfie that deſire which we had to do ſo? Or elſe, is it not credible, that we never underſtood our miſery better, then when being delivered from it, we can compare the image of it, which is ſtill very freſh in our me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, with a quite contrary con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition: ſo that it is not to be wondred at, if many times this compariſon which diſcovers to us the greatneſs of it, makes us weep even in the midſt of our joy, through a kind of pitty we have of our ſelves? Or elſe ſhall I take it thus, that in the ſudden motions of a great joy, the dilatation of the ſpirits of the heart is ſo great, that it is weakned thereby, and that our
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:60121:40"/>
ſoul finding its own weakneſs, by this means is apt to be wounded by every reflexion that hath never ſo little of trouble in it? Or laſtly, do not theſe tears of joy proceed from hence, that learning all on a ſudden, that we are delivered from ſome great evil, under which we have lain a long time, the news cannot preſently gain an entire belief in us: and that as a body that is frozen, doth not loſe its coldneſs at that very inſtant it is brought to the fire; by the ſame reaſon our ſoul cannot loſe that impreſſion of its paſſed ſadneſs, at the very ſame inſtant that the good it was deprived of becomes preſent to it? See then the cauſes which it ſeems may be given of that marvellous ſtate of man, wherein he weeps although he have a ſerene ſpirit, by an accident which we ſee ſometimes happen in the air when it <hi>rains</hi> and <hi>ſhines</hi> both at once. There are are alſo Tears which abundant <hi>laughter</hi> brings
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:60121:40"/>
into our eyes; but they are not of the ſame <hi>species</hi> with thoſe I ſpake of but now; and I conceive, they proceed only from that great and violent agitation which laughter cauſes within us; for there is no paſſion which ſhakes a man all over with greater violence; and it may very well be, that a motion ſo vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent forces out of the eyes ſome humidity; as we ſee that the violent agitation of a veſſel wherein there is ſome liquor, makes ſome drops of it ſparkle out; and as the wind that ſhakes the trees after a rain, makes thoſe drops which lay there, fall to the ground.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="problem">
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:60121:41"/>
            <head>
               <hi>PROB. 6.</hi> Whence comes it that many very wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men, are oftentimes the beſt friends?</head>
            <p>IT is found by experience, that very bad men are often moſt zealous friends to them that they bear an affection to, nay ſometimes more then the beſt of men. To enquire then the cauſes of this effect, is it not that there is a kind of amity which is not begotten by <hi>reaſon,</hi> but by a means more low, namely long <hi>acquaintance</hi> and <hi>familiarity:</hi> ſo that ſouls of the loweſt rank and that have the leaſt of reaſon, are not incapable of it: but on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry are in ſome ſort more capable than others, becauſe not governing themſelves by judgement, they do only follow the impreſſions of other things; amongſt which, that which
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:60121:41"/>
               <hi>length of time</hi> and <hi>uſe</hi> makes, is none of the leaſt? Or elſe, is it not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe good men are friends only <hi>ad aras,</hi> that is, as far as will ſtand with Religion, and wicked men beyond? So that if they muſt only proſtitute their conſciences to their friends, and tread underfoot all things ſacred, and deſpoile themſelves of the faireſt ornaments the ſoul can be adorned with, they do it very willingly. Or elſe, is it not that as <hi>dogs</hi> are faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to us, and ſuccour us againſt thoſe that ſet upon us, partly indeed out of <hi>love,</hi> but partly alſo becauſe it is their <hi>dispoſition</hi> to be eaſily provoked: ſo wicked men help us with great ardour againſt our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and combat them with great animoſity, not only for the affection they bear us, but partly alſo, for that by reaſon of their <hi>natural curſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> and <hi>venome,</hi> of which they are full, they are more apt to be inflamed with a violent choler? Or elſe, is it becauſe it is very natural for us to
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:60121:42"/>
love with violence ſomething with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out us; wicked men that love neither <hi>God,</hi> nor <hi>Juſtice,</hi> nor <hi>common good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> are conſtrained by the force of nature to love infinitely ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular perſons? Or elſe, is it that cultivating only that part of their duty which conſiſts only in <hi>friendſhip,</hi> and keeping that only as a remainder of the beauty of the ſoul, which hinders them from altogether reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling ſavage beaſts, they have the more love for that, as a mother hath the more love for her ſon, if he be her only one? Or laſtly, is it not that the nature of things is ſuch, that generally in every extream there is ſome light mixture of the contrary extream: For inſtance, we ſee by experience that in cold Countries there are ſometimes in ſummer more violent heats then thoſe of the hot Countries; and on the contrary, the ſubtilty of the air of the hot Countries is the reaſon that ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the cold there is more pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trating
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:60121:42"/>
than that of the cold Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries. The <hi>Germans</hi> that paſs for the leaſt ſubtle people of <hi>Europe,</hi> have more of ſubtilty than any of the reſt in all ſort of <hi>mechanick inventions.</hi> The moſt ingenious people are commonly the moſt awkward and unapt in ſome ſlight things. <hi>Melancholy</hi> perſons are ſubject to more violent joyes, then thoſe that are <hi>ſanguine; covetous</hi> people, according to the vulgar opinion, are ſometimes carried out to a greater exceſs of prodigality then <hi>prodigals.</hi> Men extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary valiant do often tremble more then others at the ſight of a great danger. <hi>Women,</hi> whoſe viſage is more properly then that of men <hi>the ſeat of Beauty,</hi> are alſo more ſuſcep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible then men of an extream and horrid <hi>uglineſs.</hi> Laſtly, to return to the mixture of goodneſs and wickedneſs, one of the cruelleſt Emperours of <hi>Rome</hi> could not, as the Hiſtorian ſaith, be preſent at
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:60121:43"/>
the acting of a <hi>Tragedy,</hi> but thoſe faigned miſeries which he there heard, raiſed a compaſſion in him which made him weep. We read as much of another Tyrant of <hi>Greece</hi> of the ſame nature; and when a man is arrived at the higheſt degree of wickedneſs, the laſt crime he commits, is to be his own murderer, and voluntarily to throw himſelf into everlaſting pains, by the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of the remorſe of his conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. In which there ſeems to be a certain air and ſhaddow of magna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimity and heroick goodneſs.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="problem">
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:60121:43"/>
            <head>
               <hi>PROB. 7.</hi> What is the reaſon that the Wind which comes in at a window or a little hole, is more dangerous than that which we feel abroad in the open field?</head>
            <p>UPon this Problem ſome may poſſibly think, that as the <hi>wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> meeting with a very narrow channel, becomes more rapid; ſo the <hi>wind</hi> that comes in at a door, or a window, or a ſmall chink, for the ſame reaſon redoubles its violence: Which is very true, but nothing to the purpoſe, for the clearing the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty of this Queſtion: becauſe it is certain that a very little wind gli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in at a cranny, is more apt to hurt one, then another wind much more violent, when one is in the open field. This cauſe then being thus rejected, is it not rather becauſe
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:60121:44"/>
the wind which we ſuffer in the open field doth preſently cloſe the pores through its coldneſs, and ſo arms us againſt it ſelf: whereas the wind that comes into the houſe by ſome little hole, finds us hot all the time, and conſequently doth, as long as it continues blowing, find our fleſh ſoft, and eaſily penetrable. Or elſe, is it becauſe the wind that cools only one part of us, ſuch as that is which comes in at a little crack, makes the ſpirits, to which this coldneſs is an enemy, fly to the other parts, which is hurtful to this? Or elſe, in plain terms, as the welfare of a Common-wealth conſiſts in a certain proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Citizens</hi> one to another; ſo the good ſtate of the <hi>body</hi> is a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain equal temper of all the <hi>parts:</hi> ſo that when any thing breaks this equality and harmony, and cools one part, while the reſt continue warm, this is in it ſelf a malady, and it were better they had been all equally cooled? Or elſe, is it becauſe the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:60121:44"/>
wind that one ſuffers in the open field, is a very <hi>wide,</hi> and as it were <hi>broad</hi> motion of the air, which ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riving at us, muſt needs break it ſelf againſt our body, as it were a <hi>wave,</hi> and paſs on each ſide without pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trating it: Whereas the wind of a little hole, being <hi>ſharp,</hi> doth the better <hi>penetrate</hi> our pores, and doth us the more miſchief: as we ſee that an <hi>arrow</hi> which does not hurt us if it be caſt at us <hi>broadwiſe,</hi> wounds and pierces us if it hits us with the <hi>point?</hi> Or laſtly, doth not that which <hi>Plutarch</hi> ſaies, contribute to the ſame effect, <hi>viz.</hi> that the wind of a little hole, hurts us the more, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we take no heed of it, and that ſo we ſuffer it a great while before we put our ſelves in a condition to avoid it?</p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="problem">
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:60121:45"/>
            <head>
               <hi>PROB. 8.</hi> What is the reaſon that Evil is more active than Good?</head>
            <p>IT is a very ſtrange thing, and yet very true, that <hi>Evil</hi> is more active than <hi>Good. Grief,</hi> which is an evil, is more active than <hi>pleaſure,</hi> and ſurmounts it ſo much in violence, that although a man be at the ſame time tickled with all the pleaſures that can flatter the ſenſes, a ſmall <hi>Grief</hi> will be able to ſpoil all his hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs. As Grief is ſtronger than Pleaſure; ſo Fear, which is a produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Evil, is a paſſion much more violent than <hi>Hope,</hi> which is a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction of Good. <hi>Bad examples</hi> have more force to debaſe our minds, then <hi>good</hi> have to raiſe them up. <hi>Poyſons</hi> are ſtronger than <hi>Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies;</hi> and whereas there is not any remedy that can cure us of our ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladies,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:60121:45"/>
unleſs it be applyed to us, there are poyſons ſo violent that they kill us with the very ſmell of them, if they do but come nigh our noſtrils. Things that are the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt to the taſte, as <hi>Honey</hi> and <hi>Sugar,</hi> are not yet ſo ſweet, as <hi>Wormwood</hi> is bitter: and if you mingle an equal quantity of them together, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult will be bitter and not ſweet, the ill favour prevailing over the good. Laſtly, to omit nothing upon this ſubject, and to run through all kind of things by which this truth may be cleared, although amongſt colours <hi>White</hi> be naturally more excellent than <hi>Black,</hi> as more approaching to the nature of Light: So it is, as Painters have obſerved, that it is the moſt feeble of all; and that, if one mixeth it in an equal quantity with <hi>black,</hi> it is alwayes vanquiſht. But what then is the cauſe of a thing that ſeems ſo contrary to reaſon? I anſwer, that there can be no other given of it, but this, that Good
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:60121:46"/>
here <hi>below,</hi> is not in its fountain, and that we ſee only ſome weak raies and ſmall ſparks of it; for if it were at <hi>home</hi> in its fountain, it would infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libly conquer Evil, and would be too ſtrong for it, ſince that <hi>Activity</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a <hi>Good,</hi> it is impoſſible but that it ſhould be a property and depend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of <hi>Good</hi> rather then of <hi>Evil.</hi> But as of two Kings, he that is the ſtrongeſt may be vanquiſhed by the other, in a place where he hath not the body of his forces, and his great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt power: So it may very well be that <hi>Good</hi> may be more active than <hi>Ill,</hi> and yet that it may be vanquiſht by it in <hi>this</hi> world where we are, and, as I may ſo ſay, in this <hi>lower re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> of things, where it is not in its fountain, and in its greateſt glory, and from hence may be drawn a very ſtrong conſideration to demonſtrate <hi>the exiſtence of God,</hi> as I could ſhew more at large, and more clearly, if it were here my deſign.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="problem">
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:60121:46"/>
            <head>
               <hi>PROB. 9.</hi> What is the reaſon that Water-drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers are greater lovers of fruit then others?</head>
            <p>IS it not becauſe <hi>water</hi> hath a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain faint quality that offends the ſtomach, and the juice of fruit cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rects that quality, and is to them as a kind of <hi>wine</hi> which they are not averſe from? Or elſe, doth not the ſame reaſon that makes them love water, make them alſo love fruit, to wit, becauſe they love all things that are moiſt and cooling, and that fruit as well as water is in the number of things that are moſt ſo? Or elſe, is it not becauſe they which drink wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter only, do with more difficulty di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt, and for this reaſon they love things that are eaſily digeſted, ſuch as are moſt fruits, and prefer them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore viands that give more pain to
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:60121:47"/>
the natural heat? And if any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, Whence it is that they ſay al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, that on the contrary thoſe which are great lovers of wine, do not care at all for fruit: Is it not the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to thoſe reaſons I now mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? Or elſe, do they not hate fruit, becauſe by their moiſture, they dull and deaden the palate, and ſo render it leſs ſenſible of the pleaſure to which they are ſo much addicted? Or doth not the ſame reaſon for which they love ſalt and drying meats, make them alſo hate thoſe that quench the thirſt, amongſt which it ſeems fruit holds the firſt rank?</p>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="problem">
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:60121:47"/>
            <head>
               <hi>PROB. 10.</hi> What is the reaſon there is no ſuch enmity as that which ſucceeds amity?</head>
            <p>IS it not becauſe our mind doth ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently affect all <hi>new</hi> things, and loves <hi>change;</hi> and that when we come to hate him, whom we have a long time loved, it is a very great <hi>novelty</hi> and an extream <hi>change,</hi> which conſequently hath ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular allurement to attract our minds and engage it more violently in its deſign? Or elſe, do not great friendſhips leave behind them great enmities, becauſe they could not have been deſtroyed but by great quarrels, and great ſubjects of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred and diſcontent? Or elſe, is it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe as a <hi>ſtranger,</hi> whom we do not know, cannot be either hated or loved: by the ſame reaſon, he that is
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:60121:48"/>
very well <hi>known,</hi> may be hated more, and loved more than another; and that there are none ſo well known to us, as thoſe whom a long friendſhip hath made us familiarly acquainted with. And indeed as the great know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge we have of them makes us more lively imagine the motions of hatred they bear us, the <hi>words</hi> they will ſay, the <hi>thoughts</hi> they will have, and their very <hi>geſtures</hi> in their anger, it is credible that this ſerves to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flame our wrath. Or elſe perhaps we may ſay that thoſe, that are great lovers of one another, do only <hi>ſeem</hi> to hate more then other men; and perhaps they ſeem ſo, becauſe that ſome relicks of friendſhip, which they cannot chaſe out of their mind, rendring the injuries which they mutually do one another, more grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous, makes them complain thereof with words fuller of paſſion, and talk of it unceſſantly. Indeed it is que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionleſs much more grievous to be wronged by him that one loves, then
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:60121:48"/>
by him that one hates; becauſe this kind of wrong raiſes as it were a <hi>Civil war</hi> in our paſſions, exciting one part of our heart againſt the other, and hinders us not only from <hi>obtaining</hi> what we deſire, but alſo from <hi>deſiring</hi> it compleatly and without repugnance of a piece of our ſelves; and <hi>Lovers</hi> may be good teſtimonies of this truth; for it is certain, as there are many waters that do not offend the <hi>ſound</hi> parts of our bodies, but yet when they touch a <hi>ſore</hi> place, cauſe there incredible pain: So this ſweet wounding of their heart, makes them moſt ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of injuries, which, without that, would not vex, nor move them at all. Or, laſtly, thoſe that loved very dearly, do combate one another with the cruelleſt acts of enmity, to learn, as I may ſo ſay, to hate one another, and to confirm themſelves in that bitterneſs and violence, into which they are faln, becauſe they find, that all ſorts of habits are
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:60121:49"/>
fortified by exerciſe, and by the acts which they produce.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="problem">
            <head>
               <hi>PROB. 11.</hi> Why hath extream affliction no tears?</head>
            <p>DOth it not proceed from hence, for that the ſoul in an extream affliction, hath no <hi>lively</hi> apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, ſuch as thoſe muſt be that raiſe tears, but falls into a kind of <hi>ſtupidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> and <hi>inſenſibleneſs?</hi> Or is it not becauſe when we are extreamly afflicted, Nature, which finds that the greatneſs of our Affliction would make us ſhed too many tears, and that ſo great an evacuation might exceſſively weaken, inſtead of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forting us, keeps them back altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and reſiſts the motion of our diſordered minds, which, were it not for that, would abuſe this ſove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign remedy, and employ it to our own ruine? Or elſe, may we not
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:60121:49"/>
upon this ſubject ſay, that he that is mightily afflicted, cannot weep as he would do, becauſe generally every exceſſive paſſion hinders it ſelf from arriving at its end, and becomes an obſtacle to its ſelf; and that for this reaſon thoſe that are oppreſſed with too much <hi>Fear,</hi> deſiring to flie, find that it hath nailed their feet to the ground; and that their hand ſhakes that are too much in <hi>Choler,</hi> and that they cannot expreſs but by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſequent and disjoynted words, the greatneſs of their paſſion, no more then thoſe whom a too great <hi>Love</hi> poſſeſſes, or thoſe who are in a too great exceſs of <hi>Joy?</hi> Certainly it ſeems that this is not void of like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lihood. And if it be asked, Why every exceſſive paſſion fails of ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riving at its end? it may be anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that this happens to it, becauſe it is a malady of the ſoul, and a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect; and that the qualities proper to a malady are, impotence, weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and ill ſucceſs. Or elſe, every
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:60121:50"/>
inordinate paſſion is an obſtacle to its ſelf, and is impotent, becauſe it deſires things <hi>vaſt</hi> and <hi>infinite,</hi> and beyond all <hi>poſſibility,</hi> which hinders our ſoul from executing thoſe that are <hi>real</hi> and <hi>poſſible.</hi> For we ſee evidently, that he which is moved with a very great <hi>Choler,</hi> cannot ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs, at leaſt in common and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary words, his reſentment, and the indignity which raiſed it, becauſe he ſeeks the moſt ſtrong, and deſires to uſe a more eager expreſſion then the language of man is capable of. It is plain alſo, that <hi>Lovers</hi> do many times <hi>hack</hi> and <hi>hammer</hi> inſtead of <hi>ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> for the ſame reaſon, namely becauſe they would invent terms that ſhould be as it were all <hi>flame,</hi> and have more <hi>force</hi> and <hi>energie</hi> then they can have; and that a like deſire is the cauſe alſo why <hi>Joy,</hi> which is ſo <hi>talkative,</hi> becomes <hi>mute</hi> in being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed too much, or brings forth only ſighs and inarticulate and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed ſounds. And as for exceſſive
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:60121:50"/>
               <hi>Fear,</hi> though this be a paſſion to which one cannot ſo eaſily apply this reaſon; yet one may ſay poſſibly, that he which is too lively poſſeſt by the image of a terrible and preſent danger, hinders himſelf, that in this perturbation and trouble wherein he is, he deſires not ſimply to run, but to uſe ſome means more prompt and efficacious then natural and ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ones by which a man runs away; and that his imagination thus over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlipping whatſoever is real and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, as that of others which we ſpake of but now, does not, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon hereof, put in practice thoſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties that move the parts of his body; for it is evident that it is the operation of the <hi>Fancy</hi> that muſt put in practice thoſe faculties. But how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it be, it is very likely that <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, Joy,</hi> and <hi>Love,</hi> fail of expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing themſelves well, for this reaſon; and if it be ſo, we may with likeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood ſay, that even ſo he which is very much afflicted, cannot weep,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:60121:51"/>
becauſe that his ſoul diſdaining the common characters of ſadneſs, ſearches in that ardour wherein it is, ſo great ones that they are impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Or elſe, we may ſay that it doth not ſearch for ſuch, but as that anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Painter, that choſe rather to cover with a veil the face of <hi>Aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memnon,</hi> then venture to repreſent his grief: it alſo chuſeth rather to refrain tears, and words, and not to paint forth the greatneſs of its affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, then to be forced to paint it by the ſame things which the ſmalleſt of afflictions make uſe of. If any one be not ſatisfied with all theſe reaſons, it may yet poſſibly be added, that, as we ſaid before, a moderate com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing of the inward parts, may ſqueeze forth the humidity of tears; and a too violent compreſſion of the ſame parts may, on the contrary, keep them in, by cloſing up the paſſages by which they uſe to come to the eyes.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="12" type="problem">
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:60121:51"/>
            <head>
               <hi>PROB. 12.</hi> What is the reaſon ſome things are gotten beſt by neglecting them?</head>
            <p>WE ſaid in the fore-going <hi>Problem,</hi> that a Paſſion being wrought to a very high pitch, is an obſtacle to its ſelf, and hinders us from arriving at what we aim at. Now we will endeavour to give a reaſon of a difficulty like to that, but yet greater, <hi>viz.</hi> Why there are many things which are beſt acquired by neglecting them, and looking another way. Thus for example, the Philoſophers have obſerved to us, that <hi>Glory</hi> is of ſuch a nature, that the beſt means to get it, is to run away from it, and not to deſire it, and that ſhe favours thoſe moſt, that do leaſt regard her. <hi>Pleaſure,</hi> if we conſider it well, is like to it in this: for the ſoul being ſoftened through
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:60121:52"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:60121:52"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:60121:53"/>
the love of pleaſure, and reſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes ſo ſenſible of incommodities and griefs, ſo vulnerable by all ſorts of croſſes, and ſo feeble, that the leaſt thing wounds it mortally, and makes it deſpair; and even the ſmalleſt misfortunes become great unto it: On the contrary, the contempt of pleaſure gives it preſently a more ſtrong conſtitution, by which it ſuſtains the ſhock of evils that would diſturb her reſt and her pleaſures, and by taking away her delicacy, makes her not to ſtand in need of <hi>extream</hi> pleaſures to be delighted, but to be ſatisfied if ſhe have <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> ones. In <hi>Eloquence</hi> and <hi>Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation,</hi> there are alſo many <hi>Graces</hi> which are not gotten if one <hi>affects</hi> to have them, and muſt, as I may ſo ſay, <hi>eſcape</hi> from us without our know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, to be <hi>natural and charming.</hi> But I need not enlarge here into any large diſcourſe, to prove this verity by many examples, ſeeing we meet with it at every turn in the things of
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:60121:53"/>
our life, and that even the vulgar confeſs it and alledge it very often, though they are ignorant of the cauſe of it. But it conſiſts in this, that <hi>all thoſe things that are beſt got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by neglecting them, are vanities;</hi> for our ſoul weakens it ſelf by the deſire of vanities; but on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary ſhe fortifies her ſelf, and gets more light and ſolidity, when ſhe with-draws her affection from them, and by theſe new forces, which by this means ſhe acquires, ſhe obtains afterwards not only greater advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages, but alſo even thoſe ſlight ones which ſhe contemned; for theſe ſlight and vain good things are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly appendixes to ſolid ones, and follow them as images and ſhadows follow bodies.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="13" type="problem">
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:60121:54"/>
            <head>
               <hi>PROB. 13.</hi> What is the reaſon that thoſe things to which we are accuſtomed, are not prejudicial to our health?</head>
            <p>THere is nothing more common then that ſaying, that things which we are accuſtomed to, are not prejudicial to our health; and there is commonly a reaſon given of it, with which men are ſatisfied, <hi>viz. that Cuſtom is a ſecond Nature.</hi> But certainly I conceive, that he which will a little caſt the eye of his mind upon this anſwer, and conſider it at his leiſure, will ſee it vaniſh. For <hi>Cuſtom</hi> hath indeed ſome power up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our inclinations, and on the things which depend on the <hi>ſoul:</hi> but I do not ſee that it hath the ſame power in natural changes, and things that depend purely of the <hi>body.</hi> To un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand it clearly, Suppoſe that a
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:60121:54"/>
man ſhould a hundred times hold ſome Combuſtible body very near the fire, you will ſee plainly that it will never accuſtom it ſelf to endure the power of it, without receiving harm; nay, on the contrary, it will conſume by little and little: Even ſo, if moiſture be contrary to the welfare of a body, it is very manifeſt that it will never accuſtom it ſelf ſo well to be moiſtened, but it will ſtill receive dammage from the wet. Since then this anſwer is not ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factory, ſhould we not rather ſay, that there cannot be rendred any univerſal reaſon of it, but that it happens oftentimes for ſeveral par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular reaſons, which have nothing of common, that many things ceaſe to hurt after that one hath been ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed to them? As for example, <hi>Cold</hi> doth not hurt him that is uſed to endure it, becauſe it ſhuts up the pores and thickens the skin; and that he that hath a thick skin, and his pores cloſed, muſt needs be more
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:60121:55"/>
difficultly hurt by external qualities. On the contrary, he that is uſed to walk bare-headed in the field, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives no hurt from the heat of the Sun, as may be ſeen in the <hi>Bohemians</hi> children, and in the Peaſants of ſome part of <hi>France,</hi> by reaſon that this very heat hath ſucked by little and little from their brains, all thoſe hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midities which might have bred Rheumes or Catarrhs. <hi>Violent labour</hi> alſo doth not hurt thoſe that are uſed to it, for that it dryes the Nerves, and the Nerves cannot be dryed, but they are hardened, nor hardened without becoming ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and fitter either to bear a great weight, or to thruſt a thing with ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemency. Or elſe, is there in it ſome groſs miſtake? and ſhould we not rather ſay, that things which we are uſed to, do not ceaſe to hurt, becauſe they have loſt the power to do it, through uſe: but that when a man hath long uſed a thing, without fall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into any remarkable inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:60121:55"/>
it is a ſign it was not contrary to him at the firſt, although it ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be ſo: and therefore Phyſitians do very wiſely permit him to uſe it for the future. Or elſe (if we muſt however find out ſome reaſon com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to all the effects which this Problem comprehends) doth it not conſiſt in this, that as oftentimes <hi>Good</hi> is in the <hi>middle,</hi> and <hi>Evil</hi> in the <hi>extreams;</hi> ſo alſo on the contrary that ſometimes <hi>Evil</hi> is only in the <hi>mean,</hi> and <hi>Good</hi> in the <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treams,</hi> ſo that an hurtful thing having by length of time brought our temper into ſome extream, it may by this means deliver us from the evil which it brought upon us. But that <hi>Evil is ſometimes in the middle, and Good in the extreams,</hi> there are that prove it by ſeveral reaſons: For they ſay that the <hi>higher</hi> and the <hi>lower</hi> regions of the air are more calm then the <hi>middle</hi> region, in which ſtorms and tempeſts are formed; that the extream <hi>force</hi> or
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:60121:56"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:60121:56"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:60121:57"/>
extream <hi>weakneſs</hi> of the Suns rayes do equally render the air ſerene: but that when they have only a moderate force, they <hi>raiſe</hi> vapours which they cannot <hi>ſcatter:</hi> That man ſhould either not reaſon at all, but follow plain common ſenſe, as the Peaſants do, or elſe reaſon exactly and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foundly, and become truly learned; becauſe reaſoning by halves, and being learned by halves, is the way to embroyl ones ſelf in a thouſand doubts that others know not; that Angels and things inanimate are equally incapable of miſery; but that thoſe natures that are in the middle between theſe two extreams, are only ſubject unto it. Though theſe examples be taken from things far remote from the matter in hand, yet they may bring us to a belief that it is many times after the ſame manner in things which belong to the health of our bodies.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="14" type="problem">
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:60121:57"/>
            <head>
               <hi>PROB. 14.</hi> Whence comes it, that (as it is the ſaying of ſome body) a great ſervice is not ſo proper to gain our affection, as many petty ſervices done in a continued ſecies and on all occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions?</head>
            <p>IS it not becauſe a <hi>great ſervice</hi> may be received in an <hi>inſtant,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as this train of petty ſervices takes up in the gaining of our heart, a great deal of <hi>time,</hi> which muſt needs help forward the buſineſs mightily with all ſorts of cauſes? Or elſe is it that when any ones beneficence deſcends upon us thus by little and little, and as it were <hi>drop by drop,</hi> we do at the ſeveral times we receive it, make more ſeveral reflections upon the obligation which he layes upon us, ſo that thus his benefits do <hi>ſink</hi> the better to our hearts, like herein
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:60121:58"/>
to a <hi>gentle</hi> and <hi>ſoft rain</hi> falling by little and little, which penetrates better into the earth, whereas great and <hi>violent ſhowers</hi> only ſweep it and run away without ſoaking in? Or elſe, is it that this continued train of petty devoires and ſervices, each of which apart is not of any conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, leads us to amity and good liking by ſo ſweet and gentle a force, and brings us on ſo inſenſibly, that we perceive it not, and ſo make no reſiſtance? Or elſe, as we love more thoſe meats which having delighted the <hi>palate</hi> do not lie heavy upon our <hi>ſtomacks;</hi> do we not in ſome ſort love more for the ſame reaſon the ſervices that do us good, and yet leave no weight of neceſſary and forced <hi>obligation</hi> upon our <hi>ſpirits;</hi> as queſtionleſs petty ſervices often reiterated do, becauſe that on one ſide their number ſupplies their weakneſs, and makes them counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile a great benefit all at once; and that on the other ſide they are of
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:60121:58"/>
ſuch a nature, that he which did them cannot handſomely reproach them to us? Whence it comes that the acknowledgement we preſerve of them in our minds, ſeems to us to be the more voluntary. Or elſe that which we ſearch for, proceeds it not hence, that he which doth us a great good turn, is believed by us to do it out of vanity, to gain the reputation of generouſneſs or boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, becauſe a great ſervice makes a noiſe, and is expoſed to view; but that we cannot ſuſpect the ſame of him who is aſſiduous to render us a thouſand petty devoires, which appear not to the eyes of others, and are perceived only by our ſelves? Or elſe ſhall we ſay, that one may do us a great ſervice in our abſence, but that this train of petty ſervices preſuppo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> that he that would make himſelf be beloved, is not abſent from him by whom he deſires to be beloved: but that on the contrary, he converſes ordinarily
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:60121:59"/>
with him; and that this familiarity is that which aids him principally to inſinuate himſelf into our heart? Or laſtly, doth not this alſo contribute to it, that when we have received ſome notable benefit from another, as it is a thing commonly known, it happens many times, that thoſe whoſe intereſt it is to make us forget it, have ſo much artifice to extenuate it, to give it ill interpretations, and to take away its luſtre and weight, that they ſeduce us, and extinguiſh in us the reſentment which we ſhould have had of it; whereas when any one hath inſinuated himſelf into our favour, and hath witneſſed to us the ardour of his affections in many occurrences, by petty ſervices which have not been obſerved by others, the reſentment which we have thereof is not expoſed the aſſaults of his enemies, or rivals; and he is ſo much the more aſſured, the more it is ſecret and the cauſe of it not known?</p>
         </div>
         <div n="15" type="problem">
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:60121:59"/>
            <head>
               <hi>PROB. 15.</hi> What is the reaſon that a great joy makes us facile to pardon injuries?</head>
            <p>IT is certain that a great <hi>joy</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes us extreamly to clemency, that it <hi>ſoftens</hi> our hearts, and expells that <hi>hardneſs</hi> and <hi>bitterneſs</hi> which injuries have cauſed in them, and makes us eaſie to pardon them; and as it is a thing certain, and ſuch whereof the enquiry cannot be otherwiſe than curious, pleaſant, and profitable; I conceive I have reaſon to allow it a place among'ſt theſe <hi>Problems,</hi> and endeavour to diſcover all the cauſes of it. In the firſt place then, I believe I ſhall ſpeak a very great truth, if I ſay, that our ſoul being ſurprized on a ſudden by a great happineſs, finds it ſelf ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obliged to ſome <hi>ſoveraign</hi> power, and hath ſecret motions of <hi>gratitude</hi>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:60121:60"/>
towards it; and that finding its ſelf unable to do it any good whereby to teſtifie its thanks, it is ſo much the more conſtrained to do good to his <hi>works,</hi> that is to ſay, that it becomes good, and diſpoſed to do good, even to thoſe that have wronged it. But beſides this reaſon, which without doubt contributes very much to the effect we ſpeak of, I conceive that <hi>Joy</hi> doth beſides of its own nature beautifie the <hi>ſoul,</hi> as well as it beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifies the <hi>countenance.</hi> And indeed, ſeeing that <hi>Joy</hi> is more according to nature than <hi>Sadneſs,</hi> ſeeing it is a <hi>Good,</hi> as Sadneſs is an <hi>Evil,</hi> it muſt needs for this reaſon inſpire alſo into it and waken the paſſions that are more conform to nature, and better than thoſe which are awaken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>Sadneſs.</hi> Now there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more according to nature then <hi>Goodneſs.</hi> If it be objected that <hi>Affliction</hi> corrects us, and makes us better; I anſwer, that it doth not do it out of its own nature, but by
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:60121:60"/>
accident, as a medicine cures us by accident, although at other times it be a kind of poyſon, and is alwayes in ſome ſort contrary to the temper of our bodies. For if we conſider affliction in its ſelf, we ſhall finde that as it is the property of winter and ill weather to kill flowers and to deſpoile the trees of the ornament of their foliage, even ſo it blaſts the beauties of the ſoul, ſoures and debaſes it. But above all we ſhall finde, that in cooling and weakening the courage it greatly impaires that generoſity from whence iſſues the pardon of injuries. Philoſophers ſay that <hi>Light</hi> doth naturally beget <hi>Heat,</hi> although it be not a quality of the ſame <hi>ſpecies</hi> with it, by reaſon of a certain affinity or correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of nature which is between them. I ſuppoſe it is for the ſame reaſon that <hi>Joy</hi> may beget in the ſoul goodneſs and vertuous inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, though its ſelf be not a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous inclination, ſince that being a
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:60121:61"/>
good paſſion, it muſt have ſome analogy with all the good paſſions, as <hi>ſadneſs</hi> muſt have alſo with all the bad ones. But to come to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of another cauſe of the ſame effect, it ſeems alſo that as an injury made us not angry, but out of an opinion we had that it had caſt us down, when any great proſperity comes to raiſe us up, it muſt for this reaſon appeaſe and ſweeten the grief which this pretended dejectment hath cauſed in us, ſince that it doth in ſome ſort do us reaſon. Or elſe, perhaps the ſoul, in a great pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, looking on the preſent which ſmiles upon it, and offers it nothing but matter of ſatisfaction, and a moſt perfect reſt, doth equally take its eye off, both from what is to come, and what is paſt, and therefore hates to remember paſſed injuries, ſince that it cannot do it without looking off from the preſent which is ſo grateful to it, and interrupting its delicious employment: but that
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:60121:61"/>
which ſtill puts it more ſtrongly upon the ſame reſolution, is, that having all on a ſudden received a great bleſſing, it doth paſſionately deſire to enjoy it fully, and not corrupt the ſweetneſs thereof, and that there is nothing can ſo corrupt its ſweetneſs, as a motion of hatred and revenge. For as the act of <hi>Loving</hi> is in its ſelf naturally ſweet, becauſe it is very much according to nature: ſo the motions of <hi>Hatred</hi> are naturally painful and mingled with grief, becauſe they croſs nature; and becauſe the ſoul doth as I may ſo ſay, wreſt and diſtort its ſelf, in receiving them into it, and doth ill employ its faculties. Now that all motion of revenge and hatred of another is naturally painfull and mixed with grief, is a thing that may eaſily be proved. For, beſides that our own ſenſe makes us acknowledge it to be true, we need only to look upon the viſage of man in choler, to confeſſe that nothing doth more reſemble the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:60121:62"/>
viſage of a man that is ſad; and there appears ſomething of painfull and forced, ſomewhat like to that one ſees in the face of a <hi>Porter</hi> employed with all his ſtrength to lift up a great burthen. It is even ſo alſo in all other motions of Hate. For in a word, it is as unimaginable, that a man ſhould machinate any <hi>black</hi> deſignes, and frame within himſelf ſome malicious contrivance, without loſing the native <hi>quiet</hi> and <hi>ſereni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie</hi> of his ſpirit, as that the air ſhould continue ſerene when it is formed into ſtorms and tempeſts, and that it ſhould be overſpread with dark clouds, before it pours down either hail or thunderbolts upon the earth. And as the ſpring of a Piſtol is not at reſt, and as it were in its due place, ſo long as it is cockt, and ready to give fire and kill: So our ſoul is without doubt reſtleſs, and out of its repoſe, ſo long as it continues as it were bent to the execution of ſome malicious act, and is ready to
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:60121:62"/>
do miſchief to another. And if we will deſcend from the conſideration of men to that of beaſts, we ſhall there alſo finde ſome teſtimonies of this truth, ſince that they which when they are alone, ſeem to take pleaſure in, conſidering the beauty of the day, of the meadows, of the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers and forreſts, and are moſt light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome and ſportive, are alſo the moſt innocent; and that, on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, all the ſavage and blood-thirſty ones are ſad and melancholy, which may be ſeen both by their counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and in that they hate and fly the light. It is wiſdom therefore in us to drive from our mindes all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious thoughts when we would fully enjoy any great happineſs: Or elſe, the joy which a good fortune cauſes in us, renders us ſweet and eaſie to pardon injuries, becauſe after having gotten <hi>external</hi> goods, we do the more violently deſire thoſe that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect the <hi>ſoul,</hi> namely <hi>wiſdom,</hi> and <hi>vertue,</hi> as thoſe only which we
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:60121:63"/>
want, and which remain to us to deſire.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="16" type="problem">
            <head>
               <hi>PROB. 16.</hi> What is the reaſon there is ſo much falſe news spread abroad, and that many delight to make others believe ſtrange things?</head>
            <p>IS it not becauſe a man thinks he doth not do very ill, nor traſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe much the Law of Liberty, to add to that which he receives from others, ſome ſmall matter, or to take from it ſome petty and ſlight circumſtance, which yet changes the whole face of the thing; an abſurdity like to that of an ill pay-maſter, that thought he did not any great hurt, and was no diſhoneſt man, in taking away a ſmall cypher from a paper wherein his debt was contained, and in his defrauding his Creditor of a great ſum under pretence that
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:60121:63"/>
he took away and blotted out only a ſmall <hi>cyfer?</hi> Or elſe, do not falſe news ariſe principally from hence, that we wholly give credit to our friends when they tell us ſtrange things; and that, on the contrary, our friends enlarge the wonder to us, becauſe they ſee we are delighted with it, and that they are unwilling to deprive us of it by diſabuſing us, and take from us that delightful error in which we are, no more then they would wake us if they knew we were in a pleaſant dream? Or elſe, is it becauſe many men think they do well to make uſe of a <hi>lye</hi> to uphold the <hi>Truth?</hi> Or elſe, are we not chiefly deceived by falſe relations, becauſe we think it rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable to give credit to one that is no bad man, but hath on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary much of goodneſſe; whereas we ſhould conſider whether he be not guilty, of ſome weakneſſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe a man lyes through <hi>weakneſs</hi> as well as <hi>malice?</hi> Or laſtly, may we
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:60121:64"/>
not ſay that ill news is ſpread prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally for this reaſon, that many pleaſe themſelves in making others believe ſtrange things? the truth is, experience evidently diſcovers this malady with which they are affected; and if it be demanded why they are thus delighted with it, methinks one may ſay, it is either becauſe they would have theſe great and ſtrange things be ſo, and that being unable to give them a <hi>real</hi> exiſtence, they give them at leaſt a <hi>ſhaddow</hi> of it in printing them upon the ſpirits of men: Or that half-believing them, and taking pleaſure to believe them, they labour to confirme themſelves in their opinion, by drawing many others to be of it, and acquiring to it good ſtore of ſuffrages; or that being unable to believe them in any ſort, yet when they ſee that an ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther believes them, they contemplate the joy which they imprint on his eyes, and on his viſage, and hear the exclamations which admiration
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:60121:64"/>
forces from him, and the geſtures it puts him in, and receive hereby ſome <hi>reflection</hi> of his pleaſure; like in this to many ſick people, who though they cannot eat themſelves, yet de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light to ſee others eat with a good appetite?</p>
         </div>
         <div n="17" type="problem">
            <head>
               <hi>PROB. 17.</hi> What is the reaſon that having been long on horſe-back, a man doth better refreſh himſelf by walking a little on foot, than by ſitting ſtill?</head>
            <p>IS it not that as a <hi>colour</hi> is more contrary to a <hi>colour</hi> then to a <hi>ſmell</hi> or a <hi>ſound,</hi> by the ſame reaſon one <hi>motion</hi> is more contrary to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>motion</hi> then to <hi>reſt,</hi> and ſo eaſier effaces the impreſſion of it, by that Law which ſaith that things which are under the ſame <hi>genus</hi> do more vigorouſly combate one another? Or elſe, is it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap> body of the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:60121:65"/>
horſe, on which we have been a long time, hath too much preſſed many parts of ours, and by this means ſhut up certain paſſages; and that when we walk, the ſpirits running to theſe parts to move them, do raiſe them up, and by this means open whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever was there preſſed, or too much ſtraightned, ſo that they ſoon reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver their natural ſituation?</p>
         </div>
         <div n="18" type="problem">
            <head>
               <hi>PROB. 18.</hi> What is the reaſon that when we come to reſt our ſelves after much walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing we finde our ſelves more weary a while after?</head>
            <p>IS it becauſe the heat which moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on drew into our parts rendred them more ſupple, and obedient to the will, in dilitating the nerves; and that after we have reſted a while we have loſt this heat, but we have not loſt our wearineſſe? Or elſe, is
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:60121:65"/>
is becauſe when we walk, our ſweat runs down; but when we come afterwards to reſt, it ſticks upon our skin and benums it, by its humidity, as alſo by its coldneſſe, when the repoſe of the body hath given it means to grow cold? We ſee by experience, that thoſe that come from ſwiming, feel their arms and legs weak, as if they had been beaten, by reaſon of a cold moiſture that reſts upon them. It is obſerved likewiſe, that when after a long motion we come to reſt our ſelves, we ſweat preſently much more; and this is becauſe the motion of the parts of our body doth not then hinder that by which the drops of ſweat do deſcend by their narrow paſſages, the pores. For, as every body knows, two ſeveral motions do very often hinder one the other.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="19" type="problem">
            <pb n="66" facs="tcp:60121:66"/>
            <head>
               <hi>PROB. 19.</hi> Why is it good not to let a wicked man that hath power to do what miſchief he pleaſe, perceive that we are jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of him?</head>
            <p>IT is good, firſt, becauſe he that would do wrong unjuſtly, hath yet need of a <hi>pretence,</hi> which how vain and frivolous ſoever it be, may at the leaſt amuſe his ſpirit, and hinder him from conſidering and clearly diſcerning the uglineſſe and injuſtice of his action. For, as he that is reſolved to be let blood, and hath ſtretched forth his arm, yet turns his head another way out of a certain horrour which nature hath of every thing that hurts any part of our body: So he that is reſolved to do an unjuſt and wicked action, doth yet turn away his eyes from the injuſtice which he ſees in it, out of
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:60121:66"/>
a natural horrour, and endeavours not to ſee it at all, or at leaſt to ſee it leſſe clearly. This is very hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomely repreſented by <hi>Eſope,</hi> in the fable of the <hi>Wolfe</hi> and the <hi>Lamb</hi> that drank at the ſide of the ſame river; for though the Wolfe was reſolved to devour the Lamb, and ſaw that it was beſt for him to do it preſently, for fear leaſt any one ſhould come to her ſuccour, yet he ſtayed a while to reaſon with her, being not able to put himſelf on this action, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſetting before his eyes ſome <hi>colour</hi> and <hi>ſhew</hi> of juſtice. He begins therefore to complain, that ſhe <hi>troubled</hi> the water; but becauſe ſhe replied that this could not be, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe drank a great way <hi>below</hi> him, which was ſo clear a reaſon that it ſhut out all appearance of the contrary, he could not yet fall to the committing of this evil, but ſeeks another pretence ſomewhat leſſe void of colour, in telling her that ſhe knew well enough, that her
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:60121:67"/>
Father and Mother and all her An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors had been his enemies. Not but that this ſecond reaſon was very extravagant, ſeeing it was the ſole cruelty of the Wolfe, which had bred in the Anceſtors of the Lamb this hatred, which made them only <hi>avoid,</hi> not <hi>wrong</hi> him: but nevertheleſſe this pretence for want of another, ſerved to furniſh him with ſome ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of Juſtice, without which nature cannot be moved or under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take any thing. According to this then, though a wicked man may be reſolved to do us a miſchief, and hath power to do it, yet he wants a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, which he may uſe towards himſelf, and whereby he may (if I may be bold to ſay ſo) finde obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in his own faculties; We ſhould be therefore ſo far from venturing to furniſh him with one, that we ought carefully to remedy all things from which he may draw one. But we ſhall furniſh him with a pretence and ſhadow of reaſon, if we let him
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:60121:67"/>
ſee that we diſtruſt him, although it be not without juſt occaſion; and this ſhadow of reaſon will ſerve him to conquer that reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance which he findes in his own nature. Secondly, it is good not to give wicked men any teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that we diſtruſt them, becauſe if they believe that we cannot ſo much as imagine they are about to commit a great injuſtice, they will judge us the honeſter, and farther from all treacherous and evil thoughts, and ſo will be more aſhamed to ſin before us, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover to us the baſeneſſe and ug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe of their ſouls. Beſides, if a wicked man thinks that we eſteem him an honeſt man, he cannot without regret go about to deſtroy by his actions this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief which is advantageous and glorious to him; and will be ſo much the more loth to do it, as he believes, that it is well eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed in our minds, becauſe that
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:60121:68"/>
in doing it, he ſees he wrongs himſelf: but on the contrary, if he thinks we have already an ill opinion of him, he will not have ſo great a deſire to acquire our eſteem, as he would to preſerve himſelf in it, were he poſſeſſed of it; becauſe the deſire of <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving</hi> that which a man hath, is more natural then that of <hi>getting.</hi> In the fourth place, if he believe that we are in a profound and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire ignorance of the wrong he intends us, he ſees by the ſame means, that in doing it he will cauſe us more grief, then if we had expected it, and provided our ſelves for it. Now the wickedeſt man hath naturally more of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnance to bring a great grief upon any one then a little one. Laſtly, beſides all theſe reaſons, there is this ſtill to be conſidered, that if any one thinks that men account him an honeſt man, or that they do not think him very
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:60121:68"/>
bad, this ſerves to perſwade him, that what is believed of him, is true, and that indeed he hath not very bad inclinations. Now there is no better, nor handſomer way of reforming by degrees the mind of a wicked man, then to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade him that he hath ſome ſeeds of vertue, and an inclination to worthy things, becauſe that loving himſelf, and every thing that is in him, he will conſequently love vertue, if he believes that it is one of his qualities, and a part of his being; and he will alſo love ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous men if he thinks he is like them, as he would love a man that hath noſe or eyes like his own. In a word, it is certain that every one acts according to the <hi>Idea</hi> that he hath of himſelf, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that which he believes himſelf to be: for, thoſe objects which we have moſt ordinarily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our minds, do by degrees communicate their qualities to our
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:60121:69"/>
ſouls, and our actions; Now there is no object any man hath more frequently before his mind then himſelf, ſo that if he believes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf wicked, the image which he hath of himſelf muſt needs exaſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate him and make him ſtill worſe and worſe; On the contrary, if he thinks himſelf inclined to good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, this belief muſt needs ſweeten him by little and little and inſpire into him better inclinations. This is all we have to ſay upon this <hi>Problem,</hi> which methinks we have by this means ſufficiently illuſtrat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: But yet we believe we ſhould by the way add, that the <hi>Rule</hi> which it gives, is not alwayes true; for herein are many <hi>Diſtinctions</hi> to be uſed: and eſpecially we muſt have a care, whether he whoſe injuſtice we fear, be a man <hi>intirely</hi> wicked, or whether he have <hi>ſome</hi> good principles, and be not yet fully reſolved to do injuſtly: For if he be abſolutely wicked, we muſt
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:60121:69"/>
not let him ſee that we diſtruſt him, for the aforeſaid reaſons; but if he hath ſomething of generous, and be not wholly confirmed in his evil reſolution, it is many times good to let him perceive (but with humility and without bitterneſs, and rather obliquely then in a direct and open manner) that we ſee well enough he intends to wrong us, that our unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs is manifeſt unto us, and that we have not any hope. For, beſides that this raiſes more pitty in him, it troubles him to be accounted more unjuſt then he is, and having ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of generous in him, he la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours to refute by his actions this ill opinion which we have of him, and deſires to ſhew unto us that we were in an errour when we had ſuch a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit of him.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="20" type="problem">
            <pb n="74" facs="tcp:60121:70"/>
            <head>
               <hi>PROB. 20.</hi> Whence comes it that Beaſts do natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally know how to ſwim, and that Man hath need to learn?</head>
            <p>THey anſwer commonly, that Man doth not naturally know how to ſwim, as Beaſts do, becauſe that the firſt time he tryes to do it, he is ſeized with a <hi>Fear</hi> which hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders him from making uſe of his legs and arms freely. But I do not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove this anſwer; for beaſts have at leaſt as much fear as man, the firſt time one caſts them into the water; and I have ſeen ſome of them that would tremble for fear a long time after, and remain a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoniſht, and for all that ceaſed no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to ſwim very well. Beſides, if it were only <hi>Fear</hi> that hindred man from knowing how to ſwim, this would be nothing to them that are
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:60121:70"/>
very bold, and caſt themſelves with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out fear into great dangers; and a man in this caſe would know at leaſt how to ſwim in the water of a <hi>Bath,</hi> in the midſt of a company of his <hi>friends,</hi> ſince that then he would have nothing to fear: Or elſe he would know how to ſwim in a very narrow brook, where the bottom may be ſeen all the way, and can leave him no conſiderable fear. Since therefore this anſwer doth not ſuffice, and leaves the difficulty wholly untoucht: I conceive rather, that a man doth not naturally know how to ſwim, becauſe the firſt time he tries, he cannot chooſe but man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage his legs and arms by <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and that this hinders him from doing it right, becauſe it is an action that muſt be done by the <hi>imagination</hi> only, after a brutiſh and blind man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. We ſee clearly by experience, that there are many things which we do worſt, when we would do them by <hi>Reaſon.</hi> Beſides, I believe it is
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:60121:71"/>
naught for a man, the firſt time he tries to ſwim; to be prepoſſeſt with this belief, that he doth not know how to ſwim; whereas beaſts are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt from all this preoccupation: for, to believe infallibly that one doth not know how to do any thing, is a diſpoſition to do it ill, and to come ſcurvily off. But, beſides theſe two reaſons, in my opinion it is very remarkable, that when beaſts ſwim, they are in their <hi>natural</hi> poſture, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they have not an <hi>erect</hi> ſtature; and do move according as they have an inclination to move naturally, namely, with all their feet at once; and that on the contrary, man lying at his length upon the water to ſwim, is not in the poſture in which he ſhould naturally be, and ſo hath the greater pains to move himſelf in this manner, as even upon the earth it would be painful to him to march upon all four. Or elſe I may ſay upon this ſubject, that the difficulty is not ſo much to know why crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:60121:71"/>
that are much more <hi>light</hi> than man, are more proper to ſwim; but why he doth not know how to ſwim as well as Oxen, horſes, and ſuch other creatures that are <hi>heavier</hi> than he: To which I anſwer, that it is becauſe Oxen, and Horſes, and ſuch other beaſts, have an inward capacity and cavity of their bodies much greater, which is the cauſe that though their bodies ſink deeper under water by reaſon of their weight, there yet remains part there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of above; and that it happens to them as it doth to veſſels that are high built, to wit, that they continue above the water, whileſt others that are not ſo much laden, but are much leſs, do ſink. Or elſe too, one may rationnlly ſay, that beaſts do natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally ſwim, becauſe they have for the moſt part a longer neck than man, ſo that although all the reſt of the body be heavy enough to ſink under water, yet in holdlng up their necks they take their breath at eaſe;
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:60121:72"/>
whereas mans body being ready na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally to ſink under water as well as theirs, he hath not a neck long enough, to keep his head notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding out of the water, and by this means keep himſelf from being choaked. So then <hi>Beaſts</hi> have in this received from nature divers advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages above <hi>Man,</hi> in which ſhe hath not done him any wrong, but on the contrary hath manifeſted the ſame wiſdom which ſhe ſhews in all other things, that ſhe is guided by a moſt admirable and penetrating judgement, which fore-ſees things that depend upon a long train of conſequences. For, this wiſdom foreſaw that <hi>Man</hi> only among all other creatures ſhould know how to make <hi>Boats</hi> and <hi>Bridges,</hi> or to paſs the rivers on <hi>Horſ back.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="21" type="problem">
            <pb n="79" facs="tcp:60121:72"/>
            <head>
               <hi>PROB. 21.</hi> What is the reaſon that the fruits which grow at the tops of the boughs are the beſt?</head>
            <p>IS it becauſe that which is moſt <hi>earthy</hi> and <hi>groſs</hi> in the nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, cannot reach to the tops of the boughs, ſo that they receive only that which is more <hi>ſubtile,</hi> and doth eaſier find paſſage through the nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row ſtreights of the wood? Or elſe, is it becauſe that the tops of the branches are the <hi>neweſt</hi> and <hi>youngeſt</hi> parts of the tree, and that for this reaſon they have the more vertue? Or elſe, is it for that the fruit which grows at the tops of the boughs, are more expoſed to the rayes of the <hi>Sun,</hi> which ripens them better? Or elſe, becauſe they are more expoſed to the beating of the rain, which ſerves to ſoften their hardneſs, and
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:60121:73"/>
to make them alſo ſweeter; as we ſee that fruit is ſometimes ſoftned between our hands, and made ſweeter according as we handle it? Or elſe is it, that when there is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of nouriſhment in a tree, it paſſeth to the extremities, after it hath provided for the neceſſities of all the other places; but that being arrived at the extremities, and not able to paſs further, it amuſes it ſelf, and ſo feeds thoſe fruits that grow there the better, which conſequently muſt have more of juice and of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour. Methinks one may expreſs the courſe of this nouriſhment by the example of a brook, which runs as long as it finds any way, but meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at laſt ſome obſtacle which is laid before it, and hinders it from paſſing further, it ſwells and gathers its waters into an heap. Or elſe, laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, is it that the nouriſhment, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as it aſcends from the root to the branches, is ſtill more and more concocted by the <hi>Natural heat</hi> of
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:60121:73"/>
the tree; ſo that for this cauſe it muſt needs be that which comes to the ends of the branches, muſt be moſt concocted, and moſt purified?</p>
         </div>
         <div n="22" type="problem">
            <head>
               <hi>PROB. 22.</hi> Why do good men think they ought to ſpeak in proper terms of other Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and Vices, but not of things that regard wantonneſs and corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Love?</head>
            <p>SOme antient Philoſophers diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſing upon the ſame Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which we have here propound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, have though that this modeſty which hinders us from ſpeaking plainly of things that belong to laſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viouſneſs, and the lower and more terreſtrial part of Love, was but an abuſe and vain ceremonie. Their reaſons were, that ſince we ſpeak in plain terms of all other vices, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſome are far worſe, and that we
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:60121:74"/>
dare pronounce the names of <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, Sacriledge, Impiety, Aſſaſſina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Cruelty,</hi> there is no colour of Reaſon why we ſhould not with the ſame boldneſs ſpeak of <hi>vicious Love,</hi> much leſs that we ſhould not dare to ſpeak of all the effects of <hi>lawful Love,</hi> which hath nothing in it ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regular. Whereunto they added, that whatever one might <hi>do</hi> without ſin, one might alſo <hi>ſpeak</hi> without ſin. <hi>Montaigne</hi> ſeems to have been of the ſame opinion; for in the firſt Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the third Book of his <hi>Eſſaies,</hi> he ſaies, <hi>that the rule which forbids us to expreſs ſome things in plain terms, is a falſe rule, and that he ſcorns to reckon it amongſt his true du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</hi> He ſaies afterwards, <hi>that it is the</hi> Daughter <hi>indeed of true wiſdom, as other things which reſpect Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, but a</hi> baſtard <hi>one; and that he which ſhould undeceive the world of it, would not perhaps do ſo much miſchief, becauſe man acquitting himſelf of theſe falſe offices, thinks himſelf diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:60121:74"/>
of ſo much of the obligation which he hath to natural offices.</hi> At laſt he adds, <hi>that it is only a ſparing of Vice, not to dare ſpeak of it, but by a Periphraſis.</hi> For my part, I think that the general opinion of men which is contrary hereto, muſt needs be better grounded, and that they have reaſon to look upon it as a piece of brutiſhneſs in thoſe that ſpeak plainly of whatſoever belongs to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poreal Love. And I do juſtly call this opinion <hi>general,</hi> whatever <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taigne</hi> was pleaſed to ſay, ſince there is no true Hiſtory found by which it may be proved that there was ever any people wholly void of this mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty; and although there have been ſome, doubtleſs it was only a ſavage people, and ſcarcely participant of common ſenſe, as certain Nations that have been lately diſcovered. And a thing doth not ceaſe to be of <hi>common</hi> ſenſe, though it be contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted out of ſimplicity by ſome <hi>particular</hi> people. And though we
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:60121:75"/>
could not tell how to anſwer to the ſubtilties here alledged againſt the general opinion, yet in my judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment it were not wiſdom to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believe it, and follow them. But for all that, I conceive the truth being on our ſide, will furniſh us with ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments to prove, that the objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which are urged againſt it, are weak and ill-grounded. For in the firſt place, <hi>Montaigne</hi> himſelf, in that Chapter where he is ſo much againſt the common opinion in this buſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, doth nevertheleſs confeſs, <hi>that there is no action which ought ſo much to humble a man, as this which is here in queſtion; that they are the feet of the Peacock which abate his pride; that our weakneſs and vanity appear there in their beſt apparrel; that when he conſiders the circumſtances of it, he believes that ſaying of the Antients, That man was made by the gods to ſerve them for a May-game; that all other actions admit a wiſe and diſcreet proceeding, except this only; that all
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:60121:75"/>
other Paſſions trouble reaſon and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſail it, but that this doth wholly an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nihilate it.</hi> I think that in all this he ſaith nothing but truth, but we may from hence draw arguments againſt himſelf; and indeed this truth being ſuppoſed, we have ground to ſay, that then it is impudent and vitious to ſpeak openly of a thing, where the inconſtancy of our judgement and the weakneſs of our nature ſeems to be at its beſt, after a particular manner, becauſe it is a ſign that he which doth it, doth not much trouble himſelf with the perfection and dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of his ſoul; and that he doth without regret diſcover the defects and vanities of it. If it be further ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, that yet we ſpeak openly of <hi>Perfidiouſneſs, Sacriledge, Ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and Cruelty;</hi> To this I anſwer, that good men indeed do openly and without ſcruple, ſpeak of theſe things, and that no man is offended at it, becauſe it is preſuppoſed, they are things to which they are not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject.
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:60121:76"/>
It is not ſo in the follies and ſordid things which <hi>Love</hi> makes men commit, when for hope of a corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral pleaſure, it makes a man ſubmit himſelf with too much weakneſs to that ſex, which nature hath made in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour to him: For they are follies to which the beſt have been ſubject; they are weakneſſes from which good men are not totally exempt; and even thoſe which abominate all Cruelties, Treaſons, Thefts and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitudes, and hate them with a perfect hatred, do yet find them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves weak on this ſide; and that is the reaſon they cannot ſpeak of the more baſe and brutiſh part of this paſſion without bluſhing: and truly they would be impudent, if herein the memory of their infirmity did not produce this effect in them, and if they ſhould ſpeak openly and boldly of their vice, inſtead of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voiding the repreſentation of it to themſelves by formal and direct ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions. To confeſs that this is ſo,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:60121:76"/>
it is to be conſidered, that we ſhould think a rogue impudent and brutiſh without meaſure, if being ſurprized in the fact, and being queſtioned of the manner in which he committed his theft, he ſhould ſpeak of it at large, and with all the circumſtances, without bluſhing and caſting down his eyes for ſhame; and that on the contrary we ſhould think he had ſome remainders of probity left in him, when he dares not ſpeak of it but with difficulty and by halves, making us gueſs his meaning, rather than expreſſing it. Even ſo a man that we know hath committed a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Treaſon, would be thought very impudent, if he ſhould in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany make long diſcourſes of Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors and Treaſon, and if on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary ſuch kind of diſcourſe ſhould not put him into a kind of confuſion. In a word, it becomes him that knows himſelf guilty, to be aſhamed of every thing that repreſents to him his fault. And as for that which
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:60121:77"/>
was ſaid, <hi>that it is only a ſparing the vice of wantonneſs, not to ſpeak as openly of it as of others,</hi> it is as ill-grounded as the reſt. For as for a lye, parricide, murther, impiety, avarice, cowardize and vanity, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are things which have an uglineſs, which is <hi>eſſential</hi> to them, and therefore inſeparable, it is very true, that the more lively one can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe them, the more hatred and horrour he raiſes of them; nay it may be maintained, that a lively con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception of them is enough to make one fly them, without the aſſiſtance of any other diſcourſe; juſt as men run away from blows, or from an houſe on fire, without any need of perſwaſions. But it is quite other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in Corporal Love; for it hath no <hi>eſſential</hi> deformity, and is bad only by <hi>accident,</hi> namely, for want of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary <hi>circumſtances;</hi> and when it carries us in purſuit of its object with <hi>exceſs,</hi> or by baſe and unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy <hi>means.</hi> And therefore to mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:60121:77"/>
it, it is not at all neceſſary to ſet it forth to the life, but on the contrary, by how much the more lively and in proper terms it is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, ſo much the more doth the imagination of thoſe that hear ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcreet a leſſon, grow warm with that baſe heat which it is accuſtomed to kindle there. And hence I draw one ſtrong reaſon more, in favour of that truth I maintain. For ſince that to ſpeak in proper terms of this low and ignoble part of Love, is rather helping than weakening it, he that diſcourſes of it in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, muſt needs have a deſign to render it more violent, either in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf or others; both which are equally beaſtly. Or elſe it muſt needs be, that at the ſame time, he that talks thus, and that he is with his friends, whoſe converſe ought to elevate his ſoul to nobler and more ſpiritual pleaſures, he feels himſelf moved with that laſcivious and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſtrial ardour; otherwiſe he would
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:60121:78"/>
never love to repreſent to himſelf the effects thereof ſo diſtinctly, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are of ſuch a nature, that if the imagination be not delighted with them, it is wounded by them, it being not poſſible there ſhould be a <hi>medium</hi> between theſe two ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treams.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="23" type="problem">
            <head>
               <hi>PROB. 23.</hi> Whence comes it that they ſay, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever cures us, and is good for us, diſlikes us; and that on the contrary, we love that which hurts us?</head>
            <p>IS it that in this they do not ſay true, but that as the Time whileſt we are in ſadneſs ſeems to us longer, for the ſame reaſon the accidents which are offenſive to us, ſeem to us the more frequent? Truly I think that from this Source deſcend many other <hi>Vulgar Errours;</hi> as for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample theſe; That a man is hurt
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:60121:78"/>
ſooner in the ſame part where he is already ill: That the wittieſt chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren do commonly die before they can give their parents that content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which they hope for from them: That diſaſters follow one another, and ſcarce ever come ſingle: For as we deſire that theſe accidents ſhould never happen, ſo for fear leaſt they happen, we think that they happen alwayes. Or elſe, doth not the errour wherein men are in this buſineſs, proceed from hence, that when we love that which profits us, no man takes any notice of it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is a thing conformable to Reaſon and Nature, and upon which our ſpirit ſlides away ſmoothly, as our hand ſlides upon a poliſhed bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, where it finds no rub or obſtacle; and that on the contrary, when we love that which hurts us, as it is a thing that aſtoniſhes us, and makes us ſtick ſome time to ſearch the cauſes of it, ſo we ſee it the better, and imprint it the deeper into our
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:60121:79"/>
memories? Or elſe happens it not thus, in effect, through the imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of finite things, which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces alſo many other effects, that ſeem to be againſt nature? As for example, we ſee that Difficulty <hi>whets</hi> the appetite, whereas it ſhould rather <hi>dull</hi> it; and that Evil is more active then Good, although it ought to be quite contrary, and many other the like things; ſo that this may perſwade us, that it is through this very imperfection that wholſom things offend, and hurtful things de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light us? Or elſe, is it becauſe the remedy ought to be contrary to the diſeaſe, and that contraries redouble their force againſt one another by an <hi>Antiperiſtaſis?</hi> Phyſick for this reaſon doth at firſt heighten the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, and conſequently alſo the pain. And as Phyſick doth at firſt re-in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force and heighten the diſeaſe, may it not alſo be that hurtful things for the ſame reaſon do delight us more often at the firſt, and encreaſe our
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:60121:79"/>
vigour, and that therefore they pleaſe us? If we ſuppoſe for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, that a man be ſick for want of <hi>heat,</hi> it may be if he uſes <hi>cold</hi> things that are naught for him, they will at the firſt refreſh him and give him ſome ſtrength, by making of his heat increaſe, and redouble it ſelf by an <hi>Antiperiſtaſis.</hi> Or elſe, is not nature at firſt delighted with things that redouble its evil, becauſe that by increaſing it, they may in ſome ſort ſtupifie and dull its ſenſe? And is it not, on the contrary, hurt by thoſe things that cure it? becauſe that in reſtoring it to its ſtrength by little and little, they do as it were awaken it out of that lethargie in which the diſeaſe held it, and ſo make the ſenſe of it the more quick? Or elſe, is it that Nature when ſhe hath need to be cured, is depraved and ill diſpoſed: ſo that it is no wonder if in this condition ſhe be offended with that which is good, and pleaſed with that which is bad for her? Or
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:60121:80"/>
elſe, is it not that as a man cannot take a ſpot out of his <hi>clothes</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out making the place a little more thredbare, nor refine <hi>mettals</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diminiſhing them, nor cauſe any great good in a <hi>Common-wealth</hi> without wrong to ſome: ſo alſo we cannot cure our <hi>bodies</hi> of any great infirmity, but we muſt do it ſome dammage; and that as the remedy in curing us, doth us ſome hurt, this is the reaſon why it is irkſom to the ſenſe? If you ask me in particular, What is the reaſon that almoſt all Medicines are bitter, and odious to take? (wherein methinks a great part of the difficulty of this Problem conſiſts) I anſwer, that this hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens from its quality, becauſe if the Medicine were not offenſive to the <hi>palate,</hi> neither would it offend the <hi>ſtomach,</hi> ſeeing that it is from one and the ſame quality, that things which have been diſpleaſing to the taſte when they were in the mouth, do excite alſo a ſenſe of horrour in
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:60121:80"/>
the ſtomach and offend it. Now, if the Medicine do not raiſe a ſenſe of horrour in our ſtomachs, Nature would not uſe its utmoſt ſtrength to rid it ſelf of it, and would not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject together with it, the ill humours that made it ſick: for I think it is very probable, that it is by this means that moſt Medicines purge us.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="24" type="problem">
            <head>
               <hi>PROB. 24.</hi> What is the reaſon that Children in Winter, though their face and hands ſeem to ſhow that they are more af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted with cold than men grown, yet are not eaſily perſwaded to warm themſelves?</head>
            <p>IS it not becauſe to warm them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves they muſt <hi>ſtand ſtill</hi> a good while in the ſame place, and that Children love to be conſtantly in <hi>motion,</hi> out of a kind of Impatience, which is natural to our ſpirit at that
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:60121:81"/>
age? Or elſe is it, that when they are cold and come nigh to the fire, its heat at firſt inſtead of comforting, doth more afflict them; which hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens, becauſe it re-inforceth at firſt the cold of their bodies by an <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periſtaſis;</hi> and that as they want ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience and reaſon, and follow the firſt ſentiment of nature, they reject this wholſom remedy for want of knowledge to judge, that by and by they ſhall find comfort by it? Or elſe is it, that though their bodies be more eaſily altered by the cold, then thoſe of full grown men, as it is plain to the eye; yet this alteration is not ſo painful and grievous to them; the reaſon of it is, becauſe the cold hurts chiefly by too much hardening and making ſtiff all the parts of our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and that theirs are ſo tender and ſo ſoft, that by reaſon thereof, they cannot but very hardly be brought into the contrary extream?</p>
         </div>
         <div n="25" type="problem">
            <pb n="97" facs="tcp:60121:81"/>
            <head>
               <hi>PROB. 25.</hi> Whence comes it that when we are in affliction, we are better diverted by the repreſentation of ſome Tragick Hiſtory, or by the recital of ſome great misfortune, then by more mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſhews, or facetious tales?</head>
            <p>IS it that the ſoul, being lively af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted, ſhuns light and vain joyes, becauſe that without truely comforting it, and without taking away the grounds of its affliction, they do only dilate the ſpirits by a ſuperficial emotion of pleaſure, with which they tickle the imagination, and that this dilatation of the ſpirits cannot be but offenſive to the ſoul, if it ſtill keeps its ſadneſſe at the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom of the heart, ſince that it is for its good, and to the end that it may have the more ſtrength, it keeps them together in affliction? Indeed
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:60121:82"/>
it ſeems to be for this reaſon chiefly, that the ſoul being thus afflicted, doth thus fly from gay and delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome objects, and loves ſad ones; juſt as a weak eye hates chearful and light colours; and on the contrary, loves ſuch as are dark and have but little light. Or elſe, when we are profoundly afflicted, and are preſent at ſhows full of mirth, are we not diſpleaſed to ſee others laugh there with a moſt pure and perfect joy, becauſe this doth more ſadly put us in mind of our own misfortune: whereas in hearing read, or ſeeing acted a Tragick hiſtory we finde our ſelves leſſe unhappy by conſidering the miſeries befallen others? Or elſe, doth not the recital of other folks misfortune comfort us, chiefly for this reaſon, that for a time they take off our thoughts and affections to our ſelves, and fix them upon a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign object? Or elſe, is it that as they ſay nothing doth better drive out one love then another love? for
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:60121:82"/>
the ſame reaſon nothing doth better expell one ſad thought then another. Without doubt this reaſon is upon good ground, and to ſpeak more generally, when ever one deſires to take away from a man wholly and for ever, any ſtrong paſſion, one ſhould endeavour to put him firſt into ſome other paſſion that is nigh it. For when we have wrought any change in a mind that had given it ſelf up through length of time to ſome certain inclinations, we may after that bring him to what we pleaſe; as we ſee that when a man hath moved a ſtone a little out of its place, which long lying had faſtened to the earth, afterwards he draws it whither he pleaſes; Or elſe the ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe which Tragedies and other ſuch like ſpectacles beget, is it not more apt to diminiſh afflictions, then are other things more ſportful, for this univerſal reaſon, That an evil is alwayes more eaſily cured by another evil, then by a good, which
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:60121:83"/>
happens thus, becauſe to go from evil to good is a longer way, and muſt receive a greater change then to paſſe from one evil to another.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="26" type="problem">
            <head>
               <hi>PROB. 26.</hi> Why do ſome noiſes make a man ſleep?</head>
            <p>IS it that noiſes which one hears near at hand being only a <hi>moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of the <hi>air,</hi> or at leaſt ſuch as can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be formed unleſs the air be moved, do excite ſome <hi>motion</hi> in the organs of the <hi>brain,</hi> by ſtriking the air encloſed in the ears; and that this motion being very proper to hinder the operation of the ſpirit, makes a man ſleep? Or elſe, doth not the noiſe of wind or rain, or of a ſpring make us ſleep, by <hi>delighting</hi> us? And therefore we ſee alſo that many fall aſleep more eaſily when they make ſome part of their body be rubbed, through the <hi>pleaſure</hi> that
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:60121:83"/>
comes of it; and that children alſo ſleep ſooner and with the more fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cility, when we rock them, becauſe they <hi>love</hi> to be rocked? Indeed, that <hi>pleaſure</hi> may help to produce ſleep, methinks may further be proved, in that they which are in a great and profound pleaſure, whether of body or of mind, do ſhut their eyes, ſtretch their arms careleſly, and continue in the ſame poſture, as if they were really aſleep, and that we ſay pleaſure puts a man as it were into a ſound. But why hath Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure this property to be more apt to cauſe ſleep then the other paſſions of the ſoul? Is it not that the paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons being neceſſarily either plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, or griefs, or deſires, or hopes, or fears, the ſoul that hopes, or fears, or deſires, or ſuffers, is in ſolli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citude, and ſeaches every thing, and therefore it ſets its reaſon on work, and ſo hinders it ſelf of being ſeized by ſleep, whereas when it is in plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, it ſearches after nothing, being
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:60121:84"/>
content with the preſent, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore its reaſon ceaſes to act, and by ceaſing to act cauſes ſleep to enſue; juſt as Night comes when the Sun ceaſeth to ſhine. Beſides, noiſes that tickle the ear, do make us ſleep, not only becauſe they give us <hi>plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,</hi> but alſo becauſe this pleaſure is altogether <hi>ſenſual.</hi> For a <hi>ſpiritual pleaſure</hi> makes us imploy our <hi>reaſon,</hi> and ſo keeps up within us this <hi>intern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al light</hi> of the mind, which doth no leſſe hinder us from ſleeping then an <hi>external</hi> light which ſtrikes upon our eyes; and on the contrary, a pleaſure meerly <hi>corporal,</hi> is an obſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle to <hi>meditation.</hi> But why of ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual pleaſures doth that of <hi>hearing</hi> produce ſleep? Is it not becauſe it is that only which we can admit in an intire repoſe of the whole body, and without doing any thing on our part? For, for example, the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures that come from delightful <hi>ſavours,</hi> cannot be taſted without moving the tongue and jaws; and
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:60121:84"/>
we cannot alſo well enjoy a good <hi>odour</hi> if we do not make ſome effort to draw it in and ſmell it, nor can we well admit the pleaſures of the <hi>eye</hi> without turning the eyes this way and that, and without ſtraining to hold them open, by drawing back towards the forehead the skin that covers them: but to <hi>Hear</hi> you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſay we ſhould need to do any ſuch thing; Or elſe may we not explain this <hi>Problem</hi> thus, that a pleaſant noiſe which ſtrikes the Ear, produceth firſt a ſuſpenſion and ceſſation of all other thoughts, by that ſweetneſſe which charms us, and afterwards takes from us even the ſence of it ſelf: becauſe an object that hath been long preſent to the faculty, ſtrikes it no more, and is not perceived; which appears in that <hi>Cuſtom</hi> is ſo proper to render both good and bad things inſenſible to us, and that he which hath long had his mind fixt upon a work, that he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes, becomes unable to judge
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:60121:85"/>
rightly of it, untill he hath for a while given his mind ſome other object? But why muſt the noiſes which make one ſleep, be in ſome ſort <hi>uniform?</hi> and why, for inſtance, doth the noiſe of a <hi>ſpring,</hi> becauſe it is all of one kind, make us ſleep bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then of a <hi>muſical inſtrument,</hi> which yet is more ſweet? Is it that in noiſes which are not uniform, the ſame object is not alwaies preſent to the faculty, that they have in them <hi>grave</hi> or <hi>ſharpe</hi> ſounds, <hi>high</hi> or <hi>low, ſlower</hi> or <hi>ſwifter</hi> ones; whereas in noiſes that are uniform, it is preciſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the ſame object which is alwayes preſent to the faculty, and that by this means it may, after it hath effaced all other objects of our thoughts, efface it ſelf alſo, and make it ſelf imperceivable, by the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of its action, as we ſaid, and ſo beget ſleep? Or elſe is it that the pleaſure which is given us by the noiſe of a brook or a fountain, is a pleaſure purely <hi>ſenſual</hi> and of the
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:60121:85"/>
ear only; but that the pleaſure, which the harmony of a muſical in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument creates, is not a pleaſure of the ear only, but alſo of the <hi>imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation</hi> and of the <hi>memory,</hi> ſince that a man muſt compare in it one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord with another, and conſider the proportion of the ſounds to one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, to diſlike or approve it; and that ſeeing it exerciſeth the fancy and the memory, it is not to be won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, if it be not ſo proper to make a man ſleep?</p>
         </div>
         <div n="27" type="problem">
            <head>
               <hi>PROB. 27.</hi> What is the reaſon we aggravate our miſeries, and love to perſwade others that we are very unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate?</head>
            <p>IF we ſearch why we aggravate our misfortunes, we cannot deceive our ſelves in ſaying it is to perſwade others that we are very unfortunate.
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:60121:86"/>
But it is a greater difficulty to know for what reaſon we deſire they ſhould believe ſo, becauſe oftentimes they are perſons that we do not hope to receive any ſuccour from, and that our very miſery rendring us leſſe able to be uſeful to others, may hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der many baſe and mercenary minds from doing us any good. To enquire then the cauſe of this humour of the afflicted; is it not, in the firſt place, that they are never aſſured that any man may not for the future be in a capacity to help him; and therefore they tell their misfortunes to all they ſee, and aggravate them to them, to the end that if hereafter they ſhould diſcover any means to ſuccour them, the pitty which they have raiſed in them, may preſently produce its ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect? Or elſe do they deſire to have all that come near them know their evil, and believe it to be very great, thereby to incite them to give them ſome conſolation? Or do they not hope, that he to whom they have
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:60121:86"/>
aggravated their miſery, if he be not able to help them, may at the leaſt pray for them, and that theſe prayers may prevail with the divine good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe? Or elſe, do they not deſire that thoſe very perſons from whom they cannot hope for any ſuccour, ſhould bemoane them, for that they think that ſome body elſe that ſhall have the means to deliver them from their miſeries, will do it ſo much the more willingly, if he ſees that many perſons do compaſſionate him, and are affected therewith, becauſe the more general the good is which we are intreated to do, and the more perſons it regards, the more ready are we to do it? Or elſe is it that <hi>to be beloved</hi> being in it ſelf a good, we do therefore exaggerate our miſeries, thereby to raiſe pitty, and by pitty love, becauſe we know naturally that pitty is ſo near to love, that there is nothing more eaſie then to ſlip from one to the other? Or elſe, do we not deſire that a man ſhould
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:60121:87"/>
believe that we ſuffer very much, becauſe we deſire he ſhould talk much and long of us, both while we live and after our death, and that we foreſee that men will talk ſo much the more of us, as they think that our miſeries have been great? Or is it not out of a vain affectation of glory which is annexed to conſtancy, and to be in ſome ſort admired by others, that we paint forth as very exceſſive, incomparable, and in a word, much greater then they are, the evils which men ſee we ſuffer with ſo much patience, our Vanity being ſo eſſential and united to our ſouls, that Grief it ſelf cannot expell it, and that that accompanies it even in the midſt of torments, upon the Rack, and at the Stake, as the <hi>Stoicks</hi> ſaid of their Wiſemans Happineſſe? Or elſe, do we aggravate our mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries, becauſe through humane weakneſſe, we do in our miſeries many times think that the Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence which governs the Univerſe,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:60121:87"/>
doth us ſome kind of wrong, and that to prove it, we dare not alledge our perfections, and our innocence; but we alledge only the evils which it ſends us, which we ſay are greater then all that ever man ſuffered? Or elſe, becauſe we believe that all things have their courſe in the world, and ſucceed one another; do we not for this reaſon delight to perſwade our ſelves, that we have been for the time paſt very unhappy, to the end that we may build upon this foundation hopes of being happy for the future, and of ſeeing our fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity return in its courſe, as the Day returns after Night, Summer after Winter, and Fair weather after a long Storm? Or as <hi>Caeſar</hi> very wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly painted forth to his Souldiers the enemies forces much greater then they were, to the end that after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ſeeing them leſſe, they ſhould leſſe fear them, and be provided of reſolution and courage more then enough; doth not our ſoul by a
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:60121:88"/>
like artifice fain to its ſelf its misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes greater then they are, to the end that afterwards returning to conſider the truth of the buſineſſe, it may receive ſome comfort in un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceiving its ſelf; and that when the violence of its evil ſhall return to oppreſſe it, it may have laid in a large proviſion of courage, and find its ſelf provided of more conſtancy then is requiſite for the undergoing of it? Or elſe do we not aggravate our miſeries, to provoke our ſelves to <hi>weep</hi> more abundantly, becauſe we finde that <hi>tears</hi> are a refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to us; and therefore alſo in Tragedies, afflicted perſons do com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly exhort one another to ſhed abundance of Tears? Or elſe, to conclude, do we thus aggravate our evils, becauſe we think that great and excellent things, having only great deſtinies, either in good or evil, it is ſome token of elevation and excellence to have been exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed by great evils? If any man
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:60121:88"/>
object to me, that herein we ſhould make but a ſimple conſequence; I do freely confeſſe it; but I believe he will alſo grant me, that the mind of man hath very many weakneſſes and follies, and eſpecially that he is ſo paſſionate for his own excellence, that he lets not ſlip by in vain the leaſt ſhaddow of the leaſt mark that he can give to himſelf of it. And therefore we ſee many men blame themſelves for having a bad memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, that from thence they may draw ſome advantage for their judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, becauſe though they ſee this conſequence cannot but be very weak, ſince that there are every<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where thouſands of blockheads that have neither memory nor judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, yet they think that this is ſome ſlight ſign of it, becauſe of an opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion that is received by many to this purpoſe, the truth whereof we do not here examine: and that which is yet more, you pleaſe men, if you only tell them that they have an
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:60121:89"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:60121:89"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:60121:90"/>
head made like ſome very able man, whom every body reverences and eſteems; nay they pleaſe themſelves to believe they reſemble him in their hair, or gate; or, briefly, in having any air of his, nay to believe that they have had a deſtiny like to his, and like ſucceſs in certain encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. For, as in judgements of Law-ſuits, there are ſome things which being not able to paſs for en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire proofs, do paſs for ſemiproofs, or yet for leſs; ſo our ſoul in the midſt of reaſons, by which it labours to prove its own excellence, receives very vain ones, not as entire proofs, but as things which being collected and amaſſed in a ſufficient large number, do give it means to flatter it ſelf with ſome fancy which is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantageous to it, and to attribute to it ſelf very likely ſome perfection.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="28" type="problem">
            <pb n="113" facs="tcp:60121:90"/>
            <head>
               <hi>PROB. 28.</hi> Why do many laugh to ſee another man fall?</head>
            <p>THere are ſome who propound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this Queſtion, anſwer in one word, that it is out of malice. And if a man object to them, that many of thoſe that laugh at ſuch a miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance, do not ceaſe to have very honeſt minds, and a great deal of true goodneſs: They might anſwer, that a ſoul really good, may yet have, together with its goodneſs, ſome light mixture of malice; as we ſee there is ſcarcely a man ſo wiſe that hath not ſome light weakneſs of ſpirit: As when we ſay a man is ſanguine, we do not mean that he hath not a drop of Phlegm, Choler, or Melancholy humour in his body, but only that ſanguine is predomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant in him; ſo when we ſay a man
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:60121:91"/>
is wiſe, good, or ingenuous, we are not bound to conceive him exempt and wholly purged from folly and vice; For in truth it ſignifits no more then that Wiſdom, Vertue and Ingenuity are his predominant qualities: Nevertheleſs, it is clear that in thoſe that laugh when they ſee one fall, it is not properly malice; which I inferr, not only becauſe they do not laugh if he take any conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable hurt, but alſo and chiefly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are as ready to laugh at themſelves, if by chance they burn or cut their own fingers; or if the wind blow their hats off, or if they are ſurprized, or caught with a ſhower before they can get any ſhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or if any other petty diſorder befalls them, the reaſon is, becauſe theſe petty diſorders have alwayes in them ſomething of <hi>groteſque, extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary</hi> and <hi>ſudden;</hi> and becauſe by theſe three qualities they do in ſome ſort tickle the imagination.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="29" type="problem">
            <pb n="115" facs="tcp:60121:91"/>
            <head>
               <hi>PROB. 29.</hi> What is the reaſon that thoſe who em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace Civil and Worldly affairs with too violent an ardour, are ſubject to loſe all ſenſe of Religion, and the knowledge of a Deity?</head>
            <p>THough we had not learnt from the authority of the Holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, that the care of the things of the world, and the deceit of riches, do blind the underſtandings of men in reſpect of the myſteries of Faith, experience would ſufficiently prove it; ſince that it happens even at this day very frequent, that thoſe which ſettle their affections too much on the affairs of the world, and have in their minds no other deſigns but of worldly advancements, do ſo loſe the ſenſe of the verities of Religion that there remains to them only an outward profeſſion of it, with which,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:60121:92"/>
as with a ſuperficial kind of beauty, they cover the irregularity of their opinions. To ſay from hence, that they wiſh there were no true Rili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, that they might give them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the more liberty to compleat their deſigns all manner of wayes, and that they labour all they can to perſwade themſelves of it, and at laſt do perſwade themſelves, it is to ſay very much, but perhaps not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together enough, becauſe many times it happens that the more we deſire to chaſe out of our minds a belief, the leſs able are we to do it: It muſt therefore be added further, that as thoſe who addict themſelves to the contemplation of things ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lime and abſtract, do become unfit for low things, ſuch as are the affairs of the world: So by the ſame rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, thoſe that exerciſe their minds too much about low things, and ſuch as fall under the eye, muſt become unfit for the diſcerning of ſublime things, for that our ſoul is ſo miſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:60121:92"/>
that it can hardly gain on one ſide but it loſes on the other, and its perfections do very often ſhock one againſt another, and are incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petible. But beſides theſe two rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, there is a third more nice and not ſo eaſily to be perceived. The better to comprehend it, we muſt firſt conſider, that when our eyes have been too long fixed upon the Sun, there do remain upon them ſome certain impreſſions, which make us think we ſee its image in all the objects we look on: So when our mind is ſtrongly faſtened upon the conſideration of any one object, it thinks that it ſees it everywhere elſe, and is alſo ready to believe that every one looks upon that which he doth with a great deal of earneſtneſs, as he that hath long turned round, believes that all things turn with him. Thus, for example, a man of an <hi>Amorous</hi> complexion, all whoſe deſires look only at Love, is apt to think that all things in the world are
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:60121:93"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:60121:93"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:60121:94"/>
undertaken for Love; that it is this which for the moſt part playes his own game under the maſque of Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, or ſome other paſſion; and that even wars, and all the greateſt troubles of State, are only the effects of ſome ſecret Love. But an <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious</hi> man, out of the love he bears to Glory, takes it quite otherwiſe, and believes rather that all is done out of Ambition; that Covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs it ſelf looks at that indirectly; that Learning, as well as War, aims at nothing elſe; and that in Love it ſelf, the Ambition to conquer the mind of a Miſtriſs, or to ſurmount a Rival, are our principal motives. A <hi>Souldier</hi> wiil be ready to think that Learning hath no other rational end but the Military Art; but on the contrary a <hi>Scholler</hi> will judge that War hath no other end but to provide that wiſe men may quietly and peaceably apply themſelves to contemplation. An <hi>Orator</hi> will tell you that Philoſophy was invented
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:60121:94"/>
only to move the paſſions of the Judges handſomly and with a dreſs. But on the contrary, a <hi>Philoſopher</hi> will rather judge that Eloquence hath no other end but the applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Philoſophie. It follows then, according to the preceding Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, that when a man that hath already a propenſion to impiety, hath the affairs of the world too much in his head, and the means by which they are brought about; and he thinks, night and day, of nothing but politick tricks and gins by which he may entrap others; This imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by little and little becomes plau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to him: That Religion it ſelf is an artifice that tends to the bringing about of theſe very affairs of the world; and that it is a State-device of the Politicians, becauſe he thinks that every one looks upon that which himſelf doth with abundance of affection, and thinks he ſees every<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where elſe the ſame objects which his own mind is filled with, and to
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:60121:95"/>
which he is too much addict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="30" type="problem">
            <head>
               <hi>PROB. 30.</hi> What is the reaſon that the loweſt ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits are commonly moſt perſwaded of the truth of their opinions?</head>
            <p>IS it not becauſe that as the earth and groſs bodies have this ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage over the nobleſt and moſt ſubtile ones, that they are more firm in their places, and cannot ſo eaſily be removed; ſo groſs and dull ſouls have certain advantages over others, amongſt which this muſt be reckoned to be firm in their opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? Or ſhould we not rather ſay that this is rather a diſadvantage to them, and that it is harder to take away their errours, then to take from wiſe men their ſound belief; for the ſame reaſon that makes it harder to cure a man of a diſeaſe
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:60121:95"/>
than to make him ſick? Or elſe, is it not that as a man that ſtands on tiptoes, cannot be ſo firm in this po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture as he is in that lies along and keeps himſelf with all his weight on the ground: So wiſe men cannot be ſo firm in their opinions, to which they came only by forcing and ſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves; as fools are in theirs, into which they ſuffered themſelves to fall as it were with all their weight, being far from ſtriving to raiſe themſelves up again? Or elſe, is it that baſe opinions are upheld by the ſuffrage of the multitude, and that it is not to be wondered at, if that makes us couragiouſly embrace an opinion, ſince it makes us without fear to run upon death, and aſſures us againſt the greateſt dangers? Or elſe laſtly, is it that fools for want of judgement, do not for the moſt part underſtand the reaſon of the able; and that on the contrary, able men do by their vivacity conceive the reaſons which fools object
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:60121:96"/>
againſt them, better then they do themſelves, and that this difference is alike proper to make thoſe more reſolute, and to weaken ſomething the aſſurance of theſe?</p>
         </div>
         <div n="31" type="problem">
            <head>
               <hi>PROB. 31.</hi> Whence is it that in the greateſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of affliction, we do many times take up more readily a conſtant re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, then in others that are much lighter?</head>
            <p>IT is principally for two cauſes. Firſt, that when we are much afraid of any misfortune, and look upon it as the greateſt that can hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to us, this fear makes us very often to think of it; ſo that when it befalls us, we are already preparey for it, and that for this reaſon man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> times we are more eaſily reſolut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> therein, contrary to the expecta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion of all men. The ſecond is
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:60121:96"/>
that a great misfortune disabuſes us of the too great eſtem which we ſet on the things of the world, and of the happineſs which may be gotten in it, and proves to us on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary by our own experience, that all things are very fickle and incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant. Thus then it makes us con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temn it, and by that great blow which it gives us, doth as it were cut the roots by which we were tyed unto it: In a word, by afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us on the one ſide, it comforts us on the other, and furniſhes us with weapons againſt it ſelf.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="32" type="problem">
            <head>
               <hi>PROB. 32.</hi> Wherefore are old men great talkers?</head>
            <p>OLd men have thoughts that vex and perplex them, when they come once to be entertained with much leiſure; either becauſe they have diſcovered vanity in all things,
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:60121:97"/>
or becauſe old age in which they are, ſets before their eyes as ſoon as they entertain themſelves in this manner, many grand incommodities, into which they are ready to fall, and laſtly, the moſt inevitable of all evils, which is Death. They ſeek therefore to divert their minds from theſe vexatious thoughts by all means, and hither tend their houſhold cares, to which, for this reaſon, they apply themſelves very earneſtly; but when they have nothing to do, they can only Hear, or Talk, or Read, to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that melancholy which their mind would give to it ſelf in too great a leſure. But <hi>Hearing</hi> is not ſufficient to divert their minds from thoughts that wound them, becauſe governing themſelves wholly by their own judgement, they give no great attention to the thoughts of others, or contemn them, as making account that they themſelves have others taken up upon better grounds. As for <hi>Reading,</hi> it is an em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment,
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:60121:97"/>
which beſides that it is hurtful for them, dulls their facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, which Age hath rendred leſs quick, becauſe it hath nothing that doth enough affect the ſenſes and the mind. It is then only when they <hi>Talk</hi> that their minds do in good earneſt loſe the image of thoſe things that afflict and trouble them, and diverts the ſight from every thing that inſpires it with melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly. It is not therefore to be won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered at, if they are much delighted therewith. Or elſe, as <hi>Fruit</hi> falls more eaſily from the tree when it is ripe: ſo our <hi>Conceits</hi> come more fluently from us, how careful ſoever we be to keep them in, when they are full ripe, and that we have clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and well digeſted them. Now old mens are ſuch, becauſe they are wiſe, and have made many reflections, which have diſabuſed them of many errours. Or elſe, laſtly, they are Talkers, for ſeveral particular rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, as for inſtance, if they are
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:60121:98"/>
preſent at any ſolemnity or great ſhow, they have then leſs curioſity then others, becauſe they have often ſeen the like; therefore, inſtead of being attentive to ſee; they ſuffer themſelves often to make large diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes, which being then very of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive to thoſe that are near them, hath ſo much the more eaſily gotten them the name of great Talkers. Juſt ſo alſo, if they are at a Feaſt, they have leſs appetite then others, and are ſooner ſatisfied. And therefore, were it only out of civility, they are obliged to Talk, which incommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dating thoſe that by this means ſee themſelves bound to make long re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyes, makes them ſo much the more blame this vice. Moreover, after the repaſt, they are alſo carried away with a deſire to Talk much, to keep themſelves from ſleeping, becauſe they know well it is a thing they are ſubject to. Theſe are then, it ſeems, the principal cauſes of the effect we ſpeak of, though there may be alſo many others.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="33" type="problem">
            <pb n="127" facs="tcp:60121:98"/>
            <head>
               <hi>PROB. 33.</hi> Whence comes it, that in all kind of things, thoſe that do but meanly in them, are more ſevere and rigid Judges of others, then thoſe that excell therein, and hold the firſt rank?</head>
            <p>DO not people very much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive themſelves, when they think that to <hi>diſlike all things,</hi> is a token of <hi>delicacy of judgement;</hi> whereas on the contrary, they ſhould ſay, that a ſqueamiſhneſs both in body and mind, is a ſign of ſickneſs; and as an healthful man likes well brown bread, and leſs delicate vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ands; ſo a ſpirit of a ſtrong and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous health, ought to be pleaſed with all things, wherein it ſees ſhine never ſo little of perfection, although it will perceive the difference that is betwixt them and others; which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:60121:99"/>
thus ſuppoſed, our Problem re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains without difficulty; Or elſe ſhall we ſay, that the inclination eaſily to condemn others, proceeds from rudeneſs, and a want of natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ſweetneſs, which is not to be found in minds that have an entire and perfect beauty, becauſe it is a great uglineſs; as on the contrary, it is a great part of the beauty of the mind to have ſweet and gentle thoughts, to be ready to excuſe the faults of others, and not to contemn any one? Or elſe as we ſee often, that <hi>petty Lords</hi> are leſs accoſtable than the <hi>great ones,</hi> and maintain a gravity fuller of pride, becauſe their authority being not ſo well founded as that of theſe later, they think they muſt thus uphold it, by ſurly and arrogant looks, and by a brutiſh im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudence: Is it not juſt ſo in the meaner wits, and do they not uſe this ſeverity to condemn others, for to ſeparate themſelves thereby from the common, and labour to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:60121:99"/>
the authority they uſurp, and which they perceive hath not foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and <hi>baſis</hi> enough to uphold it ſelf? Or elſe as <hi>ſubordinate Judges,</hi> are very often more ſevere and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous in their judgements then the <hi>Soveraigns,</hi> becauſe it is not in their power to remit any thing of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity of the Law: the meaner wits, are they not more hard many times to excuſe a thing that is againſt the ordinary rules, becauſe it is for great minds only to grant a diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation from thoſe rules upon certain occaſions; and becauſe thoſe that have meaner abilities, ought not to be bold therein, nor are they, for fear, leſt whiles they deſire to excuſe others, they be blamed themſelves? Or elſe is it, that meaner ſpirits are not willing to confeſs in others a moderate worth, becauſe it is troubleſom to have many compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; but that when a man doth <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell</hi> in ſome kind of thing, he is glad that many others do but <hi>meanly</hi>
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:60121:100"/>
in it, becauſe it is glorious and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightful to have a great many <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriours?</hi> Or is it not, laſtly, becauſe great ſpirits love the truth more, and have more of ingenuity and of good breeding to acknowledge the perfection that is in another, and to publiſh it with all ſincerity: but the meaner ſort are not alwayes capable of ſo pure and clean a candour, and do many times diſſemble their judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon ſome deſign? It is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain indeed, that many petty paſſions which they cannot rid themſelves of, are capable to alter their good nature, and hinder them from con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing with ſufficient magnanimity anothers worth. For ſometimes they will not confeſs it out of an appetite of <hi>revenge,</hi> which ſome ſlight words hath raiſed in them; ſometime they refuſe to do it out of ſome motion of <hi>emulation</hi> and <hi>envy;</hi> ſometimes it is not properly out of <hi>envy</hi> that they are loth to own a merit far above their own, but becauſe ſo <hi>high</hi>
               <pb n="131" facs="tcp:60121:100"/>
a perfection doth more plainly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover to them their own <hi>littleneſs,</hi> and by this means makes them ſad. Or elſe it may be, if they have once begun to blame a thing, they will not <hi>unſay</hi> it out of <hi>obſtinacy,</hi> and leſt they acknowledge they were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived. Or elſe, they will not confeſs that another hath any worth, out of fear leſt ſomebody ſhould thence in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr by a long conſequence, that they themſelves have none: Or if they have no intereſt to obſcure anothers glory, there will be ſome <hi>friend</hi> of theirs, or elſe ſome one that is of the ſame <hi>City,</hi> or of the ſame <hi>Countrey,</hi> or of the ſame <hi>Party</hi> that they are, whom this intereſt will concern, and they will not preferr before him one that is <hi>indifferent,</hi> or a <hi>ſtranger,</hi> or of a <hi>contrary Party.</hi> In a word, there are beſides many other cauſes more ſlight and more nice, which change the candour of their words, and make them deny, either in whole or in part, the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:60121:101"/>
of another: but great minds are free from theſe weakneſſes, and undefiled with this filth, becauſe they are leſs intereſſed, and therefore worth finds more equity at their hands, and is more eaſily owned.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="34" type="problem">
            <head>
               <hi>PROB. 34.</hi> Whence comes it that it is ſo eaſie to blame and find fault, that the leaſt able do it beſt, and that it is much more hard to commend?</head>
            <p>IS it not becauſe there is much more ill than good in humane things, and that thoſe which are the moſt perfect, are yet very imperfect, if a man examine them ſtrictly, and with a deſire to find fault? But this being ſuppoſed, that the moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect things in this world have very great defects: Whence comes it that the meaneſt wits do take notice of them much more eaſily then they
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:60121:101"/>
do the perfections? Is it not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe being ill-ſighted, they ſee only that which exceeds, and is very great in the ſubjects they examine, and that as we ſaid, the evil doth alwayes exceed? Or elſe, doth not the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfection of the objects more lively affect the mind, than their perfection; for the ſame reaſon that that which hurts our bodies, is much more lively felt, then that which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights them? Or elſe is it, that to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge worth, and to commend it, one muſt firſt know wherein the perfection and truth of things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts; but that to know and to prove that another man is not arrived at it, one needs only know wherein they do not conſiſt. Indeed this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſeems to be moſt true, and to be able ſufficiently to clear the difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of this <hi>Problem.</hi> For it is ſo eaſie to ſay wherein things do not conſiſt, that after this manner we know the nature of <hi>God</hi> himſelf, ſince that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ignorant <hi>what he is,</hi> we do
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:60121:102"/>
nevertheleſs know him by <hi>negation,</hi> and we know that he is not any thing <hi>material,</hi> any thing <hi>viſible,</hi> any thing <hi>mortal,</hi> and that he is <hi>incape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able of change,</hi> and of the leaſt <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect;</hi> ſo that without being able to deſcribe his greatneſs, we can eaſily blame and reprove thoſe that ſpeak too lowly of him. After the ſame manner, it is very eaſie to tell where the <hi>Center of a circle</hi> is not, and the leaſt child can point out with his fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger many places which are not the middle of it: but to know where it is, there is need of skill, time, and inſtruments. But if we muſt ſtill ſearch out another reaſon for the ſame effect, conſiſts it not in this, that as one that ſwims is carryed by the very ſame water which he ſtrikes, which he thruſts from him, and which he troubles: ſo he that reproves and combates any one, and doth all he can to decry him, is born up by his inventions, becauſe that he affirms nothing of himſelf, and doth only
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:60121:102"/>
maintain that, what he whom he cenſures ſayes, being ſuppoſed, ſuch and ſuch things do follow: So that by this means he diſcourſes often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſucceſsfully of many things which he underſtands not, nor ſees the grounds of. Truly it ſeems to be ſo; For, for inſtance, though I know not what a <hi>Half-moon,</hi> a <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terſcarpe,</hi> or a <hi>Baſtion</hi> is, it is clear notwithſtanding, that when he that diſcourſes of them before me, ſhall come to contradict himſelf, either directly or indirectly, I may in uſing theſe terms which I underſtand not, reproach to him his contradictions, fight againſt him with thoſe arms which he hath put into my hands, and appear more able and more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding by this cenſure of him, then indeed I am. On the contrary, to commend any one with ſucceſs, one muſt not ſuppoſe for ttue, any thing that he ſaies, but muſt prove and maintain it by reaſons fetcht elſwhere.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="35" type="problem">
            <pb n="136" facs="tcp:60121:103"/>
            <head>
               <hi>PROB. 35.</hi> What is the reaſon that when the Winter hath been very cold, they commonly ſay the Summer that follows will be very hot?</head>
            <p>THere are ſometimes ſome ſlight things, the clearing whereof fails not to bring ſome light to our common ſenſe, and in this number one may reckon this, which at firſt ſight hath ſome difficulty, by reaſon that one would think the quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, that if the Winter hath very much cooled the Earth and Air, they ſhould be the more difficultly heated by the following Summer. Is it therefore quite otherwiſe, that the heat of the Summer finding the earth and air very cold, doth redouble its violence by the oppoſition of its con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary? Or elſe do they ſay ſo, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they ſee that one contrary
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:60121:103"/>
doth naturally ſucceed another in the ſame degree; as for example the water doth naturally aſcend as much as it hath deſcended; the exceſs of heat in a feaver ariſeth to the ſame violence with the exceſs of cold; great friendſhips leave behind them great enmities; and great diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, when they end, produce ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream contentments; after an extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary cloudy and wet ſeaſon, we enjoy an extraordinary ſerenity and purity of air, and much fairer then that which went before it; and one that is recovered from a great ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, hath commonly better health then he had before, and recovers a ſoundneſs that is more firme and of a greater value, then that which he had loſt. Or elſe is it that when the Winter hath been extraordinary cold, it hath alſo been neceſſarily dry, by the ſame reaſon the earth being very dry is diſpoſed to receive a great heat? Or elſe that when it hath been long cold, it is a ſign, that
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:60121:104"/>
the matter of the cold and Northern wind, or of the other cauſes that do cool the air, is ſpent for a long time, and therefore it is likely it will be very hot?</p>
         </div>
         <div n="36" type="problem">
            <head>
               <hi>PROB. 36.</hi> What is the reaſon that Fear makes ones hair ſtand on end?</head>
            <p>FOr the clearing of this Problem, I think it is needful to conſider in the firſt place that <hi>Admiration</hi> and <hi>Fear</hi> have ſome affinity, and do often accompany one another. Which being ſo, it ſeems that as <hi>Admiration</hi> makes a <hi>Chilneſs</hi> run through ones whole body by reaſon that it brings into the ſoul a certain ſhadow of <hi>Fear.</hi> So <hi>Fear</hi> makes the hair ſtand on end, out of ſome mixture of <hi>Admiration.</hi> Indeed this ſeems ſo much the more proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, becauſe the frights which make
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:60121:104"/>
the hair ſtand on end, muſt ſpring from a danger whoſe image preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtrikes the ſoul, and yet it knows no cauſe of it, and that thoſe frights which come upon us when we think we ſee dead men, or Ghoſts, or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils, do chiefly produce this effect, becauſe they are not only <hi>fearful</hi> things, but alſo very <hi>admirable,</hi> as being ſupernatural. <hi>Virgil</hi> hath excellently well comprized this; for when he would expreſſe the <hi>Fear</hi> which the ghoſt of his wife <hi>Creuſa</hi> ſtrook into <hi>Aeneas,</hi> the prodigy of <hi>Polydorus</hi>'s tomb, the arrival of <hi>Mercury,</hi> that came to bring him a meſſage from <hi>Jupiter;</hi> or the <hi>Fear</hi> that <hi>Turnus</hi> was in, ſeeing an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fernal monſter flap his buckler with its wings: upon all theſe occaſions he puts down this circumſtance, that their hair ſtood up right, becauſe that all theſe things were as <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable</hi> as <hi>terrible:</hi> But in other kinds of fear, he is contented to mention only <hi>coldneſs</hi> and <hi>trembling.</hi>
               <pb n="140" facs="tcp:60121:105"/>
And if any demand of me why <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration</hi> makes the hair to ſtand up right? I anſwer, that the ſoul, having its faculties intent on the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that which appears admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, doth alſo contract the organs of the brain, and with them the skin that covers the head. Now a man may eaſily imagine that we cannot contract this skin, but by pulling it up, nor pull it up but the hairs will ſtare a little. It is true that the motion of <hi>fear</hi> doth alſo contribute thereto, becauſe it makes one <hi>cold,</hi> and that a part of our body cannot be <hi>cold</hi> without being a little more contracted then before.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="37" type="problem">
            <pb n="441" facs="tcp:60121:105"/>
            <head>
               <hi>PROB. 37.</hi> Whence comes it that many being in a frenzy, have spoke Latin or Greek, without having ever learned either of theſe languages?</head>
            <p>MAny of thoſe that have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined this Queſtion, endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to rid themſelves of the great difficulty which it preſents at firſt to the mind, have in my judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment made uſe of ſuch anſwers, as are more againſt all appearance of reaſon, then the Queſtion it ſelf, and given us remedies worſe then the diſeaſe: For they would give ſuch ſtrange force to our imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that no man of a ſound judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is able to give credit to their vain diſcourſes. Wherefore omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all that they have ſaid of it, we will ſearch only amongſt known cauſes, according to our cuſtom, the
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:60121:106"/>
reaſon of ſo marvellous an effect. <hi>Firſt</hi> then it is remarkable, that thoſe words, which many being in a frenzy have pronounced in a tongue which they knew not, have been ordinarily <hi>Latin</hi> or <hi>Greek,</hi> or ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times <hi>Hebrew,</hi> according to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of thoſe that have treated of them. In the <hi>ſecond</hi> place I ſuppoſe that the words which they have thus ſpoken, did not make any diſcourſe that was coherent or that was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent to that which was asked them, ſince that the tranſports of their frenzy hindred them from diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſing rationally. Theſe two things being thus ſuppoſed, one may add, that although thoſe that have ſpoken <hi>Latin, Greek,</hi> or <hi>Hebrew</hi> in a frenzy, never <hi>ſtudied</hi> it, and yet they eaſily may have heard thoſe words before which they ſpoke, ſeeing that theſe three languages are commonly taught throughout <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope,</hi> and that private houſes and thoſe places which are ſet apart for
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:60121:106"/>
ſpeaking in publick, do very often retain them. Now it is poſſible that theſe words, at the ſame time when they heard them, made ſome impreſſion in the organs of their memories, which through its weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs did not appear to them, untill they fell into madneſs; becauſe that the heat of the frenzy by its immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate ſubtilizing of the ſpirits of the brain, renders the ſenſe of the ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination ſo quick and ſo delicate, that there cannot be in its organs any impreſſions ſo weak which it diſcovers not and is lively enough affected with it. And that the images of certain things can lodge in our memories, and we have no knowledge of them at all, becauſe they are only painted very weakly, and as it were with dead colours, may ſufficiently be proved by <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſcence,</hi> which brings to our minds many things which we thought we had utterly forgotten. Beſides many otherlike impreſſions,
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:60121:107"/>
are alſo made oftentimes in the other organs of our faculties, and we never perceive it; and it is not to be doubted, for example, but that when the weather is about to change, our bodies, although we perceive nothing on it, do receive within them ſome change, as well as thoſe of birds that thereby do pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage fair or foul weather. In the <hi>third</hi> place, one may confeſs that certain images may be imprinted in our organs without being perceived, after the example of a man that is very ſhort-ſighted, who doth que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionleſs, for all that, receive the images of objects very far diſtant, becauſe that he would ſee them if on a ſuddain, the power which he hath of ſeeing ſhould become more ſubtile and quick. And if any man wonders not that theſe freneticks we ſpeak of, are able to retain, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve a long time in their memories the images which they do not know are there, but that the words which
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:60121:107"/>
they heard only by the by, ſhould be able to leave there any light and weak picture of themſelves. He muſt remember that beſides that the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans of the memory are without doubt very delicate, and very ſuſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptible of all impreſſions, the activity of natural things is marvellous, and hath many times much greater ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent then we believe. For, for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, could we eaſily perſwade our ſelves, that a beaſt that runs can in running imprint its ſent in all the places where it goes, if the dogs of chaſe did not prove it; and when we have handled a ring of glaſs, or ſilver, or gold, would we believe at the firſt, that ſo ſmall touching of it ſhould take away any thing from it: and yet Philoſophers hold that it muſt needs be ſo, ſince that at length we diminiſh it ſenſibly by handling it? I add further that it is not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, that the perſons we now ſpeak, of ſhould have heard thoſe words they pronounce in their
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:60121:108"/>
frenzy, only once; they may have heard them two or three ſeveral times, and a man muſt the leſs won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that we have the images of things without knowing it, when he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiders that our very deſires are hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den from us, when they are as yet very feeble, and newly born.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="38" type="problem">
            <head>
               <hi>PROB. 38.</hi> What is the reaſon that a too earneſt entreaty makes us unwilling inſtead of inciting us to grant that which is deſired of us?</head>
            <p>IS it not becauſe man being a ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional creature and one tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ought to act freely, loves to lea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> himſelf the dance in all his actions and to have the beginning of the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in himſelf; and that when one de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſires to conſtrain him with too much ardour and violence to any thing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> he thinks he is rather <hi>drawn</hi> by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="147" facs="tcp:60121:108"/>
ardour and preſſing importunity, then put upon it of <hi>himſelf,</hi> which conſequently diſpleaſes him, and makes his will more cold inſtead of heating it? Or elſe, is it becauſe he which begs of us earneſtly, makes us foreſee plainly enough, that we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not deny him his deſire without put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him into a great choler, and making him our enemy, that is to ſay, that he provides for us his enmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as it were a puniſhment in caſe we fail of compliance toward him, in which our mind ſees yet a greater image of conſtraint, and that which diſpleaſeth it more? for it hates no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo much, as to ſeem to do a thing out of fear. Or elſe, is it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we judge, that he which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires a thing with immoderate and exceſſive paſſion, is apt to tell a lie to gain it, ſooner then another man that deſires it with leſs violence; and that he doth purpoſely conceal from us ſome circumſtance, which would make his requeſt unreaſonable, and
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:60121:109"/>
unjuſt? Or elſe, is it becauſe that which is very violently deſired, ſeems to us of more conſequence; and that in things of conſequence, we are wont to demur and conſider a good while before we reſolve any thing, becauſe we are affraid of committing ſome great errour? Or elſe is it becauſe he which prayes us with too much earneſtneſs, ſayes many things which make us believe that he hath his eye faſtened only upon his own intereſt, and that he regards only the good or evil that may happen to him upon our denyal or conſent, and not on the good or evil that may befall us, which we diſlike with ſome reaſon, as being unjuſt: for, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to equity and reaſon, he that would have us be diſpoſed to do good to him, ought alſo on his part to wiſh us well, and that in deſiring of us an act of good will towards him, he have not a will indifferent toward us? Or elſe laſtly, is it not becauſe too earneſt prayers and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:60121:109"/>
are commonly accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with too low and baſe a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, and a too ſervile flattery, which commonly do quite contrary to that a man thinks they ſhould? It is manifeſt indeed that a too low and ſordid ſubmiſſion is apt to be contemned, and every one knows it well enough; but that which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives men, is, that oftentimes they do not conſider long enough before the conſequences of this contempt, and ſee not that it not only ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhes <hi>Affection</hi> in us, but alſo inclines us even to <hi>Hatred,</hi> juſt as <hi>Pity</hi> inclines us to <hi>Love.</hi> Beſides, the ſubmiſſion that any one renders to us, is not more apt to pleaſe us, and by this means to get ſome bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of us, then to make us think it comes from a baſe and dejected mind, ſince that all the advantage we can finde in it, proceeds only from the mind that it comes from: and as for the exceſſive praiſes which are given us by him that deſires to
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:60121:110"/>
obtain ſome favour from us by his too baſe flattery, if we think that they do not come from the heart, we conſider them only as ſo many cheats; and if we believe that he doth really eſteem us, with that exceſs as he makes ſhew of, firſt, we do not much thank him for it, becauſe the eſteem which a man hath of any one, is a thing forced, and depends not on him that gives it; and in the ſecond place, we do not now take ſo much care to preſerve and augment this eſteem in him by our benefits, as thinking it both great enough and well enough eſtabliſhed, whereas when any one reſpects us, but with more moderation, we labour what we can to encreaſe this eſteem by our beneficence, and take care to cheriſh and cultivate (as I may ſo ſay) a belief, which we ſee is both profitable and glorious to us.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="39" type="problem">
            <pb n="151" facs="tcp:60121:110"/>
            <head>
               <hi>PROB. 39.</hi> What are the cauſes of the marvelous things which we obſerve in the Silk-worm?</head>
            <p>TO ſay the truth, there is nothing ſo admirable as that which no body admires. Thoſe which we call <hi>occult qualities</hi> in the Elements, or in other things, may have the moſt <hi>common cauſes,</hi> like Juglers tricks, which ſeem to be grand myſteries, before one hath diſcovered them: but <hi>Man,</hi> whoſe ordinary operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and common motions we do not at all admire, offers us never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs in theſe operations and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions far more worthy ſubjects of aſtoniſhment; his <hi>Paſſions</hi> are more admirable then the <hi>ebbing</hi> and <hi>flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the ſea;</hi> the power of his <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding</hi> over his <hi>Will,</hi> more mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velous then the influence of the
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:60121:111"/>
               <hi>Stars;</hi> the operations of his <hi>Senſes</hi> are of much more difficult explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, then all thoſe of the <hi>Loadſtone; and he is a great marvail that admires little ones.</hi> Not to go too far in this diſcourſe, the conſideration of the marvels which are diſcovered in the Silk-worms, may furniſh us with ſome proofs of it: they ſeem at firſt ſight to ſurpaſs or equal the things that are moſt ſtrange; and thoſe that have deſcribed them, have not been able ſufficiently to admire that this creature ſhould be killed by the ſole noiſe of thunder, that it ſhould have an inſtinct to ſpin unprofitably, and even with the loſs of its life, ſeeing that it ſtifles it ſelf in its own work, that it can draw out of its body that Silk of which it compoſes it; that a long time after it is dead, it revives; that it transforms it ſelf into a But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfly, and after it is thus transform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, it can live ſtill many dayes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out meat, that is to ſay, to the end of its life. But how ſtrange ſoever
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:60121:111"/>
all theſe things ſeem, I conceive that if we would conſider them ſomewhat exactly, we ſhould perſwade our ſelves, that there is no neceſſity of leaving the bounds of common and ordinary cauſes to unvail and clear the ſecrets of them; and to do it, I will lay down only two things; Firſt, that Silk-worms are exceſſive <hi>cold;</hi> and Secondly, that they are full, and as I may ſo ſay, overglutted with an exceſſive <hi>moiſture:</hi> their <hi>moiſture</hi> is apparent of its ſelf to our ſight, ſince that it makes them whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tranſparent; and it is credible, that it is this that renders them ſo fruitful. Their extream <hi>coldneſs</hi> may alſo be felt by our hands, and doth beſides diſcover it ſelf by certain reaſons to our minds, ſeeing that in the midſt of Summer, if the weather come to be a little coldiſh, they dye with cold, which doth not befall any other creature; and ſeeing thoſe which take the pains to keep them, are carefull to keep them very warm,
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:60121:112"/>
and in a place that is not expoſed to the Northwind. Theſe two things being thus ſuppoſed, it is no wonder in the firſt place that the noiſe of thunder kills them; this manifeſtly proceeds from the fear which ſo ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible a noiſe cauſes in them; for they muſt needs be very fearful, ſince that they are ſo cold and are void of blood; and when fear adds its cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to that which is natural to them, ſo violent an exceſs may eaſily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive them of life. Now as the Silk-worm is very cold, and when it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins to grow old, its natural frigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity by this means encreaſing, it is not to be wondred at that it ſeeks to envelop and cover it ſelf, to the end that it may be warm: for all other creatures being preſſed with cold, do the like, and ſearch out holes wherein they lie in the ſtraw, and enwrap themſelves even in the cloaths and hangings of our houſes, to be the leſs troubled with it. Hereto ſerves the Silk which it vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits,
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:60121:112"/>
and we muſt not wonder that it can vomit this rich matter; for it is nothing but the remainders of its nouriſhment which its too weak heat cannot digeſt, and as it were a ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous humour which their abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of it hath cauſed. Beſides, when it puts it forth, it is not dry, but viſcous, and hath a clammy moiſtneſs: but preſently after the air hardens and dries it, as if it were glue. Being thus covered for warmth, it is not ſtifled as folks believe; na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture doth not give creatures any inſtincts that are ſo deſtructive to them. It dies not unleſs by a <hi>natural</hi> death for want of ſtrength, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it makes its <hi>Bed</hi> when we think it builds its <hi>Sepulcher,</hi> and <hi>ſleeps</hi> when we believe it <hi>dyes.</hi> And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, if we open this pretended grave, after that we believe it is dead, we ſhall clearly perceive that it is only in a profound ſleep; its na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural frigidity, which even before it thus locked it ſelf up, cauſed it to
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:60121:113"/>
ſleep longer then ordinarily other creatures do, making it ſleep much longer, ſince it lockt it ſelf up enveloped as it is in ſilk, which it wiſely drew out of its own body to caſt round about it; it grows a little warm by reaſon that its heat is on all ſides hindred from exhaling, and driven back, juſt as a man becomes warm by means of the cloaths he covers himſelf with. But whence comes it, you will ſay, that it tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forms it ſelf into a Butterfly? I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that there is no colour to ſay it is <hi>transformed;</hi> that the Wings it acquires were due to it from its birth; that nature intended it ſhould flye with them: but that they could not grow out, untill that being covered with ſilk, which it vomited, it had gotten together a little more heat, to ſtrengthen its <hi>vegetative</hi> faculty, and enable it to put them forth, as it doth to that of <hi>Trees,</hi> to put forth their fruits, leaves and flowers, the production whereof
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:60121:113"/>
was formerly hindred by the cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Winter. Nor doth this happen only to <hi>Silk-worms;</hi> for <hi>Caterpillers</hi> ſpin the like upon trees, locking themſelves up in their own work, and being there, they get wings as well as theſe. But that which further proves to us, that the heat of the Silk-worm, uniting it ſelf, after the manner aforeſaid, may ſerve to put forth its wings, is, that <hi>flying</hi> Serpents are to be ſeen only in very <hi>hot</hi> Countries, by reaſon it ſeems, that the extream heat of the air, ſupplying the defect of the coldneſs of their temper, gives their formative faculty power to produce them. But if we muſt ſay that they are transformed, and that they change their nature in ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring <hi>wings,</hi> becauſe that imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately after their birth they have none, we muſt for the ſame reaſon ſay, that many other creatures are transformed when they acquire <hi>Teeth, Nails</hi> or <hi>Horns,</hi> which they
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:60121:114"/>
had not when they were born, and that the very birds are transformed when they get wings, ſince that when they were hatcht they had none. The Silk-worm therefore is not transformed, but only becomes able to fly ſomewhat ſlowlier; and to conclude my ſtory, it is reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able we ſhould believe, that after it hath ſlept much, the ſame cauſe that awakens other creatures, awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens this alſo: Then doth wiſe na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture make it vomit forth a thin ſharp moiſture, which helps it to gnaw that ſilk, which it was on all ſides environed with, and by this means out it comes and continues for many dayes, and even to the end of its life, without eating any thing, wherein conſiſts the laſt marvel that we are to ſpeak of. But I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive we may eaſily gueſs the cauſe of it, if we remember, that it hath a very great moiſture joyned with a very ſmall heat: for we ſhall ſee that this ſmall heat muſt finde
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:60121:114"/>
for a long time ſufficient aliment in this great moiſture, without having need to receive any other; and hereupon might be alledged the ſtrange ſtory of a <hi>German</hi> maid, that having a very weak heat, and a body full of a viſcous and clammy humour, continued ſome whole years without eating or drinking. Now as this temper of the Silk-worm diſcovers to us the cauſe why it can live ſo long without meat: So this entire ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinence, in which it paſſes a great part of its life, may be a new con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation to us, that it hath the ſame temper which we attributed to it at firſt. For though for a certain ſeaſon it eats abundantly enough, of which there may be eaſily ſome other particular reaſon; yet conſidering its whole life in groſs, it muſt paſs for one of the ſobereſt creatures. Theſe are then, in my opinion, the cauſes of what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever appears marvelous in the
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:60121:115"/>
Silk-worm. If any one hath a mind to think that there are more ſtrange and more occult ones, it is not my intent, that this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe ſhould hinder him; But yet I believe that as we often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times do not ſee many things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are too <hi>far</hi> diſtant from the eyes of our mind, ſo at other times we do not ſee them becauſe they are too <hi>near,</hi> and that we ſearch at the other end of the world for that which lyes before our noſes, and that the great eager<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs that our underſtanding uſes to arrive at their cauſes, makes it go much beyond them.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="40" type="problem">
            <pb n="161" facs="tcp:60121:115"/>
            <head>
               <hi>PROB. 40.</hi> Why are good men often-times ſubject to a light promptitude of Choler?</head>
            <p>DO they not only ſeem to be ſo, becauſe they are more free and open, and ſo know not how to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble the ſmalleſt anger, and leaſt diſcontentments that ariſe in them; but let them preſently appear in their eyes and words: whereas thoſe that are leſs free, do conceal them what they can poſſibly? Or elſe, is it that thoſe that have honeſt and good minds, are angry for many things that regard not their particular in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts? as for example, for the glory of <hi>God,</hi> and for any thing that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects <hi>Honeſty</hi> and <hi>Piety,</hi> ſo that as theſe are general things which come every moment into our diſcourſe, ordinary converſation offers them more often occaſion to ſpeak with
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:60121:116"/>
heat and emotion, and in ſome ſort to be provoked: whereas a brutiſh man, to whom all things are indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent except his own proper inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, can hear without any diſturb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, all kind of diſcourſe which he is not the ſubject of, be they never ſo ſtrange; which makes him often appear more ſweet and gentle, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his intereſts being ſome parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular things, and little known to others, they ſcarce ever come to be the matter of a common diſcourſe? Or elſe, may we not give light to this Problem, by that which <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſaith, that Choler is enclined to obey Reaſon, but that it obeyes it too ſoon, and ſtayes not until the firſt appearance of Reaſon hath given place to another more clear and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid? And may it not be ſaid, that if ſo, it muſt needs be, that good minds muſt naturally have ſome ſeeds of a light promptitude to Choler, becauſe the inclination readily to obey Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, is without doubt a good diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:60121:116"/>
of mind, and a token of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellence, though by accident-there may ariſe from it vitious actions and other inconveniencies? Or elſe, may we not add further, that one ſhall have leſs reaſon to wonder, that Good men have many times ſuch a diſpoſition, if it be conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that there are ſome kinds of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger ſo handſom, that one may main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain they mark out more of Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Tenderneſs, and Love of good, than even motions of Pitty or Good-will; becauſe in the motions of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection and Pitty, the ſoul doth meerly deſire to do good; but thoſe of a generous and laudable Anger, are the motions of a ſoul that doth ſo much love good and hate evil, that it troubles it ſelf at it even to fury, and becomes fooliſh for a time? It may indeed be further al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged in favour of this Paradox, that the tenderneſs of nature of any creature appears not ſo much; for example, when it takes care to give
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:60121:117"/>
food to its little ones, as when full of anger and as it were in a fury, it layes on load with its wings, or horns, or other arms that Nature hath given it, on thoſe that would come too near them. Or elſe, in concluſion we may ſay, that there are certain emotions of choler, in which a man hath no intentions to do any hurt to thoſe of whom he complains with ſharp words; but rather to incite them to produce their juſtifications, to be able to find them innocent, or leſs culpable, and to continue by this means to love them: ſo that as they do not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed out of malice, but tenderneſs, there is no cauſe to wonder that good men are ſubject thereunto, and that they ſhew a good nature, like in this to Lightnings, that appear in Summer evenings, and are often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſigns of <hi>fair</hi> weather, whereas they ſhould ſeem rather to preſage <hi>foul.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="41" type="problem">
            <pb n="165" facs="tcp:60121:117"/>
            <head>
               <hi>PROB. 41.</hi> Whence comes it that they ſay, The Love of Grand-fathers to their Grand-children, is greater then that of their Fathers?</head>
            <p>IS it not becauſe a man attains through longer cares to have a Grand-child, then to have a Son; and that alwayes that which we ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire through more care, is more dear to us? Or elſe, is not a Grand-child dearer, becauſe it hath been a long time deſired? Or elſe, do we not look upon it as a more rare fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, and ſuch as heaven eommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates only to few perſons, which makes us love it the more, becauſe generally all rare things have a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular allurement for our minds? Or elſe, is not a Grand-child more beloved of his Grand-father then of his Father, becauſe that his Grand-father,
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:60121:118"/>
as being more old, and nigher his death, doth for this reaſon deſire the more to live again in another? Or elſe, is it becauſe the love we bear to thoſe that proceed from us, ariſing from a deſire to extend our being ſucceſſively to many genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, he that by this natural courſe is more removed, ſhews to us this deſign more advanced, and ſo doth more touch our inclinations? Or elſe, is it becauſe the Father loves his Son only for his own ſake, but the Grand-father loves him for his own ſake and for his Sons ſake too, and ſees in him the image of himſelf, and of him whom he hath begotten, and that theſe two divers conſiderations do produce in him two divers ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſes very powerful? Indeed this reaſon is very likely: for to go about to object, that the Father hath likewiſe two divers cauſes of loving his Son, becauſe he may love him for the Grand-fathers ſake, this makes nothing to the purpoſe;
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:60121:118"/>
ſince that, as every one knows, the affection which blood inſpires, hath much leſs force in aſcending than in deſcending. But if ſtill another rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon muſt be given of this <hi>Problem,</hi> one may alſo ſay, that perhaps the affection of Grand-fathers doth on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſeem to be greater then that of Fathers, becauſe the Son being in a more particular manner the very blood and ſubſtance of the Father; the Father for this reaſon thinks that to love him very much, is to love himſelf very much, and that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he conceals and keeps in theſe motions of it, for fear leſt they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray too much weakneſs and ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>love: Whereas a Grand-father be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not ſo much touched with this conſideration, doth the more give himſelf over to the violences of his Love, and dares more freely manifeſt it, as judging the exceſs thereof-leſs ſhameful.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="42" type="problem">
            <pb n="168" facs="tcp:60121:119"/>
            <head>
               <hi>PROB. 42.</hi> Why is it that a rare and eminent Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue which ſhines in a Prince, raiſes greater motions of Love in the lower ſort of people, then in other men?</head>
            <p>IT is a thing worthy to be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, that the vertue of a Prince when it is eminent and rare, ſeems to raiſe more Love in the loweſt ſort of people, then in any others. For we ſee it is commonly the vulgar people that appear moſt afflicted for the death of a good and vertuous Prince, even to weep in the ſtreets, ſhops, and about the fields, with an extream tenderneſs, as it were for a domeſtique loſs, and it is alſo the meaner ſort of people that in his life-time gives him with more zeal a thouſand benedictions, and labours for his glory with a more paſſionate
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:60121:119"/>
will, and ſuch as ſhows that they have more of reſentment againſt thoſe that would do him any wrong. Hiſtory may furniſh us with a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand ſtrange and admirable examples of this affection of the vulgar people toward a good Prince; but, that I may not enlarge this diſcourſe too much, we will content our ſelves to name only ſome of them. We ſee in <hi>Sueton,</hi> that after the death of <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manicus,</hi> a Prince of an eminent ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, the Commonalty of <hi>Rome</hi> grew almoſt mad, that neither the Edicts of <hi>Tiberius,</hi> nor the Religion of certain <hi>Feſtivals,</hi> could ſtop the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderate courſe of its grief, and that many of thoſe which were poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed of this grief, went ſo far as to demoliſh the Altars of the gods through deſpair, to caſt the tutelar gods of their houſes into the ſtreets, and to expoſe thoſe children that were born to them on that day, as refuſing all Happineſs and all occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of Joy. The good qualities of
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:60121:120"/>
               <hi>Julius Caeſar</hi> produced alſo the like effects after his death; for though he had taken from the <hi>Romans</hi> that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty which they prized ſo high; nevertheleſs after that <hi>Antonie</hi> had awakened by his Oration the memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of his Goodneſs, Clemency, Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, and of the number of his Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctories, the common people that heard him, were ſo touched with it, that after they had done honours to him as a god, they ran with lighted fire-brands in their hands to ſet fire to the <hi>Capitol,</hi> and had almoſt burnt down the City, to be revenged on thoſe that had newly freed it, and reduced the Common-wealth to its antient form. This very <hi>Caeſar</hi> in his life-time was ſo beloved of his Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, that having failed of their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, they deſired him to decimate them, thereby to expiate their crime, and to give himſelf ſatisfaction. The like happened alſo afterwards to his ſucceſſor <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> according to the report of <hi>Appian.</hi> And <hi>Alexander
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:60121:120"/>
the Great,</hi> leading his <hi>Macedonian</hi> Souldiers, young and old, croſs the deſerts, for none other deſign but to come to the bounds of the habitable world, was nevertheleſs ſo tenderly beloved of them, for his Vertue, that ſeeing them mutiny to return into <hi>Macedonia,</hi> and even the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of ſome of them could not ſtop their commotion, he only ſent them word, they might go whether they pleaſed, and that he would love them no longer, nor account them his, which touched them with ſo ſharp a Repentance, that flocking before his door, they fell a crying with abundance of tears, that he ſhould kill them if they had offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, as <hi>Quintus Curtius</hi> tells the ſtory. But to begin our ſearch for the Reaſon, why the Vertue of a Prince excites in the minds of the common people (that are moſt commonly intereſſed and mercena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry) ſuch diſintereſſed and ſuch he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roick motions, which ſeem to be
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:60121:121"/>
greater then thoſe that are raiſed in the reſt of men that are better bred: is it not, in the firſt place, that the common people are not in all regards inferiour in Vertue to the reſt of men; and that if they be ſomething leſs generous and more mercenary, as we have confeſſed, they are on the other ſide full of Pitty, and have in very many things more of Shame and Juſtice? And may we not add, that as the love which <hi>beaſts</hi> bear to their <hi>young ones,</hi> ſurpaſſes that which <hi>men</hi> bear to their <hi>children,</hi> it may very well be after the ſame manner that amongſt men a good motion may ſometimes be more ſtrong where there is leſs of Reaſon and Knowledge, becauſe then a man obeyes more blindly the good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citements of Nature? Or elſe is it that many times men of a middle rank look upon the Fortune of their Superiours, if not with envy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly ſo called, yet at leſt with ſome evil of heart; and that thoſe of the
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:60121:121"/>
loweſt ſort are more free from all theſe motions, becauſe the diſtance between them and thoſe that govern them is greater, and therefore they are diſpoſed the more to conſider their Vertue with Love and Admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? Or elſe, is it that the motions of an heroick and extraordinary Generoſity, when they ſhine upon the eyes of all in the perſon of a Prince, may excite more of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration in the minds of the loweſt ſort of people, becauſe they perceive themſelves leſs capable of ever ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſo high? Or elſe is it that when a Prince manifeſts his affection in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral to all his ſubjects, the loweſt people think themſelves <hi>moſt obliged</hi> to his goodneſs, becauſe they think themſelves <hi>leaſt worthy</hi> of it? Or elſe, is it not that the greateſt part of the goodneſs of a Prince conſiſts herein, to be favourable to the Poor, which, as being weakeſt, are moſt apt to be wronged by the ſtronger; not to enrich thoſe that are already
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:60121:122"/>
too rich, with the ſubſtance of the common people, and to do Juſtice equally to all his ſubjects, without having regard to the difference of quality, and that it is no wonder if all this doth more pleaſe the <hi>common</hi> ſort of people, then perſons of <hi>qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity?</hi> Or elſe is it alſo that the vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar ſort as being leſs inlightned, and leſs polliſhed by Learning, are more dazled by greatneſs of Birth, and have more veneration from the pomp and glory that attends the fortune of Princes: ſo that when the luſtre of Vertue comes to ſhine on their eyes, together with this glittering Greatneſs, it ſeems ſo ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerable to them, that it hath power over their minds to do any thing? This laſt truly ſeems to contribute not a little to their Admiration; but, to conclude, we may ſee here by the way, that <hi>Machiavel</hi> had no reaſon to ſay that the Vertue of a Prince can raiſe Love and Gratitude in a few perſons only, and that all the
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:60121:122"/>
reſt of men are ingrateful, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capeable of being moved by it; and therefore in his opinion, he ſhould endeavour rather to make himſelf feared by the rigour of his puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: This appears, ſay I, to be falſe by our Problem, for we have ſeen that the love of a Princes Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue ſhines chiefly in the common people, which makes the greateſt part of men, and is able to beget in them moſt exquiſite and admirable motions of affections, becauſe of this mixture with Greatneſs, which hath a certain Luſter and Beauty, that doth extreamly take with the people. And if I may be permitted to add ſomething upon this conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, I ſhall ſay further, that it is only the baſeneſs of his own mind, that made him imagine that Grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, ſhame of an unworthineſs ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally confeſt, or love of a rare merit, ſhould have ſo little power upon our ſpirits; for it hath been often ſeen, that a troop of mutiners
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:60121:123"/>
from amongſt the very dregs of the people, after they have contemned the fear of puniſhment, have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come calm and appeaſed on a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, meerly by the preſence of a man of known vertue, out of reverence which it imprinted in them. There are many crimes which men ceaſe not to commit every day, although they that commit them are every day hanged for it; but on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, there are ingratitudes and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthineſſes which are committed but very rarely, although the Laws have not ordained any puniſhment for thoſe that are guilty of them, becauſe the greateſt part of men have conceptions lively enough of the blackneſs and ſordidneſs of them. The fear of Death and Pain, which, according to <hi>Machiavel,</hi> do never forſake men, is overcome every day in the wars by the hope of a little pay, and the contempt of them is grown common. But of ſo many thouſand men that hazzard them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:60121:123"/>
thus, without doubt there would be but a very few, that for a much greater ſumm would betray a friend, by whom they had been ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly obliged. But we leave this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, before it hath carried us very much beyond our ſubject, and paſs on to another Problem.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="43" type="problem">
            <head>
               <hi>PROB. 43.</hi> What is the reaſon that Shame makes a redneſs to ariſe in the face?</head>
            <p>AS there are not any motions more pleaſant and more wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be known, then thoſe of <hi>Shame,</hi> ſo there are none that ſeem to produce their effects in us after ſo obſcure a manner, and ſo difficult to explain. The reaſon is, that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever our mind doth moſt genuinely and after a more natural manner, is alwayes that which it is leaſt aware of. Now the impreſſions that Shame
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:60121:124"/>
cauſes in our blood, and upon our faces, is ſo natural, that Stage-players which laugh and cry, though they are neither ſad nor merry, which can make themſelves look pale as if they were afraid, and can arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficially draw upon their faces the redneſs of Anger, and eaſily coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit Pitty, Aſtoniſhment, or Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain, cannot for all this by any cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning draw upon their faces the red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Shame, and the characters which it ought to be accompanied with. Beſides, he that cryes hath an intention to cry, and he that weeps hath an intention to weep: but moſt commonly he that bluſhes hath no intention to bluſh; and this is the reaſon that very modeſt perſons bluſh even at their very bluſhing, and by endeavouring to hide their Shame, increaſe and double it. Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that which makes the difficulty of this Problem appear greater, is, that it is certain the redneſs of Shame proceeds alwayes from ſome grief
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:60121:124"/>
and pain which the ſoul is in. Now it is the property of Grief to repreſs the blood and ſpirits, and gather them together about the heart, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of ſpreading of them in the face, as ſhame doth. Nevertheleſs, we will endeavour here to diſcover the myſterie of ſo handſom a paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: And firſt we will tell you what ſome have thought, that the ſoul ſends forth the blood into the face in ſhame, becauſe it deſires to cover it as with a veil; whereto they endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to add ſome weight from expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, which ſhows us, that thoſe which are ſurprized with Shame, do naturally hold their hand before their face. Now as I do not abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely reject this conſideration of theirs, yet I do not think it ought to ſatisfie us ſo, but that we ſhould ſearch for others: For beſides that it is perhaps a pretty <hi>fancy</hi> rather than a <hi>reaſon,</hi> certain it is, that many times they that are ſurprized with Shame, do not deſire to hide their
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:60121:125"/>
faces from him that cenſures them, but on the contrary do earneſtly wiſh that he read therein his repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and ſorrow, and for all this ceaſe not to bluſh. To ſearch then another cauſe of this effect, we muſt in the firſt place conſider, that in all the Paſſions, the <hi>Soul</hi> imprints the images of its leaſt motions upon the <hi>body,</hi> and there figures out what it reſents, and what it ſuffers by certain diſpoſitions which it gives it, as it were by ſo many <hi>Emblems</hi> and <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphorical pictures,</hi> whether it doth it out of deſign, or be conſtrained to it by neceſſity. Thus, for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, angry people hold up their heads high, and commonly ſet both their hands on their ſides, becauſe holding the head high and taking up more room then before, is a <hi>Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorical</hi> expreſſion of the vain ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of a preſumptuous mind, and of the greatneſs which it falſly attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes to it ſelf: So a man that affirms any thing with much zeal and opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onativeneſſe,
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:60121:125"/>
commonly bends his fiſts, becauſe this action hath ſome Analogy and correſpondence with the eſtate in which the ſoul is. But it were unprofitable and endleſs to think to prove a thing ſo clear and certain, by enumerating all our paſſions; wherefore ſuppoſing it ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther true, we ſay (and I think with much colour of Reaſon) that in all griefs and ſadneſſes, when the ſoul flyes ſome external evil, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiders it as external, it makes the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of the outward parts fly towards the inward, becauſe ſuch a motion as ſhews that it deſires from all ſides to enter into its ſelf, thereby to eſcape that evil which comes unto it from without, is moſt proper to repreſent to the life the deſire which it then hath, and the condition it is in: but on the contrary in the grief of Shame, becauſe it is touched with the horrour and hatred of an evil, that is within it ſelf, and is faſtened to its own ſubſtance, ſince it is nothing
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:60121:126"/>
elſe but its own imperfection, it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not better expreſs this horrour and hatred, then by violently thruſting forth the blood and ſpirits from within to the outward parts, as if it would baniſh them from us, ſince that indeed it is an eſtate that hath ſome Analogy with this corporal motion, and that it would if it could, baniſh it ſelf, and go out of its ſelf, by that means to fly from the vice which it finds it is defiled with. Moreover <hi>Shame</hi> dilates the ſpirits and the blood, and ſheds them upon the face more ſubtilly then any other paſſion, becauſe it proceeds from a moſt ſpiritual conception, to wit, from the conception of a diſhoneſt thing, and that the more ſpiritual im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions have alſo more quick and ſuddain effects. To this effuſion of the blood and ſpirits, contributes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo perhaps after another ſort, the contempt which in ſhame the ſoul hath of its ſelf; for ſeeing that then when it is moſt careful to preſerve
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:60121:126"/>
and defend us (as for example in Fear and in Affliction) it doth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinarily contract and keep them within, to ſtrengthen it ſelf the more; it may be, on the contrary, when it hates, and thinks it ſelf as it were unworthy of its own care, it doth by a natural motion remit much of that ſtraining, which holds the ſpirits thus united and collected, and gives them more liberty to ſpread themſelves, and to carry the blood along with them. But if this contribute nothing at all to it, the firſt reaſon that we give, is methinks ſufficient to clear this <hi>Problem;</hi> for though for the moſt part we do not bluſh, if we do not think our ſelves really in fault: yet ſometimes a ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumny makes us bluſh; and ſome may wonder that it ſhould be ſo, ſince then the ſoul, one would think, can not be troubled with any remorſe nor with any ſenſe of its own im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perfection. To this I anſwer, that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> truth we cannot have a true remor
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:60121:127"/>
of faults, which we have not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted; but as he which hath for ſome time held his eyes fixt upon a deep precipice, into which it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible he ſhould fall, yet cannot chooſe but tremble out of a vain ſhadow of fear that this image gives him: So he that hath great horrour for ſome fault which he is falſly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed of, according as he hath his mind bent upon the conſideration of the lewdneſs which is attributed to him, cannot chooſe, notwithſtanding the clear teſtimony of his own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience and of Reaſon, but be ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized many times with a vain ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of remorſe, which makes a bluſh mount into his face, ere his ſoul hath had time to think better on it.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="44" type="problem">
            <pb n="185" facs="tcp:60121:127"/>
            <head>
               <hi>PROB. 44.</hi> What is the reaſon that when we bluſh, it appears eſpecially in the fore-head?</head>
            <p>IS it not becauſe the fore-head is the <hi>whiteſt</hi> part of the face, and moſt free from natural redneſs, and conſequently moſt apt to make that more lively appear, which ſhame im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prints in it? Or elſe the blood which ſhame brings into the face, doth it not appear chiefly in the fore-head, becauſe the skin thereof is extream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>thin</hi> and <hi>delicate,</hi> as one may eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perceive by ſo many little wrink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, which Horrour, Diſcontent, Admiration or Anger do make in it, and becauſe it is free from <hi>hair,</hi> which in the other parts of the face may in ſome ſort hinder us for per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving ſo well the impreſſions which come into it from within? Or elſe,
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:60121:128"/>
if the conceit of thoſe that ſay, that in ſhame the ſoul ſends the blood into the face to cover it therewith, as with a veil, muſt take place; may we not ſay, that it ſends it eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly into the fore-head, becauſe it is the part moſt <hi>expoſed</hi> to the <hi>view</hi> of of him that cenſures us: ſeeing that when we ſpeak to men, we are wont to look them in the fore-head: Or elſe do not the ſpirits in ſpreading themſelves, make the blood eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly come under the skin of the fore-head, for that it is the <hi>higheſt</hi> part of the face, and that it is their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to <hi>aſcend</hi> as much as they can, as ſoon as the ſoul lets go her hold by which ſhe keeps them in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy?</p>
         </div>
         <div n="45" type="problem">
            <pb n="187" facs="tcp:60121:128"/>
            <head>
               <hi>PROB. 45.</hi> What is the reaſon that praiſes make a man bluſh?</head>
            <p>IS it not becauſe he that is much commended, feels many times that the exceſs of praiſes which are given to him, do puff him up whether he will or no with a little pride, and tickle him with a pleaſure that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves and as it were ſhakes all his gravity and firmneſs: So that he bluſhes not at the praiſes, but at the weakneſs he finds in himſelf and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covers to others? Truly that which ſhews that it may be thus, is, that we ſee thoſe which are moſt ſubject to bluſh when they hear themſelves praiſed, are commonly ſuch perſons as have indeed a ſincere goodneſs, but have not a ſoul really great; for a great ſoul is not puft up nor ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated at the praiſes it receives, any
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:60121:129"/>
more than the Sea is encreaſed or heightened by the water of Rivers that run into it. But it may be too all their redneſs proceeds not from <hi>Shame,</hi> but comes partly from an extream <hi>pleaſure</hi> they take to hear themſelves praiſed; for pleaſure alſo diffuſes the ſpirits and gives ſome colour to the face. Or elſe that on the one ſide, an honeſt and good ſoul hath not alwayes the courage, generouſly to reject the falſe praiſes that are given it, becauſe it loves glory; but that, on the other ſide, becauſe of its goodneſs, it bluſheth at the fault it commits in not reſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them, and in taking to it ſelf by this complacence an honour which is not its due. Or elſe, is it not out of extream <hi>Humility</hi> that a man bluſhes, in hearing himſelf praiſed for that he doth not at all believe that he is maſter of thoſe perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which are attributed to him, and that the praiſes given him, ſhow him what he ought to be, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:60121:129"/>
do only quicken the ſenſe which he hath of his imperfections? Or elſe, is it becauſe he that highly commends us, makes every one look on us the more, and doth in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner draw us out of obſcurity by this glory which he procures us, and that then we bluſh not at our glory, but rather becauſe we apprehend that our faults will appear the more in this great light which it ſets us in, and that it doth as well illuſtrate our blemiſhes as our perfections, and renders them the more remarkable? Here poſſibly ſome may ſay to me, if the bluſhing of ſhame proceeds only from the ſenſe which we have of our imperfection, as you have eſtabliſhed it in another <hi>Problem,</hi> to what purpoſe is it that our faults are objected to us by others to make us bluſh, and what is the reaſon that it contributes thereto? I anſwer, that it is becauſe the judgement of others doth alwayes confirm ours, and therefore if we think that another
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:60121:130"/>
blames and condemns a fault which we have committed, this belief of his doth more ſtrengthen the opinion which we had of it before, and doth more lively manifeſt the uglineſs of it.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="46" type="problem">
            <head>
               <hi>PROB. 46.</hi> What is the reaſon that a man laughs more at a pleaſant jeſt, or a merry tale, when he himſelf that tells it, doth not laugh?</head>
            <p>IS it not becauſe then he doth not ſeem to have the deſign which he hath, I mean, that he ſeems as if he would tell ſomething ſerious and of importance, whereas he only tells ſome trifle, and that our mind takes pleaſure in this deceit? But why doth it take more delight in this <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit,</hi> then it would have done in ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the naked <hi>truth?</hi> Is it not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in diſcovering it thus through a
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:60121:130"/>
lye, that is tranſparent and eaſily penetrable, it ſtill ſomewhat exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſeth its nobleſt faculty, the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and gives to it ſelf ſome proof of its ſufficiency and light? Or elſe is it becauſe a ridiculous thing ſpoken in a cold and ſerious tone, <hi>ſurprizeth</hi> us the more, becauſe we did not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to ſee it in this form, and under this appearance, and ſo it is proper to cauſe <hi>laughter,</hi> which muſt ariſe from a being <hi>ſurprized,</hi> whereas he that laughs whileſt he tells a merry ſtory, doth as it were <hi>threaten</hi> us and give us <hi>warning</hi> before hand, ſo that he doth not <hi>ſurprize</hi> us at all? But why muſt laughter ariſe from a <hi>ſurprize?</hi> Is it, as ſome ſay, becauſe it proceeds from <hi>Admiration,</hi> which is raiſed chiefly by a <hi>novelty?</hi> Or elſe, is it becauſe that which makes us laugh, is alwayes ſo vain, that if our minds could conſider it a little at leiſure, it would not find in it any ſubject of contentment? Or elſe, do we not laugh, when he that
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:60121:131"/>
tells us any merry thing laughs much at it, becauſe he ſeems to us as if he commended himſelf; and that other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe that which he ſayes, ſeems to be leſs pleaſant, and leſs apt to cauſe laughter, when we ſee he helps it for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward by beginning to laugh firſt? Or elſe laſtly, is it becauſe he which tells a merry paſſage without laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, appears to have ſome politeneſs, and with all gravity of manners: So that as he appears a more honeſt man, ſo likewiſe whatever he ſaith, hath more of grace in his mouth, and delights us the more, whereas if he laughs too much, he appears only a <hi>Bouffon,</hi> and by this means whatever he ſaies, though never ſo good, loſes more then half its grace and beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty?</p>
         </div>
         <div n="47" type="problem">
            <pb n="193" facs="tcp:60121:131"/>
            <head>
               <hi>PROB. 47.</hi> Why do we laugh in ſeeing a thing very ill-favoured, ſince that which delights the mind, one would think ought to have in it ſome perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction?</head>
            <p>TO eſcape this difficulty which is not ſo ſlight, but that many ancient Philoſophers, and Oratours have laboured to little purpoſe for the clearing of it: may we not ſay in the firſt place, that a man doth not laugh at ugly things, when they are wholly and altogether ſuch, ſince that on the contrary we do then call them horrible, and fly from them as things odious; but that moſt commonly a man laughs at ſome trifling and ſlight grace mixt with their deformity? as for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, it is clear that the habit of a <hi>Bouffon</hi> though it be deformed, hath
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:60121:132"/>
many times I know not what grace that may tickle the imagination; But what is the reaſon this remnant of grace, and this vain and ſlight ray of goodneſs that may be found in ſome ill-favoured things, makes one laugh more then a thing reaſonably well made would do? May it not poſſibly be becauſe in a thing ill made, the defects that it hath, may by their oppoſition render in ſome ſort more pleaſant, and more grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to the fancy, that little grace which ſhines in it? Or elſe rather, is it not becauſe generally every grace or prettineſs that makes one laugh, either in handſome or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>handſome things, ſhould be alwayes vain and ſlight, and not ſolid, as we ſaid in the foregoing <hi>Problem?</hi> But why ſhould it be ſo? Is it not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſolid graces chiefly affecting the <hi>Judgement,</hi> and approving them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to us by our diſcretion and underſtanding, do produce a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure though <hi>greater,</hi> yet more <hi>ſober,</hi>
               <pb n="195" facs="tcp:60121:132"/>
and ſuch as hath ſomething of <hi>grace</hi> in it; but a vain and ſlight grace, affecting eſpecially the <hi>imagination,</hi> and being chiefly liked by our weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, fills us alſo with a joy that manifeſts ſomewhat of weakneſs and childiſhneſs, and takes from us all gravity, and makes us not able to hold our countenance, which is that we call laughter, and therefore they ſay it is a ſign of folly in thoſe that are much ſubject to it? Or elſe do not things that are very ill-favoured delight thoſe that look upon them becauſe they are <hi>rare</hi> as well as things perfect and excellent? Or elſe is it not that as our ſoul loves to have its <hi>Ideas</hi> perfect and intirely expreſſive of their objects, for this reaſon it is pleaſed more in conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing things very ill done, then mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derately well, becauſe theſe firſt do perfect and accompliſh the <hi>Idea</hi> which it hath of uglineſs, and fills up its knowledge to the full every way; whereas thoſe that are moderately
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:60121:133"/>
well done can give it only imperfect notions? Or elſe do not objects that are very ill done, by giving us an <hi>Idea</hi> of extream imperfection, fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh us with an eaſie way to draw from thence the image of extream perfection, and to render it more lively in us; ſo that they very much inſtructing our mind, it delights it ſelf to conſider them, not for any reaſon that perſwades it that it ſhould do ſo, but by a natural and blind motion that makes it ſearch in it to perfect its knowledge, and to inſtruct its ſelf? Or elſe, do we not love to ſee things very ill done, to ſhew our abilities in condemning them? But what is the reaſon we cannot as well ſhow them in praiſing thoſe that are moderately well done? Is it not becauſe every body knows at firſt ſight that which is extream, and findes more difficulty in that which is moderate? Or becauſe, as we ſaid in another <hi>Problem,</hi> it is eaſier to blame then to commend?
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:60121:133"/>
Or elſe, do we not delight to expreſs the rules of good, whereof we have all ſome <hi>Theory,</hi> rather on the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of an ill made thing, then of one that is well made, becauſe a thing well made contains them in its ſelf, and ſo ſeems to ſuggeſt them to us, and to leave nothing to our inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, whereas when we expreſs them by blaming a deformed thing, we ſeem to invent them our ſelves? It is probable indeed that fools do it for this reaſon, becauſe they think they cannot manifeſt their wit bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then by detracting and finding fault. Or elſe, to conclude, is it not in many meerly an odd fanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical and childiſh humour to like a thing that is deformed, and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider it with ſatisfaction, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we ſee that all fools laugh more heartily at monſtrous and extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant things, and that good and diſcreet men ſmiling only at theſe, do laugh more heartily at things ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent and handſome, as at a bold
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:60121:134"/>
and neat reply, at a pretty compen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious way by which ſome one hath brought about his deſires, or at ſome gentleneſs that ſhines in his actions, at a gracefull motion of the body, at the fit proportions and corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondence of all the parts of an Hiſtory, or Fable, at a paſſion naturally expreſt, or ſome ſuch like thing?</p>
         </div>
         <div n="48" type="problem">
            <head>
               <hi>PROB. 48.</hi> What is the reaſon that Man being inclined to flatter himſelf, doth nevertheleſs aggravate his own imperfection above the truth; as for example, in ſaying there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but folly, and injuſtice, and ingratitude in the world?</head>
            <p>FIrſt, it may be ſaid on this ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, that in truth man attains moſt commonly to a mediocrity of <hi>wiſdome,</hi> ſeeing there are ſcarce any
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:60121:134"/>
that have not the uſe of common ſence; and that to ſpeak civilly, he alſo attains ordinarily to a moderate and common <hi>Virtue,</hi> ſeeing there are few that become unnatural: but that for all this; when we come to compare this wiſdome, and this or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary virtue of men with a ſtate of <hi>Perfection</hi> much greater, which rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon gives us the <hi>Idea</hi> of, we finde our ſelves forced to name them <hi>Vice</hi> and <hi>Folly,</hi> juſt as we call foul linnen black, in comparing it with that which hath been new waſhed, or with ſnow, though it be white in it ſelf and in compariſon with Ink; for every mean ſtate is an evil in regard of an excellency which is much above it as truly as it is a good, in regard of that which is beneath it. Now our ſoul is ſo much the more apt to look upon the good that is in it with diſdain, becauſe it finds it is born for a ſtate of perfection much more eminent; and thus though an <hi>Artiſan</hi> be to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:60121:135"/>
if he perfectly underſtand any mechanick art; yet wheen we judge of a <hi>Prince,</hi> we make no ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of ſuch an ability, if he hath no other, becauſe we conceive he is born for much greater things. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, our ſoul doth often attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to it ſelf more imperfection then it hath, becauſe the good alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy gotten ſlips out of our memory, and doth not ordinarily preſent it ſelf to our minds, as that which is wanting doth; the reaſon of it is, becauſe the ſoul alwayes withdraws its ſight from the things about which it hath no more to do, as on the contrary, it fixeth it upon thoſe that give it ſome occaſion of deſire and endeavour. In the third place, a man doth not think there is any need of aggravating the <hi>good</hi> that is in man, and believes rather it would be a thing very hurtful: but on the contrary, he thinks it is very profit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to aggravate his <hi>Vice</hi> and <hi>Folly,</hi> which is alſo very true, but yet to
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:60121:135"/>
ſome certain degrees only; for to give to man too low conceptions of himſelf, and ſuch as are like him, is an abating of his Courage and quenching of his Emulation. But however hereby, ſometimes the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfection of man ſeems to us to be greater then it is; for to conſider, firſt, that which regards his <hi>under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding,</hi> oftentimes when we ſpeak of many fools, we ſay with a ſerious tone, as if we deſired to be believed, and to have it paſs for an <hi>Axiome,</hi> that they have no more judgement then beaſts; nay in aggravating their folly, we think ſometimes that beaſts have more: though if we conſider it aright and according to the truth of the buſineſs, a man that is the moſt void of wit, gives, at but open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his eyes, and by his firſt geſtures, and by his firſt looks, tokens of a greater judgement then all beaſts put together: There are alſo Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers that have contributed to the making of the generality of men be
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:60121:136"/>
ſo ſeverely condemned; for whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it were, that herein, they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes had for their end ſome profit that might be reaped by it, or that at ſometimes they might be put upon it for ſome other reaſons, they have one after another aggravated his folly in ſuch a manner as if they had a minde to take from him even com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſenſe. In this there is too much ſeverity and bitterneſs; for we ſhould not conſider only the <hi>faults</hi> of people, but alſo the <hi>good</hi> that is in them, and then we ſhall finde that in many things they have the firſt notions moſt quick and moſt pure, though they know not how to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of them exactly, and after a ſubtile manner: we ſhould not alſo impute as ſo many <hi>faults</hi> of their <hi>underſtanding,</hi> all the <hi>weakneſſes</hi> of their <hi>imagination,</hi> and take them in the worſt ſenſe that can be; for all things appear bad to him that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiders them not with <hi>candor</hi> and <hi>equity;</hi> and he that is reſolved ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:60121:136"/>
to ſee any thing but bad, makes ſhort work, by caſting himſelf into an exceſs of rigour, and turning away his eyes from that which is laudable in them; but by this means he depraves himſelf, and not that which he conſiders after this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; the ſame alſo happens from the aggravating of mens vice. But to diſcover yet another cauſe that makes us thus defame our nature many times beyond the truth, it may further be ſaid, that every one thinks to gain ſomething to his own ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage in vilifying mankind, and the generality of men; for if he hath any perfection, he is more willing to perſwade himſelf, that it comes to him from what he hath <hi>particular</hi> and proper, then to believe that it proceeds from what he hath in <hi>common</hi> with others; the reaſon whereof is, becauſe what he hath in particular, is more his own; and on the contrary if he hath any imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, he alſo findes ſome comfort
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:60121:137"/>
in the diſpleaſure it doth him, by attributing it to the general nature of man, rather then to the fault of his own individual nature: But eſpecially wicked men are put upon a like deſign by the like motive; for, that they may finde out ſome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe, they endeavour to include all others in the ſame fault, which they themſelves are guilty of: they ſcrape together therefore what ever is moſt ugly in our life, and make it much worſe in expreſſing it, and in giving ill interpretations of it; and when we hear them thus aggravate much beyond the truth that which is ill in us, we contradict them not, as well becauſe as I told you, that we think it is <hi>profitable</hi> it ſhould be ſo, as alſo becauſe it ſeems to be <hi>Humility</hi> to conſent to an accuſation in which we are comprized; and on the contrary that it is <hi>arrogance</hi> and <hi>preſumption</hi> to oppoſe it. From hence then ariſe many ſayings and expreſſions, which import that rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:60121:137"/>
can do nothing or very little on the mind of man, that there is nothing but injuſtice and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude to be ſeen in the world, and ſuch other like things, which are contrary to other ſayings that we have at other times, which are as much beyond the truth: for it is not more impoſſible that heaven ſhould fall, then it is impoſſible that Juſtice and Reaſon ſhould ceaſe to have very much power upon the minds of men, and that they ſhould not ſuffer themſelves to be bent and affected with this ſame Reaſon, as their particular intereſt. Pirats, robbers upon the high-way, poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners, and the moſt deteſtable of men, do not make any exception againſt this rule; and though Choler be the moſt wild and ſavage of all our paſſions, and though it ſtir what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is moſt baſe and evil in us; yet that which firſt kindles it is an indignity, which is nothing elſe but injuſtice: and therefore Poets that
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:60121:138"/>
are the Painters of the ordinary mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the ſoul, when they bring upon the ſtage one that talking to himſelf alone labours to animate himſelf with a violent rage, they make him inſiſt longer upon reaſons drawn from juſtice or injuſtice, then upon others drawn from profit; and not without cauſe; for if a man do only conclude in himſelf, that it is profitable for him to be angry, there would be nothing more cold then ſuch an inticement, and he would not for this obtain of himſelf to be angry in good earneſt; but if he be perſwaded that it is juſt he ſhould be ſo, this conſideration would without fail put fire into his ſoul as ſoon as ever he thinks of it, and will there kindle the flames of choler: Hence it comes that a thief, what want ſo ever he have of money, will not be angry that a man hath been ſo care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful as not to let him cut his purſe; for he cannot ſee in this any indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and he doth abſolutely want
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:60121:138"/>
the conſiderations of juſtice, which ought to begin the forming of choler in him. And as for the common ſayings by which we expreſs the want of gratitude, which we ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily ſee in men, they alſo do often ſurpaſs the truth; for if we conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it well, there is nothing more preſſing than a motion of gratitude, and experience ſhews ſufficient ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of it amongſt all ſorts of men. But to leave this diſcourſe, I will add, that becauſe there are few ſpirits ſo miſerable, as to endeavour to make themſelves more wicked then they are: Man, for that reaſon, knows not how inacceſſible the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity of vice is, and how impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble it would be for him to diſpoile himſelf of what ever there is good and laudable in his nature, and to go quite contrary to the rules of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; and that this makes him ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times have too ill an opinion of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and to paſs beyond the bounds of truth in blaming himſelf.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="49" type="problem">
            <pb n="208" facs="tcp:60121:139"/>
            <head>
               <hi>PROB. 49.</hi> What is the reaſon that according to the common ſaying of the Poets and of Ariſtotle himſelf in the ſecond book of his Politicks, Valiant and couragious perſons are moſt ſubject to love?</head>
            <p>IS it not becauſe courage and an inclination to Love have one and the ſame Original in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perament, namely heat of blood, which may be perceived in that the age wherein man is moſt couragious through the heat of his blood, is that wherein he is moſt inclined to Love? Or elſe, is it not becauſe Love is a paſſion which hath ſome beauty and nobleneſs, and that men truly cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious, as they have a more noble ſoul, ſo have they alſo a greater pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſion to all the Paſſions that have any ray of nobleneſs and beauty,
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:60121:139"/>
and proceed partly from a good principle? Indeed we ſee, that for this reaſon they are ſubject to ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, becauſe ambition hath ſome mixture of generoſity, and of the Love of that which is honeſt; and to Opinionativeneſs, becauſe it hath a ſhadow of conſtancy; but that on the contrary they are farther then other men from Avarice, Cruelty, and deſire of Revenge, becauſe theſe motions of the ſoul have not the leaſt footſteps of any nobleneſs and beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Now to ſhew that Love is a paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion which hath ſome nobleneſs and ſomething of praiſe-worthy, we may bring this reaſon, that (whatſoever ſome ſay that would decide this bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs by fine expreſſions, and have their jeſts paſs for Oracles) a true Lover doth in ſome ſort love beauty for it ſelf, and not only for the hope of a baſe and brutiſh pleaſure; for he not only humbles himſelf before the beloved object, as we humble our ſelves before a great man by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint,
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:60121:140"/>
and with repugnance, and to obtain ſome good of him, but he alſo takes pleaſure in this very act of ſubmiſſion, and the more he humbles himſelf with innocence and freeneſs, and without any deſign, the more this pleaſure increaſes in him, which is an infallible token that he makes this the end of part of his deſire: Juſtly therefore do the Poets call the exceſs of Love <hi>handſome fooleries;</hi> for though they be <hi>fooleries</hi> in that they chooſe their objects ill, they have ſome <hi>Beauty</hi> in that they denote in the ſoul where they are formed, ſome violent inclination to love <hi>perfection.</hi> Or elſe may we ſay, that even the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination to love perfection is the ſole motive and only fountain of true courage, ſo that if Love have in it any ray or ſpark thereof, it is no wonder that thoſe who have an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream high courage, are the more ſubject to it? Or elſe is it that it is an hard matter to reſiſt at once two contrary aſſaults, becauſe this ſeems
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:60121:140"/>
to require two contrary diſpoſitions of mind; and that for this reaſon they that have a ſoul ſtrong to reſiſt griefs and objects of terrour, are many times extraordinary weak againſt pleaſures and objects that conquer by flattering our ſenſes, amongſt which thoſe that cauſe Love are the moſt alluring? Certainly, it ſeems credible, when we conſider the great weakneſs with which men, the moſt famous for their courage, have yeild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to pleaſures of this kind. Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs, herein their courage was imperfect; for our ſoul ought not to be firme like <hi>Ice</hi> very hard frozen, which reſiſting the blows of hatchets, and bearing heavy burdens, yet makes leſs reſiſtance to a ſmall heat, and to a ray of the Sun, then the moſt weak things; but rather like to a <hi>Diamant</hi> which equally reſiſts all aſſaults: and as a ſword cuts alike on both ſides, ſo a perfect and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat courage ſhould be whetted on both ſides, and have as it were two
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:60121:141"/>
edges and two points to reſiſt equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Pleaſures</hi> and <hi>Pains;</hi> Or elſe, theſe two different parts of courage, which we now ſpeak of, have not at all any thing of contrary, and do ſpring rather from the ſame foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain: but as though the Viſual fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty hath one and the ſame ſpring, yet when we would collect it into one of the eyes, and there make it become more ſtrong, we do naturally ſhut the other: ſo our ſoul in uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting all its force towards ſome one ſide, remits in it other regards, and in avoiding with great care ſome kind of weakneſs, it falls more readily into others.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="50" type="problem">
            <head>
               <hi>PROB. 50.</hi> Whence comes that averſion to marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age of perſons too near?</head>
            <p>AS there is no queſtion but the condemning of Marriage be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:60121:141"/>
perſons too near, is leſs clear by reaſon, then the condemning of vices, which are formally the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of malice: ſo he that would infer from thence, that there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of <hi>nature</hi> in this, and that it is wholly a <hi>Civil</hi> conſtitution, and no more, will be deceived; ſince that the general inclination and opinion of men teſtifies the contrary; for a general opinion can never fail of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing true, at leaſt in part; and the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of beaſts cannot upon this ſubject be conſiderable to a man of judgement; for it were abſurd to think that beaſts ſhould reſpect an affinity which they know not; and he that ſhould ſay that laughter, ſhame, deſire of glory, deſire of knowledge and the like, are not na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural to <hi>Man,</hi> becauſe they are not natural to <hi>beaſts,</hi> would evidently make a ridiculous conſequence. And if men cannot give particular rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons why they diſapprove this ſort of marriages, and ſpecifie what they
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:60121:142"/>
finde inconvenient therein according to reaſon, we ought to think that for all that they ſee it in <hi>groſs</hi> and at a <hi>diſtance,</hi> as many times we ſee afar off an <hi>houſe,</hi> though we be not able to diſtinguiſh the <hi>dores, windows,</hi> and other parts of it. And by how much the leſs clear the reaſons of it are, ſo much the more reaſon have we to exerciſe our ſelves in the diſcovery of them in this <hi>Problem. Firſt</hi> then I ſhall ſay, that not only nature gives us a ſtrong inclination to love thoſe perſons which are very near us, and are members of the ſame family with us, (for of this no man that hath his ſenſes can doubt) but that it alſo makes us conſider them in ſome man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as we do our ſelves: This ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears in that if a man commends one that is very near us, we bluſh at it as if he commended us, and do out of humility deſire him to forbear, as if theſe praiſes were meant to us. This being ſo, as every one is natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally far from the folly into which
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:60121:142"/>
               <hi>Narciſſus</hi> fell, and is not capable of being touched with the love of his own beauty: by the ſame reaſon he naturally flyes from regarding with Paſſions like to thoſe of Lovers, the perſons for whom he hath an affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ſame nature and kind with that which he hath for himſelf; and this is a token of the ardour and truth of the Amity which he bears them; as on the contrary, if this Amity ſhould ceaſe to have the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities and properties of that which he bears to himſelf, it were a certain ſign that it had received diminution, and is not ſuch as nature requires it ſhould be. In the <hi>ſecond</hi> place, the reverence which Proximity gives to perſons that are of the ſame family, being an obligation ſo ſtraight and ſo natural, that the ancient <hi>Romans</hi> have named it <hi>Piety,</hi> and that every honeſt ſoul conſiders it as a <hi>ſacred</hi> thing; it proceeds from hence that a man deſires to ſee the degrees of it very diſtinct, and ſeparate, in ſeveral
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:60121:143"/>
perſons, to the end that it may the more exactly diſcharge the duties that belong unto it, and diſcern more clearly after what manner he ought to be affected towards each of them in particular; for he perceives that this knowledge would become much more obſcure by marriages that ſhould unite in one and the ſame perſon <hi>two</hi> of theſe degrees firſt, and afterwards <hi>three</hi> or <hi>four</hi> or more of them; and that in this caſe there would be requiſite much ſubtilty of wit to diſcern the obligation that ſhould ariſe from the mixture of theſe different or contrary obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. If beſides theſe general reaſons we ſhall need to alledge others, touching the different degrees of Proximity, firſt, to ſhew that reaſon prohibits marriage with thoſe men or women that are of our neareſt kindred to whom we owe reſpect, I ſhall alledge thoſe well-known ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, whoſe truth every one will confeſs,
<q>
                  <pb n="217" facs="tcp:60121:143"/>
                  <l>Non bene conveniunt nec in unâ ſede morantur</l>
                  <l>Majeſtas &amp; Amor.</l>
               </q>
That is,
<q>
                  <l>A real Love and Majeſty,</l>
                  <l>Can hardly in one boſom lie.</l>
               </q>
Whereupon I add, that if Reaſon forbids us to uſe too familiar <hi>careſſes</hi> towards thoſe perſons I ſpake of, it doth likewiſe forbid us to deſire to unite our ſelves to them in ſuch a manner of union as above all others produces Familiarity, and doth ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily deface and aboliſh Reſpect and Inequality: I mean that Union wherein marriage conſiſts. It re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains then only to ſpeak of that marriage which may be imagined be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Brother</hi> and <hi>Siſter,</hi> in regard of which the preceding reaſon can have no place, ſeeing they owe one another no <hi>Reſpect,</hi> but meerly <hi>Ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</hi> It is well known what a great Perſonage diſcourſing on this ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject,
<pb n="218" facs="tcp:60121:144"/>
hath ſaid, to wit, that the affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction which would ariſe from ſuch a marriage, as being produced from the concourſe of two ſuch potent conſiderations, would be ſomewhat too ardent. But, for my part, I do not think he ſhould have taken it thus, nay I conceive, that in ſome ſort it ought to have been taken quite contrary. But before I explain my ſelf more clearly, I will ſay that in every <hi>ſpecies</hi> of the Paſſions, there are of them that are contrary to one another, and that expell one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and are incompatible, inſtead of increaſing and mutually aſſiſting each other. Thus, for example, there are contrary <hi>Joyes;</hi> for there is a certain <hi>Brutiſh Joy,</hi> which is ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compatible with another <hi>Spiritual Joy,</hi> that when this laſt poſſeſſes the ſoul, the other muſt neceſſarily give place; and hence it comes to paſs that many that feel within themſelves moſt perfect pleaſures, and ſuch as are very ſpiritual, have in their
<pb n="219" facs="tcp:60121:144"/>
countenance an ayr of ſadneſs, very far from having their eyes cheerful, and thoſe other marks that accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany lower and baſer pleaſures. Thus a <hi>ſadneſs</hi> that raiſes in a man a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe which he intends to make upon Humane vanities and miſery, being very far from encreaſing that which the loſs of a ſuit at Law, or the like, hath begotten in him, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſhes it, and inſtead of over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charging his ſpirit, comforts it: Thus <hi>Grief</hi> for a <hi>diſgrace</hi> far from augmenting the weakneſs into which our ſoul is caſt through a corporal grief, ſerves many times to take from her the ſenſe of it. In a word, it were eaſie to ſhew, that there are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo thus <hi>Angers, Fears, Loves,</hi> Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, as I may ſo ſay, one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and incompatible. This being thus premiſed, I ſay, that the Paſſion which we properly call <hi>Love,</hi> as ariſing from a <hi>bodily</hi> pleaſure, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing altogether <hi>ſportful</hi> and <hi>wanton,</hi> and an enemy to all <hi>ſerious</hi> thoughts
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:60121:145"/>
and conſiderations, according to the ſaying of Poets and of Lovers them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, cannot but be of a nature more contrary to <hi>Fraternal Love,</hi> which is altogether <hi>Spiritual, Holy,</hi> and <hi>Serious,</hi> and flows only from <hi>Reaſon.</hi> That for this cauſe ſo far are they from encreaſing one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, it is certain that That muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily looſen all the bonds of This, and that as we perceive that it looſens them, and that we have a very great inclination to keep them ſtill faſt and united, and ſuch as na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture would have them to be, we feel alſo for this cauſe a repugnance, by reaſon of that which thus looſens them. And herein we do for all the world, as it a man ſhould go about to make us laugh heartily, by making ſome ſerious and profound contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation of Philoſophie to encreaſe the pleaſure of it; for we ſhould ſoon perceive that quite contrary theſe two ſorts of Joy cannot agree together, much leſs augment one
<pb n="221" facs="tcp:60121:145"/>
another; and that it were an extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vigance to think they ſhould. This is all I have to ſay upon this ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="51" type="problem">
            <head>
               <hi>PROB. 51.</hi> Whence proceed the exceſſive heats of the Moneth of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> and the other effects which are attributed to the Dog-ſtar?</head>
            <p>I Have much reaſon to fear that I ſhall be accounted raſh, if I dare to queſtion the power which is gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally granted to the <hi>Dog-ſtar:</hi> but on the other ſide alſo, I conceive that if herein I am raſh, I ought to be pardoned, in conſideration that I undertake by this means to maintain familiar and <hi>known</hi> cauſes againſt <hi>occult ones;</hi> For as in <hi>Law,</hi> the cauſe of <hi>Liberty</hi> againſt <hi>Servitude</hi> is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes favourable, I conceive like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe that in diſputes of <hi>Philoſophie,</hi>
               <pb n="222" facs="tcp:60121:146"/>
the reaſons which are drawn from <hi>known</hi> and <hi>familiar</hi> things, ought to be favoured againſt all thoſe that conſiſt in <hi>Sympathie,</hi> or in <hi>ſecret in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence,</hi> or in <hi>ſpecifick</hi> qualities, and yet no doubt we ought to have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to theſe laſt: but it is only as people that are like to be drowned, catch at thorns, and embrace them in that preſſing need: that is to ſay, when we find no other means to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver our ſelves from a difficulty: for ſo long as there is any other means of eſcaping it, if it be but any thing tolerable, this muſt needs be very bad. But to come to the preſent buſineſs, Thoſe which have conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that the heat of the Moneth of <hi>Auguſt</hi> is greater then that of the Moneths of <hi>June</hi> and <hi>July,</hi> although in them the Sun be nearer to us, and ſtrikes us with leſs oblique rayes, and makes longer dayes, have thence in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred, that this exceſs of heat pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from the influence of a Star which is called the <hi>Dog,</hi> to which
<pb n="223" facs="tcp:60121:146"/>
they have alſo given other ill quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: for this (if we will believe what they ſay of it) is the cauſe that in <hi>Auguſt</hi> the heat of the Sun is more malignant, even when it is no greater then in the other Moneths of Summer; that many creatures, and eſpecially Dogs, do then run mad; and that it is then more dangerous to go into the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; and that ſickneſſes are more frequent and greater; and that men feel ſome particular weakneſſes in all the parts of the body. But all things well conſidered, it will be found, that there is nothing in all this that ſhould oblige us to attribute ſecret and particular vertues to the Dog-ſtar, and to leave the large field of known and ordinary cauſes; For firſt I do not ſee why we ſhould wonder, that the Sun is hotter in <hi>Auguſt</hi> then in <hi>July,</hi> though it be true that in <hi>Auguſt</hi> he regards us ſomewhat more obliquely, and that the dayes are ſhotter; the reaſon of
<pb n="224" facs="tcp:60121:147"/>
it is, becauſe the Earth having been exceedingly dryed by the former heats, is more apt to be violently ſcorched, as we ſee that any dry thing ſet before a leſſer fire, receives a more violent heat, then a thing that is moiſt from a fire that is much greater. That this reaſon is perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, there is an experience that me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks proves it plainly enough; it is, that though at noon the Sun be nearer to us, and caſt more direct rayes on us then he doth any time after: yet thoſe that travel in Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, do perceive a more violent heat two or three hours after-noon, then at noon it ſelf; the reaſon whereof is, that at noon the moiſture of the morning is not ſo well dryed up, either on the graſs, or the air, or the earth, as it is a while after. This example is ſo put to the ſubject I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply it to, the Queſtion in hand, that there cannot be found any difference in it, and it may ſerve well enough to prove what I ſay; for as ſomebody
<pb n="225" facs="tcp:60121:147"/>
hath well obſerved, the images of the <hi>Four Seaſons</hi> of the year, are to be ſeen in one only Day, in which the <hi>Morning</hi> by its moiſture repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents the <hi>Spring: Noon</hi> and ſometime after is like the <hi>Summer Solſtice,</hi> and the two Moneths that follow it; the <hi>Evening</hi> to the <hi>Autum:</hi> and the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rival of <hi>Night</hi> to the arrival of <hi>Winter.</hi> Now as this reaſon renders the heat of <hi>Auguſt</hi> greater, it is manifeſt that withall it renders it neceſſarily more malign. But yet if it be objected that it is often more malignant then that of other Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths, without being more violent: I anſwer, that this doth not yet force us to fly to a ſecret cauſe; for if it were neceſſary to attribute this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular malignity to the influence of ſome Star, it would follow alſo, that we muſt give influences to ſome other Star, for to render a reaſon of the particular malignity of the Sun in <hi>March,</hi> which as having a very feeble hear, one would think, ſhould
<pb n="226" facs="tcp:60121:148"/>
not be able to be hurtful, and to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gender ſo eaſily rhumes and catarrhs. But, to ſay the truth, theſe two ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral malignities are the effects only of the courſe of the year, and of two contrary extreams; for the <hi>Sun</hi> in <hi>March</hi> hath ſomething of malign and dangerous, by reaſon of the great humidity it meets with in the earth, nay and in our brain, on which it acts ſo weakly, that inſtead of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving, it only dilates it. And on the contrary, the Sun in <hi>Auguſt</hi> is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary hurtful through an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of dryneſs which it finds in the earth, after it hath endured the heats of a great part of Summer, and in our bodies, which the ſame heats have dryed. It is this dryneſs which at this time diſpoſes beaſts to mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, though indeed Dogs run mad not only in <hi>Auguſt,</hi> but alſo very often in the Moneths of <hi>June</hi> and <hi>July,</hi> or <hi>September,</hi> which need not for this borrow any thing of the <hi>Dog-ſtar.</hi> From this exceſſive dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="227" facs="tcp:60121:148"/>
proceeds likewiſe the weakneſs which we feel then in our bodies, and the diſpoſition which this ſeaſon puts us in, to divers maladies; for every extream is alwayes nigh an evil, and eaſily falls into one, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is one it ſelf: To conclude, if thoſe that ſwim in this Moneth, do find that the waters are more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wholſom then they were before, a man may ſay, it is becauſe their more <hi>pure</hi> and <hi>ſubtile</hi> parts have been ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haled by the precedent heats, and that what remains is <hi>groſs</hi> and <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pure.</hi> And I do not ſee that there is any thing in this, we ſhould need to attribute to the <hi>Dog-ſtar,</hi> more then in the other things we mentioned.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
